[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The term ‘endonuclease’ refers to cutting the DNA sequence from ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) only within the polynucleotide chain, not at the ends",
            "b) the ends of the chain",
            "c) anywhere in the chain",
            "d) exactly in the middle of the chain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cleavage is done within the polynucleotide chain and not at the ends. The enzyme which cuts the sequence at the ends is known as exonuclease."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The restriction endonuclease is having a defence mechanism in the bacterial system against foreign DNA such as viruses. But how it is able to protect its own DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By methylation of bacterial DNA by restriction enzyme",
            "b) By methylation of foreign DNA by restriction enzyme",
            "c) By phosphorylation of bacterial DNA by restriction enzyme",
            "d) By phosphorylation of foreign DNA  by restriction enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bacterial DNA is methylated by restriction enzyme and thus now it is not recognized by the restriction endonuclease. Thus methylation prevents the restriction endonuclease from cutting its own DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Even after replication, how the modified DNA remains protected?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It remains protected because of conservative mode of replication",
            "b) It remains protected because of semi-conservative mode of replication",
            "c) The mode of replication has no role to play in the protection",
            "d) It is again modified after replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of the semi-conservative mode of replication, one of the DNA strands remain methylated even after replication. One methylated strand is sufficient for providing protection against cleavage by a restriction endonuclease."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "How many classes of restriction enzymes are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Three classes of restriction enzymes are there, I, II and III. These classes are having different characteristics such as the site of cleavage on the basis of the recognition sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Type II cuts the sequence in the following way __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Within the recognition sequence",
            "b) At 100-1000 nucleotides away from the recognition sequence",
            "c) At 27-30 nucleotides away from the recognition sequence",
            "d) It cuts randomly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recognition sequence is the set of nucleotides which are identified by the enzyme and then it cleaves. In class II, the cleavage is done within the recognition sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "After cleaving the sequence, the nature of the ends created by the type II endonuclease is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ends created are always single stranded",
            "b) The ends created are always double stranded",
            "c) Either the ends are single stranded or they are double stranded",
            "d) One end is single stranded and one end is double stranded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Either the ends are both double stranded or are both single stranded. The double stranded ends are blunt ends whereas the single stranded ends are sticky ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "A sequence is having two ends, 5’ and 3’. Which of the following statements is correct regarding the nature of the ends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The 5’ end is having hydroxyl group",
            "b) The 5’ end is having phosphate group",
            "c) The 3’ end is having phosphate group",
            "d) Any group can be present at any end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 5’ end is having a phosphate group. As in a DNA sequence, the 5’ end is characterized by phosphate group and the 3’ end is characterized by a hydroxyl group."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "The recognition sequence for BamHI is 5’ G|GATCC 3’. The ‘|’ represents the cutting site. What can be inferred about the ends from it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ends created are double stranded",
            "b) The single stranded end is 5’ in nature",
            "c) The single stranded end is 3’ in nature",
            "d) To decide about the nature of the ends more information is needed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The blunt ends created can be joined by the enzyme responsible for ligation such as DNA ligase. It is not necessary to have sticky or single stranded ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "The recognition sequence of Sau3A is 5’ |GATC 3’ and that for DpnI is 5’ GA|TC 3’. Which of the statements is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ends created by both the enzymes are compatible",
            "b) The ends created by both the enzymes are not-compatible",
            "c) The ends created by DpnI are single stranded",
            "d) The ends created by Sau3A are single stranded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The other strand is just complementary to it and can be written in the following way:\n5’ G|GATCC 3’\n3’ CCTAG|G 5’\nAfter cleavage, the sequences are represented as:\n5’ G 3’            5’ GATCC 3’\n3’ CCTAG 5’             3’ G 5’\nThus, we can see that the ends generated are single stranded at 5’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The recognition sequence is at times palindromic in nature. Which of the following statements is correct with respect to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The molecules which are cut by the same enzyme, anneal only if the sequence is palindromic in nature",
            "b) When the molecules are cleaved by the same enzyme and the recognition sequence is palindromic in nature, there is no effect on annealing",
            "c) There are increased chances of annealing if the recognition sequence is palindromic in nature",
            "d) The term ‘palindromic’ can be used whether the sequence is read from 5’ to 3’ or 3’ to 5’"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Though the recognition sequence is the same, the ends are not compatible. It is so because both the enzymes leave double stranded ends and thus can’t be ligated."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "If all the nucleotides are present with equal frequencies and at random, what are the chances of having a particular four nucleotide long motif?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/256",
            "b) 1/64",
            "c) 1/16",
            "d) 1/8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term palindromic can be used only when a sequence is read along the same polarity ie either 5’ to 3’ or 3’ to 5’. When the recognition sequence is palindromic in nature, there are increased chances of annealing because now there are increased orientations. If the sequence is non-palindromic in nature, then also annealing would take place but in fewer orientations."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Isoschizomers are defined as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) enzymes having same recognition sequence and always cutting at the same site",
            "b) enzymes having same recognition sequence and always cutting at different site",
            "c) enzymes having different recognition site and cutting at the same site",
            "d) enzymes having same recognition site and they may or may not cut at the same site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Isoschizomers are the enzymes which are having same recognition sequence but they necessarily don’t cut at the same site. DraI and AhaIII both recognize and cleave at TTT|AAA, whereas on the other hand, ApaI cuts at GGGCC|C and Bspl20I cuts at G|GGCCC."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Isocaudomers are defined as the enzymes which recognize different sequence but generate same ends. Which of the following pairs of enzymes can be termed as isocuadomers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DpnI (GA|TC) and Sau3A (|GATC)",
            "b) BamHI (G|GATCC) and Sau3A (|GATC)",
            "c) DpnI (GA|TC) and BglII (A|GATCT)",
            "d) XbaI (T|CTAGA) and BamHI (G|GATCC)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: BamHI on cleavage leaves GATC as the single stranded end and the same end is left by Sau3A as double stranded, though there recognition sequences are different. The other options don’t satisfy the condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The specificity of an enzyme is affected by the concentration of buffer used. This phenomenon is termed as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) star activity",
            "b) specificity elevation",
            "c) concentration gradient effects",
            "d) diamond activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As concentration of buffer is varied, the specificity of an enzyme is lost and this phenomenon is termed as star activity. By loss of specificity we mean that, instead of a particular sequence, a particular set of sequences can be identified."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct with respect to a unit of an enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One unit of enzyme is defined as the amount of enzyme required to digest 1miligram of standard DNA in a specific time of 1hr and under given temperature conditions",
            "b) The amount of enzyme required doesn’t vary with the number of sites present in the DNA",
            "c)  If more number of sites is there in the DNA more units of enzyme are required in comparison to same amount of DNA with fewer sites",
            "d)  The amount of enzyme required for digestion of DNA with less number of sites is more than that of more number of sites in the same amount of DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: One unit of enzyme is the quantity required for digestion of 1 microgram of DNA in 1hr and under given temperature conditions. The amount of enzyme required is more if more number of sites is there in the same amount of DNA in comparison to less number of sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct regarding partial digestion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is defined as the conditions where all the sites in the DNA sequence are not recognized",
            "b) The number of fragments created by partial digestion are same as that of complete digestion",
            "c) It is not useful in representation of genomic library",
            "d) Exactly half of the sites in the DNA are recognized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Partial digestion is the condition where all the sites aren’t recognized and thus the number of fragments created are not same as that of complete digestion. It is very useful in genomic library representation because nearly each and every segment is represented."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct nomenclature of a restriction enzyme obtained from the first activity of strain R of Escherichia coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EcoR1",
            "b) EscRI",
            "c) EcorI",
            "d) EcoRI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The first letter is the first letter of the genus and the next two letters are the first two letters of the species. They are then followed by the strain and the activity from which they are isolated. The activity is represented in Roman numerals."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Why is DNase preferred over restriction endonuclease in some cases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNase is preferred over restriction endonuclease in some cases because the latter are not able to recognize some of the restriction sites",
            "b) DNase is more specific as restriction endonuclease, so the required fragment is obtained",
            "c) DNase is less specific as compared to restriction endonuclease, hence there are more chances of representation of all the possible fragments",
            "d) DNase is abundant in comparison the restriction endonuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the DNase is less specific than restriction endonuclease, thus it cuts more randomly. It further leads to the representation of more fragments and hence they can be very useful in genomic library construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Besides enzymatic means, physical stress can also be used for cleaving the DNA. Which of the following statements is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sonication, needles, syringes, etc all come under the category of physical stress",
            "b) In physical stress, there are no chances of contamination",
            "c) The ends obtained have unique sequences",
            "d) They are less effective than DNase treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ends created by DNase don’t have unique single stranded sequences. It is so because DNase is not specific in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Phosphatases refer to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the enzymes which add phosphate group at the end of the DNA molecule in the place of hydroxyl group",
            "b) the enzymes which hydrolytically remove phosphate group from the DNA molecules and replace them with hydroxyl group",
            "c) the enzymes responsible for removal of phosphate group from the DNA molecules and replace them with hydrogen",
            "d) the enzymes responsible for replacing hydrogen in the DNA molecules with the phosphate group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Physical stress methods are used to cleave the DNA randomly and it also generates non-unique ends as the DNase treatment. These include the use of sonication methods, needles and syringes. There are chances of contamination from the metal probes used in the setup used."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "How is phosphatase related to the ligation reactions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphate group is not required for the ligation reaction to take place, thus phosphatase is helpful",
            "b) It is helpful in ceasing the unwanted ligation",
            "c) Phosphatases are not at all related to ligation reactions",
            "d) They act as a catalyst in case of the ligation reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phosphatases are the enzymes which remove phosphate group and then replace them with the hydroxyl group. Kinases are the enzymes which are responsible for the addition of the phosphate group in place of hydroxyl group."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "How can phosphatase activity terminated prior to a ligation reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By heating",
            "b) By cooling",
            "c) By creating vibrations",
            "d) By alternatively cooling and heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phosphatses are used to stop unwanted ligation. It is so because if phosphatases are present, phosphate would be removed from the ends and it would further block the ligation. It is so because the phosphate group is necessary for ligation to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Basic classification of polymerases includes how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The types are- DNA dependent DNA polymerase, DNA dependent RNA polymerase, RNA dependent DNA polymerase, template independent polymerase and RNA dependent RNA polymerase. Out of these, RNA dependent RNA polymerases are not focused so much in comparison to other polymerases."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Polymerase can be defined as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) an enzyme used to synthesize a new DNA or RNA strand on the basis of pre-existing strand or at times without a pre-existing strand",
            "b) an enzyme used for removal of nucleotides from the DNA or RNA strand",
            "c) an enzyme which can synthesize only a new DNA strand, not an RNA strand",
            "d) an enzyme which can synthesize either a new DNA or an RNA strand but only when a strand is there"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The synthesis of a new DNA or RNA strand can be done either on the basis of a pre-existing strand or without it. Those which don’t require a pre-existing strand are known as template free or template independent."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of the following activity is not possible in the case of DNA polymerase I?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3’-5’ exonuclease",
            "b) 5’-3’ exonuclease",
            "c) 5’-3’ DNA synthesis",
            "d) 3’-5’ DNA synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: DNA polymerase is having the ability to synthesize DNA strand in 5’-3’ direction but not in 3’-5’ direction. Also, it is having exonuclease activity in both the directions, which means that it can remove bases in either of the direction but can synthesize only in 5’-3’ direction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "The E. coli DNA polymerase enzyme gives different domains with different activities on cleaving with protease subtilisin. Which of the following statements is correct with respect to the fragments generated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The smaller fragment is having C terminal and the larger fragment is having N terminal",
            "b) The smaller fragment is named as Klenow fragment and the intact molecule is called as Kornberg fragment",
            "c) The smaller fragment is having 5’-3’ exonuclease activity whereas the larger fragment is having 5’-3’ polymerase and 3’-5’ exonuclease activity",
            "d) Both the fragments are having 5’-3’ polymerase and 3’-5’ exonuclease activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two fragments are generated of size 35kDa and 76kDa, with the N terminal in the smaller fragment. The larger fragment, which is of 76kDa is known as Klenow fragment and the intact molecule is called Kornberg fragment. The smaller fragment is having 5’-3’ exonuclease activity whereas the larger fragment is having 5’-3’ polymerase and 3’-5’ exonuclease activity.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Removal of single stranded portions produced due to exonucleolytic activity and due to polymerase activity are termed as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) polishing and end filling respectively",
            "b) end filling and polishing respectively",
            "c) polishing in both the cases",
            "d) end filling in both the cases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The single stranded ends generated due to exonucleolytic activity can either be removed by generating their complementary strand or removing the single stranded overhang. In both cases, it is termed as polishing. Whereas removal of single stranded regions generated because of polymerase activity is termed as end-filling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Thermostable DNA polymerases are very important in PCR. How are they obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are obtained by heating the bacteria manually over high temperatures",
            "b) They are isolated from extremely stable thermophilic bacteria which are often found growing in oceanic vents",
            "c) They are found everywhere in nature",
            "d) They are obtained by genetically modifying the E. coli bacteria with thermal stability property"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermostable DNA polymerases are found naturally in thermophilic bacteria which can be found growing in oceanic vents. They are having high stability and their DNA polymerases can function effectively even at high temperatures in-vitro."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme is said as reverse transcriptase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA dependent DNA polymerase",
            "b) RNA dependent RNA polymerase",
            "c) RNA dependent DNA polymerase",
            "d) DNA dependent RNA polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RNA dependent DNA polymerases are said as reverse transcriptase and the function follows it name. The function is to reverse the phenomenon of general transcription, in which RNA is synthesized from DNA. But here it is reversed and DNA is synthesized by using RNA as a template."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Why reverse transcriptase enzymes are having comparatively high error rates than other polymerases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because they are not having 3’-5’ proofreading exonucleolytic activity",
            "b) Because they are not having 5’-3’ proofreading exonucleolytic activity",
            "c) Because they are having slow rates of exonucleolytic activity",
            "d) It is difficult to synthesize DNA from RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reverse transcriptase enzymes are not having proof reading exonuclease activity in 3’-5’ direction. Hence, when the synthesis is done in 5’-3’ direction it is not checked in the 3’-5’ direction and thus the errors inculcated won’t be removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which polymerase can be used in conjunction with appropriate phage promoters in order to have high levels of specific transcription?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA dependent DNA polymerase",
            "b) DNA dependent RNA polymerase",
            "c) RNA dependent RNA polymerase",
            "d) DNA dependent DNA polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DNA dependent RNA polymerases are very specific for phage promoters and thus they are used for carrying out highly specific transcription. They are often isolated from T3, T7 phages."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Template independent polymerases are the enzymes which add nucleotide bases without a template. Which of the following statements is correct with respect to these?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They only add a single nucleotide",
            "b) They only add a string of nucleotides and not a single nucleotide",
            "c) Terminal transferase adds a series of nucleotides at the 3’ end",
            "d) Taq polymerase adds a single nucleotide at the 5’ end of the PCR product"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Template independent polymerases can either add a single nucleotide or a series of nucleotides; it is based on the template. Terminal transferase adds a series of nucleotides at the 3’ end, which generates a single stranded tail. Whereas, Taq polymerase adds a single A base at 3’ end of the PCR product."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct with respect to exonuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They only act on single stranded DNA molecules",
            "b) They only act on double stranded DNA molecules",
            "c) They remove a single nucleotide base at a time",
            "d) They remove nucleotide bases from the middle of a polynucleotide chain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Exonuclease is responsible for removal of a single nucleotide base at a time, from the end of the polynucleotide sequence. They can act on both single and double stranded DNA molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "How many approaches are there which can be used for exonucleolytic activity in double stranded DNA molecules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 2 approaches which can be used to carry out exonucleolytic activity in double stranded DNA. The two approaches which are used as a separation of both the strands together and separation of both the strands separately."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "What is the mode of action of exonuclease III?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exonuclease III acts on single stranded DNA in 3’-5’ direction",
            "b) Exonuclease III acts on double stranded DNA in 5’-3’ direction",
            "c) Exonuclease III acts on single stranded DNA in 5’-3’ direction",
            "d) Exonuclease III acts on double stranded DNA in 3’-5’ direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is an enzyme which is having exonuclease activity in 3’-5’ direction and only on double stranded DNA. It doesn’t act on single stranded molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding S1 nuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It acts on double stranded DNA",
            "b) It acts on single stranded DNA",
            "c) It acts on both types of strands",
            "d) It is obtained from E. coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: S1 nuclease is obtained from Aspergillus orzyae and it acts on single stranded DNA molecules. It is having exonucleolytic activity.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "What happens if a DNA molecule is treated by first Exonuclease III and then followed by treatment with S1 nuclease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The molecule is shortened only from 3’ end",
            "b) The molecule is shortened only from 5’ end",
            "c) The molecule is shortened from both the ends",
            "d) Only Exonuclease acts and S1 doesn’t acts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The molecule is shortened from both the ends. It is so because as firstly Exonuclease III acts, single stranded ends are produced on both the sides. These are further acted upon by S1 nuclease and thus the molecule is shortened from both the sides."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "How can one end be protected from the action of Exonuclease III, so that the molecule is not shortened from both the ends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By using Phosphorothioate nucleotide analogue",
            "b) By making both the ends double stranded in nature",
            "c) By labelling one end with a radioactive compound",
            "d) By increasing the time of exposure of the DNA molecule to the enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phosphorothioate nucleotide analogues are used to replace some of the nucleotides at the ends with it. It doesn’t allows the action of the enzyme on it and thus the molecule won’t be shortened from that end on which replacement is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Bal31 is also an enzyme which is used. Which of the following statements hold true in its context?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is having only 3’-5’ exonuclease activity and no endonuclease activity",
            "b) It is having only an endonuclease activity",
            "c) It is having 5’-3’ exonuclease activity",
            "d) It leads to shortening from both the ends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bal31 is having an exonuclease activity in 3’-5’ direction and also an endonuclease activity. Thus, after having 3’-5’ exonuclease activity, the endonuclease activity takes place and the molecule is shortened from both the ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The extent of deletions can be manipulated by controlling which of them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time of incubation only",
            "b) Amount of nuclease added",
            "c) They both have a role to play in the extent of the deletion",
            "d) The amount of deletion which can be carried out for a particular amount of DNA is fixed regardless of the amount of nuclease and incubation time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The extent of deletion can be varied by varying the incubation time and the amount of nuclease added. Thus, they both play a role in controlling the extent of deletion."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "What is the function of methylase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition of methyl groups to DNA",
            "b) Removal of methyl groups from DNA",
            "c) Both in removal and addition of methyl groups from DNA",
            "d) It is used in production of methane gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Methylase is used for the addition of methyl groups on DNA. It is done via placing the methyl groups which are taken from S-adenosyl methionine."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Ligation is defined as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alignment of only double stranded DNA molecules at the ends and the formation of phosphodiester bonds between both the strands",
            "b) Alignment of either of the double or single stranded DNA molecules and formation of glycosidic bonds between both the strands",
            "c) Alignment of either of the double or single stranded DNA molecules and the formation of phosphodiester bonds. The bond can be between either one or both the strands",
            "d) Alignment of single stranded DNA molecules and formation of glycosidic bonds between these strands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ligation is basically the formation of bonds between the ends of two DNA strands. The strands can be single or double. The nature of the bond is phosphodiester, which means that bond is formed between sugar and phosphate. The phosphodiester bond can either be formed between one strand or both the strands."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "If only one bond is broken in the sugar-phosphate backbone, it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gap",
            "b) nick",
            "c) break",
            "d) leakage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case, if only one bond is broken in the sugar phosphate backbone, it is termed as nick. If a number of nucleotides are missing, it is termed a gap. Nick can be sealed by ligation reactions but gap can’t be sealed by a ligation reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "How many categories of ligation reaction are there on the basis of ends created?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two categories of ligation reaction and are named as blunt-ended and sticky ended reaction. They are named because of the nature of the ends of the molecules to be ligated."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "In the case of blunt-end ligation, blunt ends can be generated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) simply the action of restriction endonuclease which gives straight ends",
            "b) the polishing of staggered ends",
            "c) both the action of restriction endonuclease which gives straight ends and polishing of staggered ends",
            "d) by the action of restriction endonuclease which gives staggered ends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blunt ends are those which don’t have single stranded ends as overhangs. The ends are double stranded. And these can be generated by polishing the staggered ends or the action of restriction endonuclease which generate straight ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The ligation reaction is more efficient in which case?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blunt end ligation",
            "b) Sticky end ligation",
            "c) Both have the same efficiency",
            "d) Depends on the reaction conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sticky end ligation is generally more efficient than blunt end ligation. It is so because sticky end ligation is carried out because of complementary base pairing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "The sticky ends are held together by which type of bonds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen bond",
            "b) Covalent bond",
            "c) Ionic bond",
            "d) Van-der-waal forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sticky ends are held together by the hydrogen bonds. Hydrogen bonds are weak in nature and can easily be broken. "
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Why sticky ended ligations are carried out at temperatures lower than room temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is so because the vibrational and kinetic energy of the molecules at room temperature is lower than that of the energy required to break the bonds holding the ends",
            "b) The energy required to break the bonds holding the ends is very less than that of the kinetic and vibrational energy at room temperature",
            "c) The enzyme carrying out ligation is unstable at low temperature",
            "d) The sticky ends created, don’t just relegate at low temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sticky ends are held together by the hydrogen bonds. These hydrogen bonds are weak in nature and the energy required to break them is very less than the kinetic and vibrational energy of the molecules at room temperature. Hence the reaction is carried at 4 degrees."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "If a ligation reaction is being carried out and recircularization is observed, which type of reaction is being carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intramolecular",
            "b) Intermolecular",
            "c) Both observe recircularization equally",
            "d) Recirculation is not possible in any of the cases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ligation reaction can be both intramolecular and intermolecular in nature. The intermolecular reaction is that which ends ligated are of two different molecules. The intramolecular ligation is that which ends ligated belong to the same molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What is the kinetics of the intramolecular and intermolecular ligation reactions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Second order kinetics for intramolecular and first order for intermolecular",
            "b) First order kinetics for intramolecular and second order for intermolecular",
            "c) Both are first order",
            "d) Both are second order"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Recircularization is the phenomenon of joining the ends of the same molecule. It happens in the case of intramolecular ligation reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "What are the effects of increasing concentration of reaction components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It increases chances of ligation in both intramolecular and intermolecular reactions",
            "b) It increases chances of ligation only in intermolecular and no effect on intramolecular",
            "c) It decreases chances of ligation in intramolecular and increases in that of intermolecular",
            "d) It decreases chances of ligation in both types of reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the intramolecular reaction requires only the type of reaction species, the reaction is first order.Whereas, on the other hand intermolecular reaction requires collision between two different species and hence it is second order reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Enzyme commonly used for carrying out ligation reaction is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transferase",
            "b) Reverse transciptase",
            "c) Ligase",
            "d) DNase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ligase is the enzyme which is commonly used for carrying out the ligation reaction. They can either be obtained from E. coli or from cells that have been infected by the virus."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct with respect to T4 DNA ligase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can carry out only blunt ended ligations",
            "b) It doesn’t requires ATP",
            "c) It requires a phosphate group at 3’ end and a hydroxyl group at 5’ end for the molecule to be joined",
            "d) It is obtained from T4 bacteriophage upon infection by E. coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: T4 DNA ligase is obtained from T4 bacteriophage upon infection by E. coli. It carries out ligation both in blunt ended and sticky ended molecules and requires ATP. It requires a phosphate group at 5’ end and a hydroxyl group at 3’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "If blunt ended ligations are to be carried out. Which of the following enzymes can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E. coli DNA ligase",
            "b) T4 DNA ligase",
            "c) Both of these enzymes act equally in carrying out blunt ended ligations",
            "d) None of them is able to carry out blunt ended ligations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If blunt ended ligations are to be carried out, T4 DNA ligase should be used. E. coli DNA ligase is unable to carry out blunt ended ligation."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Mechanism of ligation for both T4 DNA ligase and E. coli DNA ligase makes use of Adenosine Monophosphate (AMP). Which of the steps is involved in the ligation mechanism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AMP is added to the 5’ phosphate of one of the DNA molecule",
            "b) It leads to the liberation of pyrophosphate from NAD and nicotinamide mononucleotide from ATP",
            "c) The AMP is further displaced by an electrophilic attack",
            "d) The AMP is further displaced by nucleophilic attack by 3’ hydroxyl of the same DNA molecule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The E. coli DNA ligase requires a cofactor nicotamine adenine dinucleotide (NAD), along with 5’ phosphate group and 3’ hydroxyl group."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Topoisomerase is also an enzyme which is used for carrying out ligation. The correct statement for topoisomerase is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They act only on double stranded molecules",
            "b) They alter the degree of supercoiling of DNA molecules",
            "c) They are less effective than conventional DNA ligase",
            "d) There are three types of topoisomerases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AMP is added to the 5’ phosphate of one of the DNA molecule. It leads to the liberation of pyrophosphate from ATP and nicotanamide mononucleotide from NAD. It is further displaced by nucleophilic attack by 3’ hydroxyl of the other DNA molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Mobile genetic elements can be transferred from one DNA portion to another. The enzyme carrying out this is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ligase",
            "b) Transciptase",
            "c) Transposase",
            "d) Endonuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Topoisomerases alter the degree of supercoiling of both single and double stranded DNA molecules. There are two types of topoisomerases, I and II. I is responsible for altering single stranded molecules and type II for altering double stranded molecules. They are more effective than conventional DNA ligase.\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Phage based recombination systems are used for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cleaving the molecules at specific sites",
            "b) adding the molecules at specific sites",
            "c) breakage and rejoining the molecules at specific sites",
            "d) breakage at random sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transposase is used for transferring mobile genetic elements from one portion to another. They are useful in inserting origin of replication or anti-biotic resistance genes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Bacteriophage lambda is having a phage recombination system. Following are the characteristics of this system ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used for inserting phage genome into the bacterium",
            "b) It is used for inserting bacterial genome into the phage",
            "c) The specific site in bacteria is attB and that in phage is attP",
            "d) The specific sites in both of them are called as attP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phage based recombination systems are used for breaking and rejoining the molecules at specific sites and not at random sites."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Ligation enzymes are used for ligating newly synthesized okazaki fragments. What holds true for okazaki fragments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Okazaki fragments are short fragments of DNA formed on the leading strand",
            "b) Okazaki fragments are large fragments of DNA formed on the lagging strand",
            "c) Okazaki fragments are short fragments of DNA formed on the lagging strand",
            "d) Okazaki fragments are large fragments of DNA formed on the leading strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The phage genome is inserted into the bacterium. The site for insertion at the phage genome is attP and that in the case of a bacterium is attB."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Introduction of DNA molecules into the recipient organism is termed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transformation",
            "b) translation",
            "c) transduction",
            "d) transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Introduction of DNA molecules into the recipient organism is termed as transformation. It is done with the help of endonucleases and ligases and the recipient organism is termed as host."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Many bacterial species are having a natural ability to take up the exogenous DNA material. Which of the statement is not correct in regard to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) This ability is termed as competence",
            "b) It is not limited to particular growth phases",
            "c) The bacteria may develop new biochemical abilities under special conditions such as nutrient deprivation",
            "d) Induction of specific set of bacterial proteins may take place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This ability is termed as competence and it is limited to particular growth phases. It may lead to developing new biochemical abilities under special conditions such as nutrient deprivation. If the bacterial cells are naturally competent, they may take the foreign DNA by simply incubating them with foreign DNA. "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Which of the statements hold true for conjugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conjugation is the natural process of transferring DNA from one species to another",
            "b) It is the artificial process in case the cells are not able to take them up naturally",
            "c) The plasmids are transferred from one cell to another by physical contact",
            "d) The plasmids are transferred from one cell to another by chemical means"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conjugation is the process used for transferring plasmids from one cell to another in case they are not able to take up naturally. It is done via physical contact and the plasmid being transferred encodes the machinery."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "F plasmid is often used in conjugation. The correct statement is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The F plasmid encodes the factor which is transferred from one cell to another",
            "b) The factor encoded by the F plasmid is called as Filamentous (F) factor",
            "c) It is transferred from one cell to another by filament",
            "d) The bacteria must belong to same species to carry out the conjugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: F plasmid encodes the factor called Fertility or F factor. It is transferred from one cell to another by the sex pilus. It is present in E. coli and for the conjugation to take place; bacteria can also belong to different species."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Plasmids can be classified into how many types depending on the genes present for their transformation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plasmids can be said as self-mobilizable and mobilizable. They are self mobilizable in the case they contain all the genes necessary to direct its own transfer. Mobilizable are those plasmids which don’t carry all the genes necessary for their transfer but they can be transferred if the genes are present somewhere in the host.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Chemical transformation refers to the methods which use chemicals in order to carry out transformation. Which of the following statements is true with respect to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical transformation decreases the efficiency of transformation as compared to natural transformation",
            "b) Ice cold calcium solution followed by heat shock is responsible for affecting the efficiency of DNA uptake",
            "c) The mechanism responsible for it named as ‘the heat shock model’",
            "d) Other complex mixtures such as those containing Manganese and hexamine cobalt can’t be used to affect the efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Viral infection can be used to take up the DNA by the cells. It is all because of the viral coat and the nucleic acid contained within has no role to play."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Electroporation is also used for taking up the DNA by the cells. It constitutes of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) inserting the DNA into the cells via an electric shock",
            "b) increased efficiency than both natural and chemical methods",
            "c) causing the least amount of damage in comparison to other methods",
            "d) decreased efficiency than both natural and chemical methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemical transformation methods increase the DNA uptake efficiency as in comparison to natural methods. The treatment by ice cold calcium solution which is followed by heat shock is responsible for increasing efficiency. But the exact mechanism behind it is not known till now. Other complex mixtures which comprise of cobalt, manganese etc. can be used to increase the efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Transformation carried out using a particle gun is known as biolistic transformation. It falls under which category of transformation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical",
            "b) Chemical",
            "c) Electroporation",
            "d) Natural"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electroporation is the method of DNA uptake via an electric shock. It is provided by varying the potential difference across the electrodes. It is having increased efficiency as compared to other methods. But also if prolonged treatment is given, it can cause destruction. It is so because the electric shock can be at times fatal to the cell wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "The particle gun method consists of which of the following steps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The DNA of interest is absorbed onto microprojectile beads",
            "b) These beads are often made of aluminium",
            "c) The explosion in a gun propels a macroprojectile forward which in turn propels microprojectile beads",
            "d) The macroprojectiles and microprojectiles both cross the perforated plate and hit the target tissue behind it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transformation carried out using a particle gun falls under the physical transformation category. The physical transformation uses some physical methods in order to carry out the transformation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Isolation of genomic DNA follows the same principles as that of obtaining plasmid from E. coli. Which of the following is not included in it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell lysis",
            "b) Removal of proteins",
            "c) Removal of chromosomal DNA",
            "d) Dissolving plasmid in water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are some basic steps which are included in obtaining plasmid DNA from E. coli. Firstly, the cell is lysed, further removal of proteins and chromosomal DNA is done. A plasmid is obtained and collected but not in water. Also, further purification is done if necessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "How many methods are there for obtaining the plasmid DNA from the bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two methods which are used for obtaining the plasmid DNA from the bacteria. They are named as alkaline lysis method and boiling lysis method. They both are having different working principles."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Cell lysis is carried out by which substance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysozyme and detergents",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Sugar solution",
            "d) Suphuric Acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cell lysis is carried out by adding lysozyme and detergents. The cell wall is made up of N-acetyl glucoasamine and N-acetyl muramic acid and they are having cross links. The agents added to break the cross links present between the molecules of the cell wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Chromosomal or genomic DNA is separated by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sedimentation",
            "b) Dissolution in water",
            "c) Centrifugation",
            "d) Distillation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromosomal or genomic DNA is comparatively heavier and large in size than that of plasmid DNA. Hence, centrifuging at a high speed leads to settling down of the genomic DNA and thus can be separated easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Proteins can be removed via treatment by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenol and chloroform treatment",
            "b) Treatment with sodium hydroxide",
            "c) Chloroform treatment alone",
            "d) Centrifuging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Proteins can be removed via treatment with phenol and chloroform treatment. Chloroform is alone not sufficient. The phenol added helps in the destruction of proteins and chloroform helps in its dissolution under acidic conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Nucleic acid precipitated constitutes of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plasmid DNA",
            "b) plasmid DNA, along with RNA and chromosomal DNA",
            "c) rna alone",
            "d) chromosomal DNA only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The nucleic acid is present in the solution and is precipitated by the addition of sodium or ammonium acetate and ethanol. It is because; nucleic acid is polar in nature and thus easily dissolves in water. Hence, to avoid this sodium acetate and ethanol is added. Sodium acetate is shields the charge present on the sugar phosphate backbone and further bonds are easily formed between ethanol and phosphate. It leads to separating out of nucleic acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Treatment with exonuclease leads to removal of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) remnants of chromosomal DNA",
            "b) RNase",
            "c) plasmid DNA which is circularized",
            "d) proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nucleic acid precipitated contains the plasmid DNA and along with it RNA and remnants of chromosomal DNA are also present.  RNA can be removed via adding RNase."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Adsorption onto a solid phase support followed by elution is used as an alternative for separation of which component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) chromosomal DNA",
            "b) plasmid DNA",
            "c) RNA alone",
            "d) other impurities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Exonuclease leads to removal of remnants of chromosomal DNA because they are usually having linear ends. The circularized ends of plasmid are protected from the action of exonuclease because they don’t have any free ends for their action."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which of the following components bind to the solid column made of silica, under high salt concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins",
            "b) Polysaccharides",
            "c) Both proteins and polysaccharides",
            "d) Plasmid DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This method is used for separation of plasmid DNA. It is advantageous because it avoids the use of phenol and also removes RNA at times along with plasmid DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Purification of DNA by using silica derivatized groups by DEAE is termed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ion exchange resin based method.",
            "b) silica based purification",
            "c) atom based resin exchange method",
            "d) packed bed purification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasmid DNA binds to a solid support which is made of silica and under high salt concentrations. A high salt concentration doesn’t allow less polar molecules to bind such as polysaccharides and proteins. The binded DNA molecule is further eluted by using a low salt concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct with respect to caesium chloride centrifugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Caesium is light in weight",
            "b) The dissolution of caesium and nucleic acids leads to the formation of gradients",
            "c) According to the amount of supercoiling and A+T content, the DNA settles",
            "d) Nicked DNA settles below than supercoiled DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silica derivatized groups by DEAE are used for purification of DNA. These groups are positively charged and the DNA gets attached to it, along with other species such as RNA which are negatively charged. Further, DNA can be obtained by varying the ionic concentrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of the following components settles at the bottom?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA",
            "b) Proteins",
            "c) Nicked DNA",
            "d) Supercoiled DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:b\nExplanation: Caesium chloride is heavy and when the nucleic acid is dissolved with it, density gradients are formed. According to the extent of supercoiling and G+C content, settling of DNA takes place. The nicked DNA settles above than the nicked DNA. "
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "The location of plasmid DNA can be visualized by addition of:",
        "Options": [
            "a) bromophenol blue",
            "b) ethidium bromide",
            "c) ortho xylene",
            "d) texas red"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The component settling at the bottom is RNA. And the proteins float on the free surface. The nicked DNA forms a band above the supercoiled form."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Gel electrophoresis separates nucleic acid molecules based on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) charge on molecules",
            "b) size of the molecules",
            "c) nature of the molecules i.e. whether DNA or RNA",
            "d) chemical properties of the nucleic acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gel electrophoresis separates nucleic acid molecules on the basis of their size. The nucleic acid molecules move through the gel because of the force provided by the applied electric field."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "The charge present on the DNA backbone is negative. The force required to accelerate the molecules towards anode is directly proportional to the number of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sugar molecules",
            "b) nitrogenous bases",
            "c) phosphate groups",
            "d) both phosphate group and sugar molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DNA backbone is negatively charged because of the phosphate groups. Hence, the force required to move the molecules towards anode is directly proportional to the number of phosphate groups present."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which one of the following will travel fastest through the gel if the amount of DNA present is same in all?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular",
            "b) Supercoiled",
            "c) Nicked",
            "d) Supercoiled and circular will move at same speed and faster than nicked"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the charge increases, which is because of the number of phosphate molecules, the size also increases. As, the size increases, it also results in increase of mass. Thus, now the force and also the acceleration are independent of size until a retarding force is present. But, in the case of gel electrophoresis, the retarding force is provided by gel and thus separation takes place on the basis of size."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "How is the size of molecules under analysis measured?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By measuring the distance moved through a ruler",
            "b) By measuring the amount of visualising dye used",
            "c) By running a standard molecule, whose size is known in parallel",
            "d) There is no exact criterion for doing so"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The supercoiled form of DNA will travel the fastest. It is so because; the movement through the gel is based on the size. The smaller the molecule is the less retarding force it experiences when it moves. Hence, supercoiled which is having the smallest size will move the fastest."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Gel matrices are generally of two types Agarose and Polyacrylamide. Which of the statements is correct with respect to agarose gels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agarose is a polysaccharide which is obtained from red algae",
            "b) Agarose is a polysaccharide obtained from fungus",
            "c) It is composed of glucose residues",
            "d) It is obtained via dissolving in its water by boiling in water and then cooling it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The size of the DNA molecules is measured by a standardized molecule. It is known as DNA ladder. The molecules under analysis are compared with the DNA ladder. "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Polyacrylamide gels are the other types of gels which are commonly used. Which of the following statement is not correct with respect to these types of gels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are obtained via polymerization between acrylamide and bis-acrylamide",
            "b) The components added for initiating polymerization are ammonium persulphate and TEMED",
            "c) It is casted in horizontal and flat trays",
            "d) TEMED catalyses the formation of free radicals from persulphate ions which leads to initiation of cross-linking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Agarose is a polysaccharide which is obtained from red algae. It is composed of galactose residues. Agarose gel is obtained via dissolving in it a buffer by boiling it and then cooling it. It leads to the formation of agar in conjunction with other polysaccharides, agropectin."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "If the amount of agarose added is more, the molecular under analysis should have the following characteristic:",
        "Options": [
            "a) small size",
            "b) large size",
            "c) size has no relation with the amount of agarose",
            "d) the amount of molecules under analysis matters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polyacrylamide gels are made up by the polymerization of acryl amide and bis acryl amide units. The polymerization takes place because of TEMED and ammonium persulphate, as TEMED catalyses the formation of free radicals from persulphate. These gels are usually casted in vertical trays whereas the agarose gels are casted in horizontal and flat trays."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "In the case of electrophoresis of single stranded DNA or RNA, which type of gels are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Renaturing",
            "b) Denaturing",
            "c) The routine agarose gel",
            "d) The routine polyacrylamide gel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of agrose gels, the separation takes place because of size. If the amount of agarose is more, smaller size molecules will be able to move easily as in comparison to larger size molecules. It is so because; the movement is through the pores. More the amount of agarose, smaller the size of the pore."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "At times, a specific fragment of the molecules of DNA which are analyzed needs to be separated. One of the methods is digesting the gels simply. Which of the following statement is not correct in with respect to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The gelling temperature has an important role to play",
            "b) For higher gelling temperatures, digestion of DNA is done via the addition of agarase or some chaotropic agents",
            "c) For lower gelling temperatures, simply slicing out of target DNA is done which is followed by melting",
            "d) The DNA can be extracted via the addition of sodium or any positively charged group"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of single stranded molecules, denaturing gels are used. It is so because, if denaturing gels are not there, there are chances of formation of secondary structures which hinder the movement of nucleic acids. Thus to avoid this, denaturing agents such as urea, etc. are added."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "A piece of DNA that is to be separated is crushed and soaked into the buffer. The majority of DNA diffuses, how can it be separated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filtration and centrifugation",
            "b) Filtration or centrifugation",
            "c) Allowing to sediment",
            "d) By passing through a silica column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the target DNA is crushed and soaked into the buffer, the majority of it diffuses into the gel. It can be separated via filtration or separation. It is simply termed as recovering the DNA from the gel by diffusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Another method of DNA recovery is termed as freeze-squeeze. The correct statement for it is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The slice containing DNA is cut and frozen into liquid oxygen",
            "b) Freezing doesn’t have any effect on the DNA structure",
            "c) After freezing centrifugation is carried out through glass wool plug",
            "d) The substance used for centrifugation allows the gel to pass through but the liquid is retained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is also a method for obtaining DNA from gels. The slice containing DNA is cut and frozen into liquid nitrogen. Freezing in liquid nitrogen leads to disruption of structure. As the centrifugation by glass wool plug is carried out after freezing out, the gel is retained by it. The liquid which is containing dissolved DNA will be allowed to pass through."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "If further electrophoresis is used for recovery of DNA from gels, the method is termed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) secondary electrophoresis",
            "b) recovery electrophoresis",
            "c) denaturing electrophoresis",
            "d) electro-elution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If electrophoresis is used further for recovery, the method is termed as electro-elution. There are different electro-elution methods which are used such as dialysis tube or membrane is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "UV shadowing is used at times for visualising the DNA. Which of the statements is correct for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In this method, the DNA bands are visualized because they fluoresce under UV",
            "b) The DNA bands won’t fluoresce but will absorb the UV light",
            "c) It is not suitable for visualizing single stranded molecules",
            "d) It is less preferred over the use of ethidium bromide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As further electrophoresis is carried out, the DNA moves out of the gel but is retained by the buffer. From the buffer, it can be obtained via pipetting."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "The greatest separation is obtained in which portion of the gel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower portion where the anode is",
            "b) Lower portion where the cathode is",
            "c) The separation is uniform all over",
            "d) It varies according to the quantity of the size of the molecules to be separated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In this method, the DNA bands won’t fluoresce but will absorb the UV light. This leads to the formation of a non-fluorescent shadow on the screen. It is suitable for visualising single stranded species because the mode of action is not intercalating as in the case of use of ethidium bromide. It is preferred over it because ethidium bromide is often difficult to remove."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the statements is correct for non uniform separation obtained other than the conventional one?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be obtained via applying strong field towards the cathode",
            "b) It can be obtained via applying the same field on both the sides",
            "c) The separation is greater on the side of stronger field",
            "d) Its is greater towards the weaker field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The greatest separation is obtained in the lower portion of the gel where the anode is. Thus the smaller molecules are having the greatest separation because they are the one which travels farther in the gel."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "How can gradient in the field strength be obtained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be obtained via varying the amount of current, keeping the resistance constant",
            "b) It can be obtained via varying the amount of resistance, keeping the current constant",
            "c) Both can be varied, but resistance is having more effect",
            "d) Buffer-gradient gels can be used with decreasing concentration of buffer at the bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conventionally, separation is greater towards the lower portion i.e. where the anode is. In order to obtain greater separation towards the cathode, the stronger field is applied here. As the field is weaker on the anode side, the molecules retard as they move towards anode and are less separated."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "If the molecules to be separated are larger than the size for conventional electrophoresis, which type of gels can be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wedge gels",
            "b) Buffer-gradient gels",
            "c) Pulse field gels",
            "d) Varying the amount of agarose will carry out the separation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The gradient field strength can be obtained via varying the resistance because the current flowing throughout the gel needs to remain constant. To vary the resistance, often buffer-gradient gels and wedge gels can be used. Wedge gels are thick and thus are having lower resistance at the bottom. Whereas buffer-gradient gels with increasing concentration at the bottom are used. As the concentration increases at the bottom, resistance decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct for the method of separation of large molecules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The large DNA molecules can pass through the matrix in any direction, not necessarily in the direction parallel to the movement",
            "b) The separation can be carried out if the fields are at right angles to each other",
            "c) The time of pulse should be less than that of the reorientation time",
            "d) Separation is not of the megabase level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the case, if the molecules to be separated are very large, say the chromosomes are to be separated. In this case, pulse-field gels are used. It is termed as pulse field gel electrophoresis (PFGE)."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Often the DNA or RNA needs to be removed from the gel to the solid support. The process can be termed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blotting",
            "b) Transfer",
            "c) Chromatography",
            "d) DNA purification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At times, the DNA or RNA needs to be transferred from the gel to the solid support for various purposes such as analyses. This process is termed as blotting."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which of the following steps is not included in the transferring of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The gel containing the DNA is immersed in the buffer in the reservoir",
            "b) The buffer flows up through the gel via a wick",
            "c) Membrane is placed over the gel",
            "d) The nucleic acids are dissolved in the buffer and are obtained from it via pipetting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gel containing the DNA molecules is immersed in the buffer. The membrane is placed over the gel. The buffer rises from the wick and passes through the gel. It carries along with it, the nucleic acids and they are then trapped by the membrane. The membrane can be washed further in order to obtain the DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "If the DNA samples are to be analyzed, the membrane should be studied. Which of them is correct for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The membrane should not be treated with UV or heat",
            "b) The membrane is further immersed in the buffer containing labelled nucleic acids which are known  as strips",
            "c) Labelled nucleic acids bind to the sequences which are same as the sequences present on the membrane",
            "d) The binded sequences can be visualized by autoradiography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The membrane should be treated with UV or heated. It ensures the cross linking of the DNA molecules on the membrane. The labelled nuclei in the buffer are called a probe. These sequences bind to the complementary sequences on the membrane and can be visualized via autoradiography."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "In the case DNA is transferred from gel to the membrane, it is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) southern blot",
            "b) western blot",
            "c) northern blot",
            "d) south-western blot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the DNA to be transferred, it is called a southern blot. If RNA is to be transferred it is called as northern blot. For transferring of proteins it is called a western blot. "
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Oligonucleotides can’t be referred to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) undefined sequences",
            "b) sequences that can be used as PCR primers",
            "c) sequences that can be used in DNA sequencing",
            "d) sequences that can be used in identifying complementary DNA molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oligonucleotide is the defined sequences which are having various purposes such as primers in PCR. They are also used in DNA sequencing. Oligonucleotides can be used as probes in complementary base pairing reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Oligonucleotides are synthesized chemically. Which of the following step is involved in oligonucleotide synthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleotide addition is done by adding many nucleotides at a time",
            "b) The coupling reaction should involve water",
            "c) Only one type of nucleotides can be added at a time",
            "d) Unblocking of the reactive groups leads to addition of nucleotides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oligonucleotide synthesis is done on the basis of blocking the reactive groups so that only one nucleotide is added as the unblocking is done. The coupling reaction should not involve water because than water will do nucleophilic reaction. A mixture of nucleotides can be added at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "If the known DNA sequences are immobilized onto a solid support, it is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blot",
            "b) Microarray",
            "c) DNA plate",
            "d) Column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case known DNA sequences are immobilized on a solid support, the arrangement is called a microarray. If unknown sequences are immobilized, it is called a blot."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "In the case of microarrays ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Often the whole organism is not sequenced",
            "b) Changes in transcript level can be studied in response to environmental changes",
            "c) RNA is synthesized only after the property which is to be studied is inculcated",
            "d) DNA is synthesized for this RNA by transcriptase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In microarrays, often the whole organism is sequenced on the solid support such as a slide. The change in the transcript level can be studied in response to environmental changes. The RNA is synthesized both for before and after the change is to be studied. DNA is synthesized for both RNAs by reverse transcriptase."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "If undefined sequences are immobilized, the set up is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blot",
            "b) Microarray",
            "c) Plate",
            "d) DNA chip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The DNA is labelled with fluorescent dyes. The amount of fluorescence they give corresponds to the level of transcription. The dyes which are often used are Cy3 and Cy5."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "The process of amplification of specific DNA sequences by an enzymatic process is termed as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) amplification",
            "b) polymerase chain reaction (PCR)",
            "c) translation",
            "d) microarrays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of amplification of specific DNA sequences by an enzymatic process is termed as Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR). For the PCR to take place there should be small sequences at each end which should be known."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What are primers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primers are the short sequences at the end of the nucleotide sequences which are used for amplification",
            "b) Primers are the short sequences which are complementary to the nucleotides at the end of the sequence which is to be amplified",
            "c) Primers are the short sequences present anywhere in the nucleotide sequence to be amplified",
            "d) Primers are the short sequences which are complementary to the nucleotides anywhere in the sequence to be amplified"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Primers are short nucleotide sequences which are complementary to the stretches at the ends of the DNA sequence to be amplified."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "A reaction mixture for PCR consists of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) heat unstable polymerase",
            "b) primers in a limited amount",
            "c) deoxynucleoside triphosphate (dNTPs)",
            "d) a region complementary to the sequence to be amplified"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A reaction mixture for PCR consists of the region of the DNA sequence to be amplified, primers in large molar excess, heat stable polymerase and dNTPs. Heat stable polymerase which is used commonly is Taq polymerase. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of Taq polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an RNA polymerase",
            "b) It is heat stable",
            "c) It is obtained from thermophilic bacterium and can be grown in the laboratory below a temperature of 75 degrees",
            "d) It is used in cellular synthesis processes and the optimum temperature is at least 90 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Taq polymerase is a DNA polymerase obtained from thermophilic bacterium Thermus aquatics. It is heat stable and can be grown in the laboratory at a temperature above 75 degrees. It is used in cellular DNA synthesis processes and the optimum temperature is at least 80 degrees. It is not readily denatured by repeated cooling and heating cycles and thus is used in amplification processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a condition for PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial melting carried out for 5 minutes at 94 degrees",
            "b) Initial melting followed by 30 cycles each consisting of melting for 1 minute at 94 degrees",
            "c) Renaturation for 5 minutes at 60 degrees",
            "d) DNA synthesis at 72 degrees for 1.5 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCR consists of a series of steps. Firstly, the reaction mixture is heated so that the strands are separated i.e. their denaturation takes place. Then it is again cooled so that the primers are able to attach. Once the primers are attached, the synthesis of DNA is allowed. This whole process is repeated."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "All the molecules generated during PCR will not be full length. Some will also be of intermediate length. Which of the statements is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) After first cycle, majority of the molecules will be full length and only some will be of intermediate length",
            "b) In the next cycle, each intermediate molecule will generate one intermediate molecule and one target molecule",
            "c) The number of full length molecules increase as number of cycles proceed",
            "d) The number of intermediate molecules increase geometrically and the number of target molecules increase arithmetically"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The melting temperature is 94 degrees and the initial melting is carried for 5 minutes at this temperature. It is followed by 30 cycles each consisting of melting for 1 minute at 94 degrees. The renaturation is carried for 1 minute at 60 degrees. The DNA synthesis is carried out at 72 degrees for 1.5 minutes. After the 30 cycles, a final round of extension is carried out for 10 minutes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following activity is not present in Taq polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’-3’ polymerase",
            "b) 5’-3’ exonuclease",
            "c) 3’-5’ exonuclease",
            "d) Both 5’-3’ polymerase and 5’-3’ exonuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Primers and polymerases are not added more as the reaction proceeds. It is so because the polymerase is heat stable and is not destroyed during the reaction. Primers on the other hand are added in excess at the beginning of the reaction.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Taq polymerase is having high processivity",
            "b) Processivity is defined in this case as a synthesis of DNA by polymerase",
            "c) It requires a 5’ end for the elongation to take place",
            "d) The maximum size of the molecules which can be synthesized is 10kbp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Intermediate molecules are those which would be having primer at one end and the other end won’t be defined. After the first cycle, half of the molecules would be full length and half would be of intermediate length. In the next cycle, each intermediate molecule generates one intermediate molecule and one target molecule. Target molecule is that which is defined by primers at both the ends. The number of full length molecules remains constant. But, target molecules increase geometrically and the intermediate molecules increase arithmetically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "What is the half life cycle for Taq polymerase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 minutes",
            "b) 80 minutes",
            "c) 10 minutes",
            "d) 50 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Taq polymerase is not having 3’-5’ exonuclease activity. It is a proof reading activity and it is very important to have a check on the mutations if they are encountered in the PCR products."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Taq polymerase incorporates which residue at 3’ end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G",
            "b) T",
            "c) A",
            "d) C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Taq polymerase is having low processivity. It means that it falls off from the template before it has synthesized a large piece of DNA. It requires a 3’ OH for carrying out the elongation. The maximum size of the molecules which can be synthesized is 2-4 kbp. "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Polymerases are also available from other Thermus species. Which of the following is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermus flavus gives Tfl enzyme",
            "b) Thermus thermopilus gives Tfl enzyme",
            "c) They are having proof reading activity",
            "d) Thermus flavus gives Tth enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The half life cycle for Taq polymerase is 40 minutes at 94 degrees. Thus, at the end of the 30 cycles, a significant loss of activity takes place. "
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Polymerases are available with proof reading activity. Which of the following are the characteristics of these types of polymerases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They add A residue at 3’ end",
            "b) They are obtained from Thermococcus litoralis",
            "c) They can’t be obtained from archaebacteria",
            "d) The marine bacteria from which they are obtained grow at temperatures lower than that of Thermus aquatics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It incorporates A residue at the 3’ end. This overhang is often useful in carrying out the cloning of these PCR products."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Primers are generally ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20-30 nucleotides long",
            "b) 40-50 nucleotides long",
            "c) as long as the template is",
            "d) taken according to the amount available"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Primers are generally short in length. They are 20-30 nucleotides long. It is easier to match short primers with the template in comparison to long primers. But in the case of eukaryotic DNA as a template, long primers are preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which end of the primer should be matched properly in order to carry out the amplification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5’ end",
            "b) 3’ end",
            "c) Both of the ends should be matched properly",
            "d) Anyone of the ends should match"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For carrying out the amplification, it is not necessary that the whole primer should match with the template. But it is necessary that 3’ end should match because if 3’ end is not matched the polymerase won’t be able to carry out elongation."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following nucleotides should be there at 3’ end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Any of A, T, G or C will work out",
            "b) Either A or T",
            "c) Either G or C",
            "d) Specifically G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At 3’ end, either G or C should be present. It is so because; these form three hydrogen bonds and thus are stronger. Whereas, A and T form only two hydrogen bonds and thus are comparatively less strong than G or C. "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Melting temperature is given by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4(G+C) + 2(A+T)",
            "b) 2(G+C) + 4(A+T)",
            "c) 2(A+G) + 4(C+T)",
            "d) 4(A+G) + 2(C+T)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The melting temperature is that temperature at which the primers associate with the template. The melting temperature is decided by the amount of different nucleotides present."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Why internal secondary structures are not preferred for primers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal structures are very bulky and thus elongation is not preferred",
            "b) Because of it, primer may fold back on itself and won’t be available for template",
            "c) Internal secondary structures require more amount of template",
            "d) If internal structures are present, no proof reading would be observed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both the primers should have a nearly same melting temperature. It is so because then they would nearly bind at the same time as the temperature is being lowered for their annealing."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following is favoured for primer design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The melting temperature should be different for both the primers",
            "b) Primers should be long in length",
            "c) Primers should not be complementary to each other",
            "d) Matching should be of whole primer to the template"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Internal structures are not preferred because if they are present the primer may fold back on itself. As the primer folds back on it, it is not available for the template. As an intramolecular reaction, self annealing is preferred over intermolecular annealing of primer to the template."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "What will happen if the amino acid sequence is used directly for primer designing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There would be certainty because the genetic code is unique for each amino acid",
            "b) There would be uncertainty as the genetic code is degenerate and none of the amino acid is having a unique code",
            "c) There would be uncertainty as the genetic code is degenerate but some of the amino acids such as methionine are having a unique codon",
            "d) The amount of uncertainty or certainty is a matter of chance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Primers should not be complementary to each other. It is so because if they are complementary, primer dimer formation takes place. If primer dimer is formed, proper elongation won’t be taking place."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "In the case of uncertainty, if more than one nucleotide is included at a position it is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mixed site",
            "b) polynucleotide site",
            "c) unique site",
            "d) degenerate site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the amino acid sequence is used directly, there would be uncertainty. It is so because the genetic code is degenerate. It means that one codon can correspond to many amino acids. There are some exceptions such as methionine which are having a unique codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What is the property of inosine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Having narrow range of pairing capabilities",
            "b) Having a broad range of pairing capabilities",
            "c) The pairing capability is the same as the normal nucleotides",
            "d) It is abbreviated as A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If uncertainty is there at times, more than one nucleotide can be included in one position. And in this condition it is called a mixed site. "
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following is useful in applications of PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is manual",
            "b) Only one sample’s analysis can be carried out at a time",
            "c) It is having a high speed",
            "d) The amount of DNA required initially is high"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PCR is having numerous advantages over normal cloning procedures. It is automated and many samples can be analysed at a time simultaneously. It is having a high speed and the initial amount of DNA required is very less."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "What is the correct statement with respect to ddNTPs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are dideoxynucleotide triphosphates",
            "b) They are used in the termination of DNA sequencing",
            "c) They are used for initiating DNA sequencing",
            "d) They are used in the case if the starting amounts are large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ddNTPs are dideoxynucleoside triphosphates. It is used in the case for termination of sequencing. It is so because, both the hydroxyl molecules are removed sequencing would be terminated. It is beneficial in the case if the initial amounts are less."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Sickle cell anaemia is a genetic disorder. Which of the following doesn’t holds true for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be analysed by PCR",
            "b) It destroys a restriction site",
            "c) The mutation is in alpha globulin gene",
            "d) The conventional approach took weeks for the whole analyses to be carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cycle sequencing is that when very less amounts of DNA template is used for carrying out the sequencing. And the whole process is facilitated by the use of ddNTPs."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "PCR products can be analysed in many ways. Which of the following is not possible?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of restriction enzymes",
            "b) Determining whether a particular oliginucleotide probe hybridizes to a PCR product",
            "c) Electrophoresis",
            "d) Direct sequencing can’t be carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sickle cell anaemia is a mutation in the beta globulin gene. It destroys a restriction site and the analyses can be carried out by PCR. PCR is very fast in comparison to conventional methods which took weeks to be completed. And the former method is completed in just one day."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the statements don’t hold true for the forensics and the amplification carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the case of forensics, conventional methods such as southern blotting are used very effectively",
            "b) In cases of bone fragments which contain less than 300 nucleotides conventional methods can’t be applied as they involve southern blotting, restriction digestion etc",
            "c) The poor condition of DNA also makes the PCR amplification difficult",
            "d) Microsatellites composed of simply varying repeats of CA sequences are used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Restriction enzymes can be used and analyses can be done via destroying the restriction site. Checking for the hybridization of oligonucleotide probe with a PCR product. Electrophoresis can be used to check the mobility and compare it with a wild type molecule. Direct sequencing can also be carried out in order to analyse the PCR product."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "The genetic relatedness between organisms can be identified by studying the band patterns when different PCR products are analysed electrophoreically. This method is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP)",
            "b) amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP)",
            "c) random amplification of polymorphic DNA (RAPD)",
            "d) polymorphism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of forensics conventional methods are not very useful. If the bone fragments are having less than 300 nucleotides then the conventional methods can’t be applied easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "PCR amplification can be used for which type of samples?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Old samples only",
            "b) Recent samples only",
            "c) Equally to both recent and old samples",
            "d) Recent samples are preferred but can be applied to old samples also"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The genetic relatedness between organisms can be identified by studying the band patterns of different PCR products. This process is termed as random amplification of polymorphic DNA (RAPD)."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "What is the problem associated with historical DNA samples?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are less in amount thus amplification is difficult",
            "b) Because the samples are very old, there can be contamination",
            "c) They degrade during repeated cooling and heating cycles",
            "d) As the samples are old, the standard sequences for comparison is not present"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If properly designed primers are used then it is possible to amplify DNA from one organism that can’t be separated from others. For say a bacterial strain in a mixed population."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which of the statement holds for long-range PCR and in its relation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the PCR in which longer templates are used",
            "b) DNA polymerases which don’t have proof-reading activity give larger products",
            "c) DNA polymerases’ processivity is not a measure to have larger products",
            "d) It is PCR in which a mixture of enzymes is used to have larger products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Long range PCR is the PCR in which a mixture of enzymes is used to have larger products. If DNA polymerases are having proof reading activity then we can obtain larger products because in this case chain terminators are not used. Also, the processivity of the enzymes is also very important."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions don’t contribute to wrong annealing to primer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chance complementarity",
            "b) Conditions of annealing",
            "c) The original sequence of the primers",
            "d) Both the conditions of annealing and the original sequence don’t play any role"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are cases when wrong annealing of the primer takes place. It can happen because of chance complementarity, conditions of annealing such as ionic concentration and temperature. The original sequence of the primers is very important."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "How can the specificity of primer annealing be increased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of short primers",
            "b) Raising temperature",
            "c) Adjusting the concentration of sodium ions",
            "d) Using polymerase with proof reading activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specificity of primers annealing can be increased in various ways such as increasing temperature, using long primers. If long primers are used there are increased chances of having correct matching. Also, if the magnesium ion concentration is adjusted, annealing can be done more effectively. It is so because they stabilize primer-template binding."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which can be used as a precaution in order to minimize contamination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Careful use and design of pipettes",
            "b) Placing the pre-PCR and post-PCR stages in the same rooms",
            "c) Extracting the DNA along with surface layers",
            "d) Use of primers carefully is not very important"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Laboratory contamination consists of aerosols in pipettes from previously formed PCR products or related DNA sequences. External contamination includes contamination from bacteria, fungi and other human contamination.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "During amplification, there are chances of having a product of a mixture of different sequences. There are various ways to detect it. Which of the statement is true in regard to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct sequencing can’t be used in the case if the template DNA is heterozygous at the locus",
            "b) Direct sequencing can be used if the template DNA is heterozygous at the locus",
            "c) If cloning is done before sequencing, then it is detected via using only a single clone for sequencing",
            "d) In the case several recombinants are used, it can’t go undetected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pipettes are very important in minimizing contamination. Thus they should be designed and used carefully. The pre-PCR and post-PCR stages should be places in separate rooms. While extraction of DNA surface layers should be removed because they might be containing bacteria. Sometimes the use of species specific primers is also very important, thus they should be used carefully."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "If the template DNA belongs to several individual rather than single one, this type of heterogeneity is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heterzygosity",
            "b) Product heterogeneity",
            "c) Population heterogeneity",
            "d) Template heterogeneity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the template DNA is heterozygous at the locus, it can be detected via using direct sequencing. It is so because it would give rise to two different signals at the same nucleotide position at the sequence output. If the cloning is done before sequencing, a single clone won’t be helpful to detect heterogeneity. It is because single clones are derived from a single PCR product. Also, if several recombinants are used, there are chances that they go undetected. "
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Heterogeneity can also arise if DNA is damaged before amplification. Which of the following doesn’t cause DNA damage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amination of bases",
            "b) Chemical cross-linking between the strands",
            "c) Chemical cross-linking within the strands",
            "d) Slowing down the polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the template DNA belongs to several individuals then this type of heterogeneity is known as population heterogeneity. It also gives rise to heterogeneity in PCR products."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "If cytosine is deaminated, which of the base is formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thymine",
            "b) Guanine",
            "c) Adenine",
            "d) Uracil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are various reasons for DNA damage such as chemical cross-linking both between and within the strands. Deamination of bases is also one of the reasons. If polymerase is slowed down there are chances of incorporation of incorrect bases."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the statement is correct for misincorporation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If direct sequencing has carried this misincorporation is a great problem",
            "b) The erroneous molecules give strong signals than genuine molecules in case of misincorporation",
            "c) If the misincorporation in cloned PCR products it is a problem",
            "d) Even if the error is induced at an early stage it is not incorporated in many sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If cytosine is deaminated it leads to the formation of Uracil. This Uracil is further read as Thymine during DNA synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Errors can be introduced because of many reasons such as polymerase error or because of heterogeneity. Which of the statement holds true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The error caused because of polymerase is biased for the first position in the codon",
            "b) The error caused because of polymerase is evenly distributed on all the positions in the codon",
            "c) The error caused by sequence heterogeneity is mainly because of first position in the codon",
            "d) The error caused by sequence heterogeneity is evenly distributed on all the codon positions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the misincorporation takes place and direct sequencing is carried out, it is not a major problem. It is so because only small portion of molecules have it and thus the signals are weaker than that of genuine molecules. If the misincorporation is in cloned PCR product, it is of great problem. It is so because if it is included at an early stage, they are incorporated in many sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which of the statement is incorrect for jumping PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used in the case when the DNA fragment is degraded",
            "b) In this type of PCR, the molecules are not long enough to span between the two primer sites",
            "c) At the end of first round of synthesis, the extension of the molecule from the primer site to the end of the fragmented molecule takes place",
            "d) It doesn’t leads to the formation of chimeric product"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The error caused by polymerase whether due to template change or not, it is always distributed evenly over all the codon positions. If the error is caused by sequence heterogeneity is concentrated on the third codon position. It generally doesn’t leads to amino acid substitution."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "What are the possibilities which can occur until the temperature has reached for primer annealing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extension doesn’t starts until the appropriate temperature is reached",
            "b) Extension may start even when the temperature is low",
            "c) At low temperature, there is specific annealing of primer taking place",
            "d) There are more specific products which are generated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Until the temperature has reached for primer annealing there are chances of extension by polymerase. It is so because at low temperatures primer can anneal in a non specific manner and thus non specific products are generated."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Hot-start PCR is a modification of PCR. Which of the following is not corresponding to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The basis is that extension is not started until the first cycle reaches its maximum temperature",
            "b) The polymerase is added after the first cycle has reached its maximum temperature or melting temperature",
            "c) It is satisfactory for small number of samples",
            "d) It leads to generation of non specific products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hot-start PCR is a modification which is used in order to overcome the problem of the extension before the maximum temperature of first cycle is reached. Hence, polymerase is added only after the maximum temperature for first cycle is reached. Hence, there are more specific products which are generated because proper annealing of primers has taken place. It is suitable for a small number of samples but not for a large number of samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "An alternative to adding polymerase at later stage is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Make the polymerase inactive by binding it to an antibody",
            "b) Introduce the polymerase or Magnesium in clay beads",
            "c) Make the polymerase inactive by attaching groups which cause stearic inhindrance",
            "d) Introduction of polymerase or Magnesium in plastic wires"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An alternative to start the extension at higher temperature is to make the polymerase inactive by binding an antibody to it. The antibody detaches itself at a higher temperature and thus polymerase is activated at higher temperature. Also, the polymerase or Magnesium can be introduced into wax beads and these beads melt at higher temperatures. Magnesium is required for the polymerase to function."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Touch-down PCR is another modification. Its characteristics include:",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lowering the temperature for primer annealing",
            "b) Primer annealing is done at higher temperatures initially",
            "c) The temperature is abruptly reduced in the second cycle",
            "d) In earlier cycles less stringent conditions are there and in later cycles, more stringent conditions are there"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The primer annealing temperature is often very low from the maximum temperature. Though the low temperature is for stable binding of the template and the primer but at times it leads to mismatches."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "If two successive PCR are carried out, it is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Touch-down PCR",
            "b) Hot-start PCR",
            "c) Combined PCR",
            "d) Nested PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is done in order to overcome the slight mismatch which takes place at lower temperatures. For this, initially the temperature is kept very high and it is reduced in further cycles. As the temperature is reduced, a stage is reduced at which correct primer-template binding is possible but not the incorrect one. In this, in the earlier cycles more stringent conditions are there and in later cycles less stringent conditions are there."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "If two successive PCRs are carried out, in which PCR there are chances of having a non-specific product?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First PCR",
            "b) Second PCR",
            "c) Both the PCRs",
            "d) It depends on the annealing temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nested PCR is that in which two PCRs are carried out. In the first PCR, it uses a conventional template and the second PCR is carried out using the product of first PCR as a template."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "The process of inserting an amplified PCR product in a vector for cloning is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) making library",
            "b) insertion",
            "c) making a hard copy",
            "d) making a PCR based vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If two successive PCRs are carried out, there are non-specific products created in the first PCR. But there are least chances that non-specific products also have annealing sites for both the primers in the second PCR. Hence, non specific products are not generated in the second PCR."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "How can PCR product be cloned into a vector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be done only when PCR products are blunt-ended",
            "b) It can be done only by restriction enzyme digestion",
            "c) Both the methods can be used",
            "d) The blunt-ended approach is favoured"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of inserting an amplified PCR product in a vector for cloning is termed as making a hard copy. It is further maintained by conventional means."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect regarding the cloning of PCR products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In cloning via restriction enzymes, restriction sites are induced before amplification is carried out",
            "b) The restriction sites are induced in the primers before annealing",
            "c) The intermediate molecules are having restriction sites at both ends",
            "d) The amplified molecules can be cut at both the ends by appropriate enzymes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PCR product can be cloned into a vector if the DNA molecules are blunt ended or it can also be done by restriction enzyme digestion. In restriction enzyme digestion restriction sites are introduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Topoisomerse I is also used for cloning of PCR product at times. Which of the statement holds true for such type of cloning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The restriction site is induced into the vector and the topisomerase enzyme is induced into the PCR primers",
            "b) The topoismerase I is used for cutting both the strands",
            "c) The induction of topoisomerase enzyme is done into the vector in the case it is very small in size",
            "d) The restriction site is induced into the PCR primers and the topoisomerase enzyme is induced into the vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If cloning is done via restriction enzymes, restriction sites are induced before amplification. The restriction sites are induced in the primers before annealing. As the primer binds, the restriction sites are induced at one end of the intermediate molecule. In full length molecules, restriction sites are at both ends. And the amplified molecules can be cut at both the ends by appropriate enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Generally, amplification is carried out between the PCR primers. But if amplification is carried out outside the primers, it is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inverse PCR",
            "b) Circular PCR",
            "c) Non-conventional PCR",
            "d) In-situ PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the case of this type of cloning, the restriction site is induced into the PCR primers and the enzyme is induced into the vector. The enzyme cuts the PCR product at the restriction site and joins it to the vector. Topoisomerase I is responsible for cutting only one strand and Topoisomerase II cuts both the strands."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not done if amplification of the non flanking region is carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Firstly, restriction enzyme digestion is done of those sites whose sequence is not known",
            "b) Then the self-ligation of molecules is allowed",
            "c) Now the molecules are cleaved where the known sequence is",
            "d) Again, the molecules are linearized and the known sequence is in the middle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If such amplification has to be carried out, firstly the restriction enzyme digestion is done at those sites whose sequence is not known till now. Then self ligation is carried out i.e. conditions for intramolecular ligation is applied. As the molecules circularize now, cleavage is carried out of known sequence. As the known sequence is cleaved, the molecule is now cleaved with a known sequence at the ends. As it known sequence, primers can be constructed for it and the unknown region is amplified."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Reverse transciptase PCR is also carried out at times. Which of the statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplification of RNA samples is not required for knowing the abundance of mRNA",
            "b) Both the start and the end primers are used",
            "c) Only a single cDNA strand is synthesized before the PCR",
            "d) The primer used is always specific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reverse transciptase PCR is carried out by the use of reverse transciptase enzyme. RNA amplification is necessary at times to know the abundance of mRNA. In this only one primer is used and one cDNA strand is synthesized before the PCR. The primer can be oligo-dT for general cDNA synthesis or a specific primer is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Which type of PCR allows the use of permeabilized tissue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inverse PCR",
            "b) In-situ PCR",
            "c) Quantitative PCR",
            "d) Hot-start PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In-situ PCR allows the use of permeabilized tissue, such as thin sections on a microscopic slide. The PCR product is detected by hybridization and it allows locating the nucleic acid in the target tissue. "
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "How many approaches are there for measuring the quantity of PCR products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are basically two approaches for measuring the amount of PCR products. These are known as end-point approach and real time approach. In end-time approach, the amount is measured once the PCR is done. In real time approach the amount is measured while the PCR reaction is still going on. "
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Which of the statement hold true for Quantitative PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A fluorescent dye is used which binds on single stranded DNA molecules",
            "b) SYBR green is an example such type of dye",
            "c) The quantity of DNA is simply measured by measuring the amount of fluorescence",
            "d) This approach is useful if the products are non-specific in nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A fluorescent dye is used which binds on double stranded DNA molecules and SYBR green is an example of such type of dye. The quantity of DNA is measured by simply measuring the amount of fluorescence. It is used only in the case if products are created specifically because it simply relies on binding of the dye to double stranded molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "In another method of quantitative PCR, reporter-quencher set up is used. Which of the statement holds true for this methodology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It allows detection of all double stranded molecules",
            "b) The reporter and quencher are the molecules present on the same probe",
            "c) The quencher is having a fluorescent group",
            "d) Fluorescence is observed only when both the groups are present in proximity to each other"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This method allows the detection of only specific molecules. It is so because the probes are specific for areas to be amplified. The probe consists of reporter at one end and quencher at the other. The reporter consists of the fluorescent group which fluoresce only when the quencher is released. Quencher is released as a specific binding of the probe is taking place. "
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement with regard to quantitative PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) End-point PCR is favourable over real time PCR",
            "b) In real time PCR, quantification is done as the reaction is going on",
            "c) If the product measurement is done after the completion then the measurement is done by target sequence and no other factor affects it",
            "d) If the primers are available in limited amount, then the product obtained is proportional to the target sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If two oilgonucleotides are used, which bind nearby to the target DNA help in quantifying the DNA. The first probe is meant for absorbing light and the second probe absorbs the light emitted by the first one and then re-emits it. DNA is quantified by measuring the fluorescence from the second probe and it is possible only when both the probes are close to each other i.e. they have bound to the location near the target DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "If amplification of one of the strand is favoured, the modification of PCR is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) single-strand PCR",
            "b) partial PCR",
            "c) asymmetric PCR",
            "d) anchored PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Real-time PCR is favourable over end-point PCR. It is so because real-time PCR is performed when the PCR is going on and the end-point PCR is performed when the PCR has been completed. In the end-point PCR, it is limited by the amount of reactants such as primers. If fewer amounts of primers are there, the product formed is less and is not proportional to the amount of target sequence only."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the statement is incorrect for anchored PCR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anchored PCR is the modification in which only one piece of the sequence is known and thus one primer",
            "b) The known sequence is attached to the required region of amplification and then further used as a second priming site",
            "c) Fragment the sample DNA and ligate it to known sequence",
            "d) Tails are added enzymatically to the region of known sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mutation is deliberately induced in PCR product at times and the process is termed as mutagenesis. In mutagenesis, primers are constructed in such a way that they correspond to the mutated sequence rather than the original one. "
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Emulsion or droplet PCR is another modification of PCR. Which of the statement holds true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is possible to incorporate the reagents in a lipid drop",
            "b) It refers to the PCR carried out at large scale",
            "c) The temperature variation is not possible easily",
            "d) If there is a single template molecule at the start then amplification results in the mixture and it because of the extent of extension carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the amplification of one of the strand is preferred, it is called asymmetric PCR. This leads to the formation of single stranded products which are having uses such as in sequencing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Isothermal amplification is carried out at times. Which of the statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The repeated heating and cooling required by PCR is not the reason for limiting how quickly the reaction is carried out",
            "b) It is carried out typically at 65 degrees",
            "c) Normal Taq polymerase is used",
            "d) It requires expensive PCR machines to be carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anchored PCR is based on the fact that only a piece of the sequence is known and thus only one primer. The known sequence is attached to the required region of amplification and is further used as a second priming site. The sample DNA is fragmented and ligated to known sequence. Also, enzymatically tails are added to the sample DNA or to the molecules formed after first round of synthesis. This tail can be further used as a primer."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Plasmids are used for carrying out the cloning procedure. Which of the statement is true for plasmids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacterial plasmids are linear in nature",
            "b) They are single stranded",
            "c) Insertion of DNA into plasmid allows it to be propagated in host cells and they are known as vectors because of their this property",
            "d) They are not capable of replication in bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasmids are double stranded and they are circular in nature. They are capable of replication in bacteria. Insertion of DNA into plasmid allows it to be propagated in host cells and the molecules which are used for propagation by this method are called as vectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following characteristic is not present in a plasmid on a general basis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple cloning site (MCS)",
            "b) Origin of replication (ori)",
            "c) Antibiotic resistance gene",
            "d) Beta galactose genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasmid generally consists of characteristics such as multiple cloning site, origin of replication, antibiotic resistant genes and beta galactosidase genes. An origin of replication is necessary for the replication to take place. "
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Bla is a gene, which is incorrect for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an antibiotic resistance genes",
            "b) Antibiotic acts by blocking the cross-linking of the bacterial cell wall and thus leading to lysing of cells",
            "c) It encodes beta lactamase enzyme",
            "d) The beta lactam ring is activated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bla is an ampicillin resistant gene. Antibiotic acts by blocking the cross-linking in the bacterial cell wall and thus leading to lysing of the cells. If antibiotic resistant gene is used, which encodes for beta lactamase enzyme it inactivates the beta lactam gene by hydrolysing it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Which of the characteristics is present in lacZ gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It encodes for beta galactosidase enzyme",
            "b) Beta galactosidase enzyme is responsible for cleaving monosaccharides into the constituent elements",
            "c) It doesn’t cleaves a substrate called as X-gal",
            "d) But if X-gal is cleaved, it liberates pink coloured dye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: lacZ gene encodes for beta galactosidase enzyme. This enzyme is responsible for cleaving of disaccharides into monosaccharides. It cleaves a substrate known as X-gal, which then liberates a blue dye."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following orientation is not propagated to later stages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular plasmids having genomic DNA",
            "b) Intramolecular ligation of plasmids",
            "c) Linear molecules",
            "d) Head to head ligation of two DNA plasmids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When a cloning experiment is carried out, there various orientations which are possible. The orientation which is not propagated to the later stages is a linear molecule. Other possible orientations are relegation of plasmid, intramolecular ligation of genomic DNA. Intermolecular ligation of two DNA plasmids and genomic plasmids is also possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Molecules having new combination of sequences that were not present before are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) intermolecular ligants",
            "b) recombinants",
            "c) couple",
            "d) intramolecular ligants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After cloning experiment is carried out, there are various orientations possible. Molecules having combination of new sequences which were not present earlier are called as recombinants."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Transformation efficiency is defined as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ratio of transformed colonies by microgram of sample DNA that is to be inserted",
            "b) ratio of transformed colonies by amount of sample DNA that is to be inserted",
            "c) ratio of transformed colonies by microgram of plasmid DNA",
            "d) ratio of transformed colonies by amount of plasmid DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Insertion of DNA into lacZ gene may lead to disruption of the gene function. It always doesn’t so but there are minimal chances that function is not disrupted because often it leads to shifting of the reading frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "After carrying out the cloning experiment, the cells are plated on agar. Along with agar, it also contains antibiotic resistant genes, X-gal and an inducer of lacZ gene. Which of the following would grow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cells that have taken up plasmid DNA",
            "b) Cells that have taken up genomic DNA",
            "c) Cells having no insert",
            "d) Cells either having no insert or having genomic DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Transformation efficiency is defined as the ratio of transformed colonies to that of the amount of plasmid DNA which is taken. It is often altered by altering the competence of the cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true regarding taking up of plasmid DNA in the bacterial cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are more chances of having two plasmids in a single cell",
            "b) There are more chances of having a single plasmid in one cell",
            "c) Uptake upto two plasmids is possible but not more than that",
            "d) Both are taken up with the same efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are more chances of having a single plasmid in one cell. But there are possibilities of having two plasmids in a single cell but the chances are less."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "If genomic DNA has been inserted instead of the plasmid, what will happen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It would lead to inactivation of lacZ gene",
            "b) The X-gal substrate would be broken down",
            "c) The colonies formed are blue in colour",
            "d) The lacZ gene would be intact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If genomic DNA is inserted instead of the plasmid the lacZ gene would be inactivated. The X-gal substrate won’t be broken down and thus the colonies formed would be white or off-white."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Often PCR can be performed in order to confirm whether an insert is present in the plasmid. Cells are taken directly and PCR is performed, this type of PCR is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) direct PCR",
            "b) colony PCR",
            "c) quantitative PCR",
            "d) in-situ PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When cells from colonies are taken and directly PCR is performed, it is called as colony PCR. Primers anneal to each side of the cloning site and there is no need of purification in such cases."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Generation of recombinants by randomly cloning fragments of total DNA from an organism is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) genomic library",
            "b) screening",
            "c) recombination",
            "d) shotgun cloning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Generation of recombinants by randomly cloning the fragments of total DNA from an organism is called as shotgun cloning. Collection of such fragments is known as a library."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "The phenomenon of alpha complementation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) α + β = ω",
            "b) α = β + ω",
            "c) β = α + ω",
            "d) It is either α + β = ω or β = α + ω"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alpha complementation is the phenomenon of having the alpha and beta subunit combining to give the omega subunit. These are the different genes of the lac operon."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "An operon is defined as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A related set of genes each having different promoters and are present differently",
            "b) A set of genes which are present together but are controlled by different promoters",
            "c) A set of genes which are present together and are controlled by the same promoter",
            "d) A set of genes which are not present together but controlled by the same promoter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An operon is defined as the cluster of genes which are present together and are controlled by the same promoter. An example is lac operon. It consists of three subunits, alpha, beta and omega."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Why the whole lacZ gene can’t be present in the plasmid at one time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because the whole lacZ gene can’t be present anywhere",
            "b) The whole lac Z gene is very large in size and the plasmid size is small",
            "c) The whole lacZ gene is never functional",
            "d) Because the plasmid takes is having a restriction site only for taking up a portion of the lacZ gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The whole lacZ gene is not present in a plasmid because the plasmids are generally small in size and the lacZ gene is large in size. And if the whole gene is present, it makes the overall size very large."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Alpha complementation is an indicator of lacZ system. Which of the statement is incorrect for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One portion of the lacZ gene known as minigene is present in the plasmid",
            "b) Another portion is present in the host itself",
            "c) If they both are allowed to combine in the presence of IPTG, X-gal and ampicillin, blue colonies are observed",
            "d) If insert is also present along with host and plasmid, it results in the formation of blue colonies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alpha complementation system is used as a lacZ indicator system. In this, one portion of the lacZ gene is present in the plasmid and is termed as minigene. The other portion is present in the host itself. The combining of two portions is very important to have an intact lacZ gene and in the case, it is intact blue colonies are observed in the presence of IPTG, ampicillin and X-gal. It is so because lacZ breaks down X-gal and it gives blue colour. If the insert is also there, the lacZ gene is interrupted and thus X-gal is not broken down and hence white colonies are obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "What will be the consequence of not having an origin of replication (ori) in the vector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If an ori is absent, replication of vector would not take place",
            "b) As the cells divide after taking up the vector, both the daughter cells would be having the vector",
            "c) A colony of transformed colonies is observed",
            "d) The vector won’t be taken up by the cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case ori is absent, the vector won’t be able to replicate. As the replication won’t take place, only one of the daughter cells would be having the vector. A colony of transformed colonies won’t be obtained. The puc18 ori came from a plasmid in clinical bacterial isolate and was called as pMB1."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "It is required to distinguish between the cells that have taken up the vector and that have not. It is done by using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) multiple cloning site",
            "b) origin of replication",
            "c) high copy number",
            "d) selectable marker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Whether the cell has taken up the vector or not is distinguished by using a selectable marker. A selectable marker often used is the ampcillin resistance property. Cells having the plasmid or vector show resistance against ampicillin."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Multiple cloning site (MCS) is defined as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) site within the plasmid which contains a site for many restriction enzymes",
            "b) site within the plasmid which contains a site for many restriction enzymes and they are not present anywhere else in the plasmid",
            "c) as the site containing many sites for only one restriction enzyme",
            "d) cloning many inserts together"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MCS is defined as a location in the plasmid which is having the site for many restriction enzymes and they are not present anywhere else in the plasmid."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "If a restriction site is 6 nucleotides long, what are the chances of finding it in a vector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Once every 46 base pairs",
            "b) Once every 64 base pairs",
            "c) Once every 24 base pairs",
            "d) Once every 16 base pairs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The size of vector is related to having a suitable single restriction site. It is so because; if the vector is large in size there are more chances of having that sequence in the vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Which of the statement is true for pBR322?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It contains only an ampicillin resistance gene",
            "b) It contains both ampicillin resistant and tetracycline resistant gene",
            "c) The cloning site is present only in the ampicillin resistant gene",
            "d) It is a natural vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a restriction site is 6 nucleotides long, the chances for having it in a vector are once in every 46 base pairs. It is so because there are 4 nucleotides which form the DNA and at six positions, they can form 46 combinations."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "If a plasmid is having two antibiotic resistant genes, say ampicillin resistant and chloramphenicol resistant. If the plasmid grows in ampicillin containing medium but not in chloramphenicol, what can be concluded?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The insert is not present in any of the gene",
            "b) The insert is present in ampicillin gene but not in chloramphenicol gene",
            "c) The insert is present in choramphenicol gene but not in ampicillin gene",
            "d) The insert is present between both of the genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: pBR 322 is the man-made vector. It contains both ampicillin resistant and tetracycline resistant genes. The cloning site is also present in both of the genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "If high copy number is there, the replication is called as ______ and if low copy number is there the replication is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) stringent, relaxed",
            "b) relaxed, stringent",
            "c) relaxed, relaxed",
            "d) stringent, stringent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The insert is present in the chloramphenicol gene and not in the ampicillin gene. As the insert is present in it, it disrupts its function and hence they are not able to grow in chloramphenicol containing a medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Chloramphenicol amplification is carried out in various plasmids. Which of the statement is incorrect for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used for increasing copy number in plasmids containing pMB1 origin",
            "b) Chloramphenicol promotes bacterial protein synthesis",
            "c) The protein synthesis is responsible for chromosomal DNA replication",
            "d) Chromosomal DNA replication is related to cell division"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If high copy number is there, the replication is known as stringent and if the copy number is low, the replication is known as relaxed."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "The phenomenon of not allowing the recombinants to escape into the environment is termed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) blocking",
            "b) termination",
            "c) disablement",
            "d) inactivation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chloramphenicol amplification is used for increasing the copy number in plasmids containing the pMB1 origin. It is responsible for inhibiting bacterial protein synthesis. As the bacterial protein synthesis is inhibited, chromosomal DNA replication is also inhibited. Chromosomal DNA replication is related to cell division and it is also blocked. But the plasmid replication is not inhibited and it replicates."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "How will we choose which transformation method is to be used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It depends on the available conditions for the reaction to take place",
            "b) It depends on the efficiency which is required to be obtained",
            "c) All the transformation methods can be used equivalently",
            "d) Each reaction has been assigned a particular transformation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The choice of transformation method to be used is based upon the efficiency which is desired in the reaction which has to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "The cell in which the recombinant molecules are propagated is termed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) host",
            "b) vector",
            "c) plasmid",
            "d) carrier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hosts are the cells which are used for propagation of recombinant molecules. The choice of a correct host is very important."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Some mutations are present which assist the uptake of DNA. Which of the statement is incorrect for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) deoR is such a mutation which assists the uptake of DNA",
            "b) It is a transcriptional regulator",
            "c) It is having DNA binding activity",
            "d) It controls the expression of a set of genes involved ribonucleoside catabolism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are various factors which affect the uptake of DNA by the cells. deoR is an example of such a mutation which assists the uptake of DNA. It is a transcriptional regulator and is having DNA binding activity. It controls the expression of a set of genes involved in deoxyribonucleoside catabolism."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for K strain for E. coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It contains restriction-modification system which is encoded by hsDMRS locus",
            "b) hsDR encodes for endonuclease which is responsible for cleaving the DNA sequence containing –AACGCNNTGC-",
            "c) Cleavage is carried out when the second A is non methylated",
            "d) hsDR mutation can be used for cleavage of incoming unprotected DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Endogenous DNA-degrading system is essential in determining the transformation efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Methylation dependent restriction system (MDRS) are included in which class of restriction enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type I",
            "b) Type II",
            "c) Type III",
            "d) They are the product of mcrA, mcrB or mrr loci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It consists of K restriction-modification system which is encoded by hsDMRS locus. hsDR encodes for endonuclease which is responsible for cleaving the DNA sequencing containing –AACNNNNNNGTGC-. Cleavage takes place only in the case when the second A and the A opposite to T in the second strand is methylated. This mutation can be used to avoid cleavage of incoming unprotected DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement with respect to dam and dcm genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Their enzymes are responsible for methylation of DNA",
            "b) Dam protein methylates cytosine in –GATC-",
            "c) Dcm methylates cytosine in-CCAGG- and –CCTGG- sequences",
            "d) The extent of methylation also has effects on the efficiency with which the other restriction enzymes cleave the DNA in vitro"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: MDRS don’t come under the general classification of type I-III. They are the product of mcrA, mcrB and mrr loci. It would degrade DNA containing methylcytosine (mcrA, mcrB) or methyladenine (mrr)."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "How many recombination systems are present in E. coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The enzymes of dam and dcm genes are responsible for mrthylation of DNA. Dam protein methylates adenine in –GATC- and dcm methylates cytosine in –CCAGG- and –CCTGG- sequences. The extent of methylation also has effects on the efficiency with which the other restriction enzymes cleave DNA in vitro."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Disablement is also done in plasmids. Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The strains carrying out the recombinant plasmids should not escape outside",
            "b) Preferred strains are having mutations which allow their growth in wild",
            "c) Mutations confer prototrophy",
            "d) If the recombinants escape outside, there is no such harm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are mainly three recombination systems in E.coli. They are the products of recBCD, recE and recF genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "endA mutation is often induced in host molecules. Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It activates the gene for DNA-specific endonuclease",
            "b) It enhances the yield of plasmid DNA preparations only",
            "c) It enhances the quality of plasmid DNA preparations only",
            "d) It enhances both the quality and yield of plasmid DNA preparations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Disablement is also done in plasmids, in order to ensure that the recombinant plasmids don’t escape outside. If they escape outside, it causes contamination. Preferred strains are having mutations which don’t allow their growth in the wild. Mutations confer autotrophy. Autotrophy is the condition of the introduction of particular metabolites in the medium because they are not synthesized. The opposite of autotrophy is called as prototrophy."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "lacZΔM15 represents __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fully present lacZ gene",
            "b) it is not required in alpha complementation",
            "c) it represents the lacZ gene with M15 mutation",
            "d) it is partially deleted lacZ gene which is needed for alpha complementation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: endA mutation is often induced in host molecules. It inactivates the gene for DNA-specific endonuclease. It enhances both the yield and quality of plasmid DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "The correct statement with respect to lacIq is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a mutant of lac repressor gene and decreases the level of repressor",
            "b) It doesn’t control the lacZ gene",
            "c) It is important for the vectors to replicate in a low copy number",
            "d) It doesn’t titrate out the repressor produced by wild type Lac-I gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The representation is for a partially deleted lacZ gene and it is very important for alpha complementation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "There are various methods to distinguish whether a colony contains a recombinant or not. One such method is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) blue white screening",
            "b) checking whether replication is taking place or not",
            "c) checking the number of copies",
            "d) looking for the multiple cloning site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blue white screening is a method to know whether a colony is having a recombinant or not. It is also known as alpha complementation method. It is based on the lacZ operon. If there is an insert, the colonies are white in colour and if there is no insert, the colonies are blue in colour."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "At times it is observed that non-recombinant plasmids are more than that of recombinant plasmids. Choose the correct statement in regard to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It makes easier to get the recombinant plasmids from the mixture",
            "b) The ratio of insert DNA to vector DNA is reduced to get recombinant plasmids",
            "c) Alkaline phosphatase is used to get recombinant plasmids",
            "d) Alkaline phosphatase method is less reliable in comparison to the ratio method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Often the recombination plasmids are less in number as compared to non-recombination plasmids. This makes it difficult to get the recombination plasmids from the mixture. In order to overcome this, the ratio of insert DNA to vector DNA is increased. Another more reliable method is to use the alkaline phosphatase method."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Alkaline Phosphatase is used at times and the vector is treated with it. Choose the incorrect statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It removes 5’ terminal phosphate group from nucleic acids",
            "b) The 5’ phosphate group is required for the ligation to take place",
            "c) Two phosphate bonds should be formed for the complete ligation to take place",
            "d) The ligation between vector and insert won’t take place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alkaline phosphatase is used at times and the vector is treated with it. It is responsible for the removal of phosphatase group from the 5’ end. This group is required for the ligation reaction to take place and at each end two phosphates are required. But as the phosphate groups are removed from the vector, its relegation is not possible now. But as the insert is still having a phosphate group, one strand will form the bond and the ligation reaction will take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What is the correct time for carrying out the alkaline phosphatase treatment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) After the cutting of vector has been done",
            "b) Before the insert DNA and the vector are mixed",
            "c) After the cutting of vector has been done but before the insert DNA and vector are mixed",
            "d) After the mixing of insert DNA and vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The alkaline phosphatase treatment is carried out after the cutting of DNA has been done but before the mixing of insert DNA and vector has been done. There should be no traces of the enzyme left after the insert DNA has been added."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "ccdB gene is used at times. Choose the correct statement with respect to this gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a control of cell birth gene",
            "b) It is activated in complex vectors to increase the fraction of recombinants",
            "c) If intramolecular ligation takes place this protein is released",
            "d) It is often regarded as control of cell death and birth gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is an approach to increase the fraction of recombinants. There are some genes which are activated on the self ligation of the molecules and are responsible for the death of host molecules. ccdB is control of cell death gene and its protein is responsible for killing the host molecules when intramolecular ligation takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "When inserting a DNA fragment, it is possible to have two orientations. If the orientation is controlled, this cloning is referred to as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) forced cloning",
            "b) orientation cloning",
            "c) correct cloning",
            "d) restricted cloning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is possible to insert the DNA fragment into two possible orientations. If somehow it is controlled to insert the fragment in a particular orientation, it is known as forced cloning. "
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "What happens if insert DNA is cut with two different restriction enzymes at the ends?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is difficult to insert the fragment",
            "b) The insert can be ligated in any orientation",
            "c) The insert can be ligated in one orientation only",
            "d) The amount of product increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the DNA is cut with two different enzymes at the ends, it is possible to ligate the fragment in only one orientation. It is so because each end would have a unique sequence to ligate."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "What is the disadvantage of amplification of using PCR over natural cloning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In PCR, there is no proof reading activity",
            "b) In PCR, small fragments can’t be amplified",
            "c) There is an A incorporated in PCR products, which makes cloning difficult",
            "d) PCR takes more time as compared to natural cloning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The biggest disadvantage of using PCR amplification over natural cloning is that there is no proof reading activity in the case of PCR. Thus if an error is induced, it is carried forward and is amplified. Also, if large fragments are to be cloned, natural cloning is preferred over PCR. The incorporated A at ends makes the process of cloning of PCR products easier. "
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "TA cloning is a method used for cloning of PCR products. Which of the statement is correct with respect to it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is based on the fact that a T residue is incorporated at the end of the PCR product",
            "b) ‘A’ residue is incorporated into the end of the vector",
            "c) It gives a low yield",
            "d) It is preferred over blunt end ligation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: TA cloning is a method used for cloning of PCR products. It is based on the fact that A residue is present at the 3’ end of the PCR product and thus now T residue is incorporated at the end of the vector. It is preferred over blunt end ligation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement in respect to topoisomerase I.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used to cleave only one DNA strand",
            "b) It leaves at the recognition sequence –C/TCCTT- and is covalently attached to one end of the cleaved molecule",
            "c) The supercoiling of the DNA strand is altered and then it is sealed again by the enzyme",
            "d) It is slower than the normal DNA ligase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Topoisomerase I is an enzyme used for cleaving of one DNA strand. It leaves at the recognition sequence –C/TCCTT- and is covalently attached to one end of the cleaved molecule. The supercoiling of the DNA strand is altered and then it sealed by the enzyme again. It is usually faster than DNA ligase. Topoisomerase II is used for cleaving both the strands."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Linkers are often used in cloning. Choose the incorrect statement for linkers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) These are short chemically synthesized molecules that contain a particular restriction enzyme site within the sequence",
            "b) They are blunt ended molecules",
            "c) They are ligated to staggered ended insert molecules by T4 DNA ligase",
            "d) After treatment with enzyme, both the ends of the linker are staggered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Linkers are often used in cloning. These are short chemically synthesized molecules that contain a particular restriction enzyme site within the sequence. They are blunt ended molecules and are ligated to the blunt ended insert molecules by T4 DNA ligase. After treatment with the enzyme, both the ends of the linker are staggered."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for adaptors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are blunt ended at both the ends",
            "b) They are single stranded at both the ends",
            "c) They may be single stranded at one end and other end may be blunt",
            "d) They don’t have extra restriction sites within their sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the insert itself is having a restriction site, the insert itself is cleaved when the restriction enzyme is cleaved along with the linker. To avoid this, the methylation of the site in the insert is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "If linkers are combined with other features such as a selectable marker, it is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cassette",
            "b) modified linker",
            "c) adaptors",
            "d) induced linker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adaptors are molecules which are used for cloning. There is no restriction on the type of end they have. Either of the ends can be blunt or staggered. They may also have extra restriction site within the sequence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "F (fertility) factor is used in many bacterial systems for different purposes. Choose the incorrect statement with respect to the F factor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It was identified in E. coli for catalysing genetic exchange between cells",
            "b) Cells having F factor are called as female",
            "c) The F factor is transferred from one cell to another via factors present outside",
            "d) They are not related to BAC systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: BAC vectors are based on the F (fertility) factor. They are known for transferring genetic material between cells and they do it by a proteinaceous filament called sex pilus. The cells having F factor are called as male cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "F factor integration into the host chromosome is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) F’ plasmid",
            "b) F factor and host chromosome recombination",
            "c) Hfr (High frequency of recombination)",
            "d) Recombinant host chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: F factor integration can be done into the host chromosome and this is called as Hfr (High frequency of recombination) strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Excision of the F factor can also be done from the host chromosome. Choose the incorrect statement in respect to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) This excision is possible in vivo",
            "b) Along with the F factor, host chromosome’s DNA sequences are also excited",
            "c) The sequences of host chromosome which can be accommodated in the F plasmid are small in size",
            "d) These plasmids are termed as F’ plasmids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It is possible to carry out the excision of the F factor from the host chromosome. The excision is possible in vivo. Along with the F factor, the DNA sequences of host chromosome are also excised. The F plasmid is able to accommodate very large size f host chromosome fragments and these are known as F’ plasmids."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for BAC vector system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) BAC vector system stands for bacteria and chromosome",
            "b) It usually accepts insert of size approximately 1000kbp",
            "c) The repE and oriS sequences are required for controlling the copy number and par A-C sequences are required for replication",
            "d) A selectable marker is there for chloramphenicol resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually, the F plasmids are present in a low copy number in cells. These low copy numbers are very essential for the stability because then only a few molecules can act as substrates for recombination mediated deletion."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "The bacteriophage M13 vectors belong to a group of phages called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) skinny or filamentous phage",
            "b) M phage group",
            "c) single stranded phage",
            "d) double stranded phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BAC vector system stands for Bacterial Artificial Chromosome. It accepts an insert of size 100kbp-300kbp. The repE and oriS sequences are required for controlling the replication and the par A-C sequences are required for controlling the copy number. A selectable marker is there for chloramphenicol resistance. A lacZ gene is also present and recombination of BAC vectors is done into E. coli by electropoartion."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for the infection process of M13.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The infectious particle is double stranded",
            "b) It is contained in a protein coat which is made up of products of gene III or gene VIII",
            "c) The phage infects only female cells",
            "d) The phage enters the bacterial cells by the filament which is meant for movement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteriophage M13 vectors belong to a group of vectors known as skinny or filamentous phage. They have a dimension of 850 nm * 6 nm * 6nm. They are very useful as they convert the double stranded DNA into single stranded DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Once the bacteriophage enters the bacterial cells, some changes are carried out in it. Which of the following is not included?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The single stranded molecule entering the cell is single stranded and is called as a + strand",
            "b) The single stranded molecule is converted into double stranded molecule which is called as replicative form (RF)",
            "c) It is carried out in a process similar to normal replication process of E. coli",
            "d) The positive strand is used for the transcription of viral proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: M13 infectious particles are single stranded in nature. It is contained in a protein coat which is made up of products of gene III or gene VIII. The phage infects the bacterial cells by sex pilus and thus it infects only male cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Replication can also be carried out by rolling circle replication. Choose the correct statement for this type of replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be used for the formation of RF",
            "b) The product of gene III binds on a specific site of double stranded genome",
            "c) It creates a nick in the – strand generating a free 3’ hydroxyl",
            "d) This strand is extended by the polymerase and displaces the original – strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Once the bacteriophage enters the bacterial cells it is converted into double stranded form from the single stranded form. The double stranded form is known as replicative form (RF). The single strand enteri g is called as a + strand. It is carried out in a process similar to that the normal replication process. A specific origin of synthesis is used for transcription of the complementary negative strand. The minus strand can be used to synthesize viral proteins. "
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Gene V blocks the production of which gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene III",
            "b) Gene II",
            "c) Gene VIII",
            "d) Gene IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rolling circle replication is used for the formation of RF. The product of gene II binds on a specific site of double stranded genome. It creates a nick in the + strand generating a free 3’ hydroxyl. This strand is extended by the polymerase and it displaces the original + strand. This strand is removed from the newly synthesized strand because of another nick by gene II. Thus a separate + strand is created and it is circularized by gene II product. "
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "What is the size of the DNA molecule which can be packed by the viral protein coat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100kbp",
            "b) 200kbp",
            "c) 500kbp",
            "d) No size restriction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is no size restriction on the DNA molecule which is packaged by the viral coat protein. It is an advantage."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "The uniform layer of cells is known as lawn and the holes peppered from infected cells are termed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plaques",
            "b) holes",
            "c) colony",
            "d) pothole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The infected cells, which are from the infection by bacteriophage create holes and they are termed as plaques."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "The plaques formed by M13 infection are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) retarded plaques",
            "b) true plaques",
            "c) pseudoplaques",
            "d) lysogenized plaques"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: M13 doesn’t actually lyse the cells. It infects the cells and retards the growth but doesn’t actually lyse the cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "M13 vector is tightly packed. Where is the available site to insert DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the gene II",
            "b) Between gene II and IV",
            "c) Between gene III and V",
            "d) Between gene V and VIII"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the plaques created by M13 are because of slow growth and not because of lysis, these plaques are called as pseudoplaques. "
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement with respect to the collection of single stranded molecules.",
        "Options": [
            "a) An infected culture is set up and after a while the cells are removed by centrifugation",
            "b) The phage is in the supernatant and is precipitated by addition of glycol and sodium chloride",
            "c) The phage pellet is resuspended and phenol is used for removal of protein",
            "d) The single stranded molecules sediment at the bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The production of phage depends upon the insertion of DNA without disrupting any of the phage genes. Hence, M13 vector is tightly packed. One such site for the insertion of DNA is between gene II and gene IV. Here, the lacZ and MCS are also present."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for Sanger’s method of sequencing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are also called as chain termination methods",
            "b) Use of M13 vector is made for getting double stranded DNA",
            "c) Use of dideoxynucleotide phosphate (ddNTP) is made",
            "d) The use of M13 vectors is more preferred these days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The collection of single stranded molecules is slightly different. An infected culture is set up and after a while cells are removed by centrifugation. The phage is present in the supernatant and is precipitated by addition of glycol and sodium chloride. It is followed by centrifugation. The phage pellet is resuspended and phenol is used for removal of protein. The single stranded molecules remain in the solution and thus can be precipitated further."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the statement doesn’t holds for phage display systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The filamentous phage is often used as phage display system",
            "b) Coding sequences are inserted in one of the protein coating genes",
            "c) The most common protein coding genes are gene II or gene VIII",
            "d) The inserted is expressed along with other protein coat genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sanger’s method of DNA sequencing is also known as the chain termination method of sequencing. Dideoxynucleoside triphospahte (ddNTP) are used as chain terminating agents. M13 vector is used to obtain the single stranded DNA. Now a days there are technologies available for sequencing on double stranded DNA, thus it reduces the use of M13 vectors these days."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for the synthesis of RNA probe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double stranded DNA is only used for probe synthesis",
            "b) Single stranded DNA can be used for probe synthesis",
            "c) Probes are prepared for RNA transcripts which are specific for only particular strand",
            "d) Probes are prepared for RNA transcripts which are specific for both the strands"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The filamentous phage is often used as phage display system. The coding sequences are inserted in one of the protein coding genes and the most common protein coding genes are gene III and gene VIII. The insert is expressed along with other protein coat genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "M13-plasmid vectors are often used. Which of the following is not a feature for this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are known as phagemid, plage or phasmid",
            "b) Replication takes place through the origin of replication of M13 derivatives only",
            "c) Replication from M13 requires proteins to be provided by helper phage",
            "d) Some of the examples of these types of the combination are pUC 118, 119 and 120"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNA probe can be synthesized by single stranded DNA. This single stranded DNA can be obtained from filamentous phage. Probes are prepared for RNA transcripts which are specific for either of the DNA strands."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "It is very important to study lambda biology as lambda phages are used for cloning purposes. Which of the statement is true for lambda phage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an example of temperate phage",
            "b) The fate of the phage is decided before it infects the cell",
            "c) The lysis fate is that where the phage inserts its genome into the bacterial genome and the replication goes on",
            "d) The lysogenic fate is that where the phage infects the cell and lysis is carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lambda phage is a temperate phage and its fate is decided as it infects the cell. It can be either be lytic or lysogenic in nature. Lytic phage is that which infects the cell and it is lysed whereas lysogenic phage is that in which phage genome is inserted into the bacterial genome and is replicated along with it."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for the infectious particle of lambda phage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is single stranded genome",
            "b) It is circular double stranded genome",
            "c) The ends are blunt with cos (cohesive) sequences",
            "d) The ends are created by cleavage at cos sites during phage packaging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The infectious particle of lambda phage id linear double stranded genome. The ends are staggered with cos (cohesive) sequences and they are created by cleavage at cos sites during phage packaging."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Some changes are encountered in the infectious particle as it infects the cell. Choose the incorrect statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The infectious particle circularizes upon causing infection by annealing at cos sites",
            "b) There are two promoters present, PR and PL",
            "c) Upon infection only PR is activated",
            "d) Promoters give rise to immediate early transcripts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the infectious particle infects the cell it circularizes by annealing at cos sites. Both the promoters PR and PL are activated upon infection. Promoters give rise to immediate early transcripts which terminate at rightward and leftward terminators."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The immediate early transcripts direct synthesis of which genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) N genes",
            "b) cro genes",
            "c) Both N and cro genes",
            "d) PR and PL genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The immediate early transcripts are transcribed by promoters and they direct the synthesis of gene products of N and cro genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What is the function of the N gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It promotes the function of terminators",
            "b) It overrides the function of terminators",
            "c) It promotes the production of the cro gene",
            "d) It is responsible for making the infectious particle linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: N gene is responsible for overriding the function of terminators. As the terminators are overridden, the transcription is carried in the surrounding regions."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for cII gene and its related function?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The transcription is extended to the region of cII gene and it is termed as late transcription",
            "b) They are responsible for deactivating the promoter for repressor establishment",
            "c) This promoter is responsible to decide whether the life cycle would be lysogenic or lytic",
            "d) cII gene is responsible for other gene which is gene cIII"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cII gene product is formed when the transcription is extended because of the overriding of terminators by the N gene. It is responsible for activation of a promoter for repressor establishment. This promoter is responsible for deciding whether it would be in lysogenic or lytic mode. The transcripts formed by extension are called as delayed early transcripts and cIII is also produced along with cII. "
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which gene is required for the lysogenic phage to be adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cI",
            "b) cII",
            "c) cIII",
            "d) All the three genes are interrelated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All three genes are interrelated. The cII gene is protected from proteases by cIII gene and it further promotes the expression of cI gene. cI gene is necessary for silencing of rest of the lambda genome. cII is most important but as it related with other two as well, thus they all are required for lysogenic mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for lysogenic mode.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PRE forms cI gene product which is responsible for activation of promoters",
            "b) The cII protein is responsible for interfering with cro and Q proteins and they are required for lytic life cycle",
            "c) The cII protein activates the promoter PINT",
            "d) The Int protein with host protein is responsible for site specific recombination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cI gene product is responsible for inactivation of promoters and thus silencing rest of the lambda genome. The cII gene product is responsible for interfering with cro and Q proteins and they are required for lytic life cycle. The cII gene also activates promoter PINT and the Int protein produced along with host protein is required for site specific recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for the cI gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It represses only cII gene",
            "b) It activates cII gene and represses cIII gene",
            "c) It represses both cII and cIII gene",
            "d) It activates both cII and cIII gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: cI gene represses both cII and cIII gene and thus the expression of cIII is also suppressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which of the promoter requires a low level of cI gene for its activation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PR",
            "b) PL",
            "c) PRE",
            "d) PRM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The promoter requiring low level of cI gene for its activation is PRM (Promoter for repressor maintenance). It is inactivated by high levels of the cI gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement with respect to lysogen and prophage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The integrated phage is called as lysogen",
            "b) The infected bacterial cell is called a prophage",
            "c) If there is only growth of few lysogens, the E. coli lawn would be turbid",
            "d) If lysogens won’t be formed, the plaques won’t be clear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The integrated phage is called as a prophage and the infected bacterial cell is known as lysogen. Lysogens are immune to further infection by the same phage. If only growth of few lysogens would take place, the lawn would be turbid. In the acse, if lysogens aren’t formed, the plaques would be clear."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for cro and Q proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are required for the lytic life cycle to continue",
            "b) Cro protein inactivates the PRM promoter",
            "c) The Q protein is responsible for the expression of late genes",
            "d) cII protein is required for the lytic life cycle to continue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cro and Q proteins are required for the lytic life cycle to continue and cII protein is not required for it. Cro protein inactivates the PRM promoter and the Q protein is responsible for the expression of late genes. These late genes are responsible for producing coat proteins, allowing assembly of functional phage and cell lysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Induction of lysogen takes place because of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low levels of cII gene",
            "b) Low level of cI gene",
            "c) Low levels of both cI and cII gene",
            "d) High levels of both cI and cII gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Induction of lysogen takes place because of low levels of the cI gene. It is caused by specific proteolysis under the action of host recA protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the phage genes are responsible for phage excision?",
        "Options": [
            "a) xis gene",
            "b) int gene",
            "c) recA protein",
            "d) both xis and int gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the level of cI genes fall, the repression of PR and PL genes is lifted up. Now phage genes are expressed and xis and int genes are expressed. These genes are responsible for causing phage excision."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "How many phases are there for replication of lambda DNA to take place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two phases for the lambda DNA replication to take place. They include the theta mode and rolling circle mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "The phase generating additional circular DNA molecules in the first phase does it by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bidirectional theta mode",
            "b) rolling circle mode",
            "c) separation of the two strands",
            "d) copying only one strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first phase includes circularization of the molecule by annealing of the cos sites and they replicate in a bidirectional theta mode. This leads to the generation of an additional circular DNA molecule."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement with respect to rolling circle replication.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is for a single replication fork and yields a concatemeric molecule",
            "b) Staggered cleavage of DNA takes place at the cos sites",
            "c) The cleavage generates 10 nucleotide long overhangs",
            "d) Without the cos sites, the packaging won’t be possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The second phase constitutes of rolling circle mode. It is done with a single replication fork and yields concatemeric molecules. They are required for assembly into mature phage particles. The packaging region should be flanked by the cos sites. Phage DNA is inserted into the phage head and the cos sites are brought adjacent to each other. It is followed by cleavage at cos sites and it leaves 12 nucleotide long staggered ends. The cos sites are required for packaging to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Insertion vectors are a type of vectors. Choose the correct statement for this type of vector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) These are complex vectors",
            "b) DNA is inserted through many restriction sites",
            "c) There is an upper limit on the size of the DNA to be packaged",
            "d) Lambda gt09 is an example of this type of vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Insertion vectors are the simple vectors and DNA is inserted through a single restriction site. It must be a non-essential gene to maintain phage viability. There is an upper limit on the size of the DNA to be packaged thus only a few kilobases of the extra DNA can be included. Lambda gt10 and gt11 are an example of insertion vectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for lambda gt10.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is having an EcoRI site",
            "b) It is having cII gene",
            "c) It accepts an insert of size greater than that of 8 kbp",
            "d) This size is less than that the size which is generally accepted by wild type phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lambda gt10 is having an EcoRI site which contains the cI repressor gene. It accepts an insert of size upto 7.6 kbp which is generally more than that of the size generally accepted by a wild type phage."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "The presence of insert leads to inactivation of which gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cII",
            "b) cI",
            "c) cIII",
            "d) both cII and cIII"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The presence of insert leads to inactivation of the cI gene and this is the method to detect the presence of an insert."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "A portion of phage is removed and in place of it, the DNA of interest is inserted. This type of vector is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) displacement vector",
            "b) insertion vector",
            "c) substitution vector",
            "d) transposition vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If a portion of phage is removed and in its place, the DNA of interest is inserted, it is called as substitution or replacement vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the central portion of the lambda genome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The central portion is not required for lytic growth",
            "b) The central portion includes repressor gene",
            "c) The repressor gene is not required for lysogenic growth",
            "d) It is approximately 10kbp long"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The central portion of the lambda genome is approximately 20 kbp and it is not required for lytic growth. The central portion constitutes of repressor gene and thus it has to be removed for the lysogenic growth to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The fragment inserted in the place of the central portion of the genome is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) insertion fragment",
            "b) substitution fragment",
            "c) stuffer fragment",
            "d) displacement fragment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The fragment inserted in the place of the central portion of the genome is known as the stuffer fragment. It is generated by doing partial digestion an enzyme having a 4bp long recognition site. "
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Choose incorrect statement for the substitution vector EMBL4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is having two single multiple cloning sites",
            "b) The region to be removed is on one side of the multiple cloning sites",
            "c) If a digestion within the multiple cloning sites, it generates central portion and right and left arms",
            "d) The right and left portions are called as arms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The substitution vector EMBL4 contains two multiple cloning sites. The two multiple cloning sites flank the region which is to be removed. If digestion is done within the multiple cloning sites, it generates central portion and the right and left portions. The right and left portions separated are known as arms."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "At times, a second enzyme is used while the central portion is removed and the stuffer fragment is placed there. Choose the statement which doesn’t holds for this process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a method which is used for avoiding the relegation of central portion before the stuffer fragment is attached over there",
            "b) In this method, the central portion is cut with another enzyme after being separated from the arms",
            "c) The arms are also cut with this second enzyme",
            "d) It is not necessary to remove the fragments generated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The central portion should be stopped from religating before the stuffer fragment should be ligated. There are chances that central portion gets religated to the arms."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Physical separation is also used at times. Choose the correct statement with respect to this method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical separation constitutes of gel electrophoresis and or by using centrifugation in sugar density gradient",
            "b) In sugar density gradient, the molecules are separated on the basis of density",
            "c) The central portion is recovered from the gel or the gradient",
            "d) Gel is more efficient than the sugar density gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A second enzyme is used in order to avoid the relegation of the central portion and the arms. In this method, the central portion is cut with a second enzyme after being separated from the arms. These arms are not cut with the second enzymes. Hence the ends created are different now and the arms won’t ligate to the central portion again. It is not necessary to remove the fragments generated because the chances of having a multimolecular reaction which are required for the formation of original phage are very less."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Packaging in vitro is also carried out to introduce the lambda DNA into the cells. Choose the incorrect statement in respect to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packaging in phage coat is a more efficient process than the normal transformation process",
            "b) The lambda DNA is incubated with lysate of lambda infected cells in a concatemeric configuration",
            "c) Lysate constitutes of lambda proteins needed for phage assembly",
            "d) The amount of non-recombinant phage in the background is less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Physical separation is also used at times, it constitutes of using gel electrophoresis or by using centrifugation in the sugar density gradient. In the sugar density gradient, the separation is done on the basis of size. The arms are separated from the gel or gradient. A gradient is more efficient than gel, thus gradient is more preferred over the gel."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Packaging in vitro is basically carried out by two different strategies. Choose the incorrect statement for it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separate strains with chain-termination mutations in different genes for coat components are used __________",
            "b) Temperature sensitive cI repressor is used",
            "c) Due to heat shock packaging proteins are induced",
            "d) Packaging is carried out in each strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Packaging in vitro is used to introduce the lambda. It is more efficient than the normal transformation procedure. Thus, the lambda DNA is incubated with lysate of lambda infected cells in a concatemeric configuration. This lysate constitutes of lambda proteins needed for phage assembly and hence the recombinant DNA is also packed. But there is also a large amount of non-recombinant packaging in the background."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Chain-termination mutations in coat proteins genes are carried out. The coat protein coat genes used are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A gene",
            "b) D gene",
            "c) E and D gene",
            "d) D and A gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Packaging in vitro is basically out by two different strategies. In the first strategy, separate strains with chain-termination mutations in different genes (mostly D and E genes) for coat components are used. Temperature sensitive cI repressor is used and due to induction by heat shock, packaging proteins are produced. But packaging is not carried out in any of the strain because none of the strain is having full complement of proteins to carry out packaging. "
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "What happens if chain-termination mutation is in the S gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell lysis is blocked",
            "b) Growth of cells containing low levels of packaging proteins is not allowed",
            "c) The lysis of cells is not carried artificially",
            "d) Packaging is not carried out efficiently"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If chain-termination mutation is carried out is in the S gene, cell lysis is blocked. The growth of cells having high levels of packaging proteins is carried out. The lysis is then carried out artificially."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for blocking the phage-encoded recombination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mutation in D gene",
            "b) Mutation in E gene",
            "c) Red mutation",
            "d) Mutation in S gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Red mutation is used for blocking the phage-encoded recombination. It ensures that no recombination or rearrangement takes place while carrying out packaging in vitro."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a consequence of deletion in the b region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excision of the prophage on induction is prevented",
            "b) It reduces the amount of endogenous phage DNA in the packaging mix",
            "c) It reduces the amount of exogenous phage DNA in the packaging mix",
            "d) It reduces the level of background non-recombinant phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The deletion in the b region is responsible for preventing the excision of the prophage on induction. It reduces the amount of endogenous phage DNA in the packaging mix and thus resultantly it reduces the level of background non-recombinant phage."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "The cI function can be scanned in order to check whether the recombinants are present or not. Which of the following doesn’t hold true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cI protein is required for the formation of lysogen",
            "b) The plaques formed are turbid in the case if the cI gene is active",
            "c) The plaques formed are clear in the case if the cI gene is inactive",
            "d) hflA mutant host reduces the amount of cII stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case, if a single strain is used for packaging, there are increased chances of endogenous material being packed. It can be avoided by using additional mutations such as xis in the prophage to stop the excision and packaging of the lysogenic phage from the cells producing packaging extract."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "What is the function of red and gam gene products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It promotes the growth of the phage in the E. coli cells which are lysogenic for bacteriophage P1",
            "b) It inhibits the growth of the phage in the E. coli cells which are lysogenic for bacteriophage P2",
            "c) It inhibits the growth of the phage in the E. coli cells which are lytic for bacteriophage  P1",
            "d) It activates the growth of the phage in the E. coli cells which are lytic for bacteriophage P2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cI protein is required for the formation of lysogen to take place. The plaques formed are clear in the case if cI is inactive and turbid in the case if cI is active. hflA (high frequency of lysogenization) mutant hosts is used for enhanced screening. It is so because it increases the amount of cII stability and thus consequently lysogenization is taking place efficiently."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The red and gam genes are removed in which type of phages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Substitution phage",
            "b) Replacement and substitution phages both",
            "c) Replacement phage",
            "d) Substitution is preferred over replacement phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The red and gam gene products inhibit the growth of the phage in the E.coli cells which are lysogenic for bacteriophage P2. When red and gam gene products are absent, the growth takes place in the cells which are lysogenic to bacteriophage P2."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Phages which are designated as spi-are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) red+ gam+",
            "b) red+ gam-",
            "c) red- gam+",
            "d) red- gam-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The red and gam genes are removed in replacement vectors. And this can be used as a potent method to select the recombinants by plating them on P2 lysogen.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for RecBCD nuclease.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It promotes rolling circle replication",
            "b) It is blocked by Gam protein",
            "c) It blocks theta mode of replication",
            "d) It is blocked by Red protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: red- gam- are called as spi- and they are not able to grow on P2 lysogens. The red+ gam+ mutants are called as spi+."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "The essential sites for recombination are known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chi sites",
            "b) rec sites",
            "c) gam sites",
            "d) red sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RecBCD nuclease is blocked by Gam protein and it blocks rolling circle replication. As the rolling circle mode is blocked, replication would be carried out by only theta mode of replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "There is a limit on upper size of the DNA to be packed. Choose the correct statement with respect to phages in this context.",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is some phage DNA lost in this process",
            "b) The phages are known as transformed phages",
            "c) These type of phages can’t be selected and harvested",
            "d) Lambda is not a special attachment site"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sites necessary for recombination are known as chi sites. Host recombination enzymes may not work until and unless the recombination sites are present. "
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "There are some phages which don’t preferentially transduce some special regions of the phage genome. These phages are known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transducing phages",
            "b) specialized transducing phages",
            "c) generalized transducing phages",
            "d) transforming phages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The replication rate is not the same for all the phages. Some phages having a certain insert may be replicating in a slower rate than that of other phages. Thus, there might be under-representation of some of the sequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for the lambda ZAP vector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is not based on bacteriophage lambda",
            "b) It contains a region that can be excised in vivo",
            "c) The excision leads to the formation of bluescript plasmids and it contains an initiator region only",
            "d) The multiple cloning site is not flanked by the initiator and the terminator region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lambda ZAP vector is based on the bacteriophage lambda. It contains a region that can be excised in vivo and leads to the formation of bluescript plasmids. This consists of multiple cloning site which is flanked by the initiator and the terminator region."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "The initiator is recognized by which gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gene I",
            "b) Gene I and II",
            "c) Only gene II",
            "d) Gene III"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The f1 initiator and terminator region flanks the multiple cloning site and the initiator region is recognized by gene II."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the replication process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The initiator site is nicked and replication of one strand is started",
            "b) Replication takes place in both the directions",
            "c) Replication continues through the bluescript",
            "d) It is stopped at the terminator and then again a nick is made"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The initiator site is nicked and the replication of one strand is initiated. Replication takes place in one direction only and continues through the bluescript. It is stopped at the terminator and then a nick is made again there. "
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which of the following doesn’t takes place after replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The single stranded sequence is generated",
            "b) It is circularized to form closed single stranded molecule",
            "c) It may circularize or remain linear",
            "d) The double stranded molecule can be synthesized by cellular DNA synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the replication takes place, a single stranded sequence is generated and it circularizes in vivo in order to form single stranded circular molecule. The double stranded molecule can be synthesized by cellular DNA synthesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for cosmids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be regarded as lambda substitution vector",
            "b) Less amount of phage DNA is deleted",
            "c) Only cos packaging sites are left",
            "d) It doesn’t contains a origin of replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cosmids can be regarded as lambda replacement vectors. More amount of phage DNA is deleted and only cos packaging sites are left. There are no coat protein genes left. It also contains an origin of replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct method to check whether the DNA has entered into the cell or not in the case of cosmid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If a transformation has taken place turbid plaques are formed",
            "b) If a transformation has taken place clear plaques are formed",
            "c) If a transformation has taken place, it can be confirmed via ampicillin resistance",
            "d) If a transformation has taken place, it can be confirmed if forms plaques and is ampicillin resistant also"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Once cosmids are inside the E. coli cells, they don’t generate more phage but are propagated as plasmids. It is so because no more coat protein genes are present and thus it can’t be packaged. They can’t give rise to plaques. "
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which size of the insert is accepted by the cosmids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-20 kbp",
            "b) 35-45 kbp",
            "c) 50-60 kbp",
            "d) 100-120 kbp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the case of cosmid, transformation can be confirmed via counting the colonies containing ampicillin. As the plaques are not formed by cosmids, it can’t be used as a method to detect transformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What happens once the cosmid enters the E. coli cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is strict size selection inside E. coli cells",
            "b) Partial deletion may take place",
            "c) The tendency of deletion may is increased by using low copy number",
            "d) The tendency of deletion can’t be altered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is a minimum size limit on the insert which is accepted by the cosmids and it lies in the range of 35-45 kbp. They generally accept large size insert and it is beneficial for the construction of genomic libraries."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "If colEI derived origin of replication is replaced by the origin of replication of F plasmid, it is called as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) phagemid",
            "b) F cosmid",
            "c) plasmid",
            "d) fosmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There is no size selection once the cosmid enters the E. coli cells. Because of it, partial deletion may take place. The tendency of deletion can be reduced by using a low copy number."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Bacteriophage Mu is also a phage, choose the correct statement for it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is an example of temperate phage",
            "b) It is packaged into heads containing 50 kbp of DNA",
            "c) When the phage replicates it goes transposition only a few times",
            "d) Mu can’t be used for cloning in vivo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteriophage Mu is also a phage, it is an example of temperate phage. It is packaged into heads containing 39 kbp of DNA. When the phage replicates it goes transposition a few hundred times and inserts itself into many places in the host genome. Mu can be used for cloning in vivo as a ‘mini Mu’ that contains reduced phage genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for ‘Mini Mu’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is produced by cloning of bacteriophage Mu in vivo",
            "b) It contains reduced phage genome",
            "c) It doesn’t contain replication of origin of plasmid",
            "d) A selectable marker is added"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mini Mu is produced by cloning of bacteriophage Mu in vivo. It is having reduced phage genome. A selectable marker and an origin of replication of plasmid are added."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included as a step for cloning mini Mu in vivo?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A culture of target strain, whose DNA we want to clone is infected with mini Mu",
            "b) The phage is inserted at multiple sites in the genome",
            "c) Some of the packaged strain is flanked by two mini Mu genes",
            "d) The packaged phage is introduced into a second strain and Mu would replicate as a phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For cloning in mini Mu, a culture of target strain whose DNA we want to clone is infected with mini Mu. The phage is inserted at multiple sites in the genome. Some of the packages strain is flanked by two mini Mu genes. The packaged phage is introduced into a second strain and the Mu won’t be able to replicate as a phage."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a restriction for cloning in bacteriophage Mu?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is limited to handling only small number of phage particles",
            "b) It relies on whether the DNA is flanked by two mini Mu genes or not",
            "c) Recombination between the elements in the second strain is not a restriction",
            "d) Fragments of any genomic DNA can be cloned irrespective of the fact whether or not the phage can replicate in it or not"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If recombination takes place between elements in the second strain, it would replicate as a plasmid by the origin of replication of mini Mu. Thus a plasmid is formed with a piece of DNA from first strain and stably maintained in the second strain."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "What is the size of the insert that can be accommodated in the head of bacteriophage PI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30-40 kbp",
            "b) 80-95 kbp",
            "c) 110-115 kbp",
            "d) 200-300 kbp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cloning in bacteriophage Mu is restricted by some factors. These include, it depends whether the DNA is flanked by two mini Mu genes or not. Recombination between the elements in the second strain is also important. Fragments of only those genomic DNA can be cloned, in which Mu can replicate."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What is the function of the pac site in the bacteriophage PI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is responsible for the initiation of packaging",
            "b) It is responsible for the termination of packaging",
            "c) It is responsible for the initiation of replication",
            "d) It is responsible for the termination of replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacteriophage PI is known to accommodate the larger size of fragments. The size of the fragments that can be accommodated in the head of this phage lies between 110-115 kbp."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "What is the function of loxP sites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is responsible for linearization of DNA in the host bacterium",
            "b) It is responsible for circularization of DNA in the host bacterium",
            "c) It is responsible for conversion of single stranded DNA into double stranded DNA",
            "d) It is responsible for conversion of double stranded DNA into single stranded DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pac site in the bacteriophage PI is responsible for initiating the packaging of DNA into the phage heads. "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included as a step in cloning in bacteriophage PI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The growth of vector is done as a plasmid by using pBR322 origin of replication",
            "b) Cleaving with BamH1 is done and then products cleaved with Sau3A are ligated",
            "c) Incubation with mutant lysogen is done which doesn’t cleaves the recombinants at pac sites",
            "d) Incubation is done with mutant lysogen which doesn’t contains head and tail proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lox P sites are responsible for the circularization of the linear DNA molecules in the host bacterium."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "What happens after packaging is carried out in the phage head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A sequence dependent cleavage of DNA is carried out",
            "b) A sequence independent cleavage of DNA is carried out",
            "c) They are linearized before they are infected into the bacterial cells",
            "d) They are circularized before they are infected into the bacterial cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacteriophage PI is a complex vector. The growth of vector is done as a plasmid by using pBR322 origin of replication. Cleaving with Bam H1 is done and it is followed by ligation with Sau3A partial digestion products. It is followed by incubation with mutant lysogen which cleaves the recombinants at pac sites but there are no head and tail proteins. It is followed by incubation in lysogen in which cleavage is not carried out at pac sites but there are head and tail proteins. It leads to packaging into heads."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "How many origins of replication are there once the cyclization is carried out by loxP sites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After the packaging is carried out in the phage head, a sequence independent cleavage of DNA is carried out. Molecules with a very small size insert can’t fill into the whole phage head before the next pac site is reached."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for PAC vectors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In these vectors, the phage packaging signals are removed but the two P1 origin of replication persist",
            "b) They resemble BAC vectors",
            "c) They accept an insert of upto 300 kbp",
            "d) Instability is observed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Circularization must take place in the bacterial cells before the replication is initiated. The cells are introduced into the bacterial cells after the packaging has been carried out.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement in respect to sacB gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cloning site for PAC lies on the side of sacB gene",
            "b) It is responsible for producing an enzyme which is responsible for catalysing sucrose into glucose and fructose",
            "c) Expression of sacB in the presence of sucrose is beneficial",
            "d) Levan is non-toxic for E. coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two origins of replication once the cyclization is carried out by loxP sites. One origin of replication is for low copy number and the other can be activated for carrying out a high copy number replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Selection of molecules by lack of inserts on the basis of the sacB gene is known as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) positive selection",
            "b) negative selection",
            "c) counter selection",
            "d) sacB selection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PAC vectors are those vectors, in which the phage packaging signals are removed but the two P1 origin of replication persist. These resemble BAC vectors. They accept upto an insert of upto 300 kbp. Maintenance at low copy numbers is helpful in avoiding instability. "
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Libraries can broadly be classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Libraries can be classified basically into two types- genomic libraries and cDNA libraries. Genomic libraries are constructed from the whole genome of the organism. cDNA libraries are constructed from the DNA copies of RNA sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for genomic libraries.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genomic libraries include the representation of the whole genome of the organism",
            "b) Sequences such as telomeres are also represented",
            "c) Telomeres can be readily cloned",
            "d) The larger the size of the insert of genomic DNA in recombinants, the more is the number of recombinants required to represent the genome in the library"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genomic libraries include the representation of the whole organism. Sequences such as telomeres can’t be represented in the genomic libraries because they can’t be readily cloned. The larger size of the insert of genomic DNA in recombinants, less number of recombinants is required to represent the genome in the library."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the preparation of genomic libraries.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The first step is the isolation of genomic DNA",
            "b) Physical damage to the DNA should be avoided",
            "c) If a nuclear DNA library is to be constructed, organelle DNA is to be removed",
            "d) For the construction of organelle library, organelle DNA is purified from the nuclear DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the preparation of genomic libraries, the first step is the isolation of genomic DNA. Physical damage to the DNA should be avoided and DNA of high molecular weight should be obtained. For the construction of nuclear DNA library, organelle DNA (DNA which is included in mitochondria and chloroplast), is not removed. It is so because they are very less in the amount in comparison to nuclear DNA. For the construction of organelle library, organelle DNA is purified from the nuclear DNA. "
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "To avoid ligation of separate DNA fragments, which of the enzyme is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) phosphatase",
            "b) kinase",
            "c) ligase",
            "d) endonuclease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Firstly, the isolation of genomic DNA is carried out. It is followed by the fragmentation of DNA. Then the vector preparation is done, which is followed by the ligation and introduction to the host. The final step is the amplification of the recombinants."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Vector and insert are mixed, ligated and packaged and introduced into the host by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transformation",
            "b) transduction",
            "c) infection",
            "d) transformation and infection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Partial digestion is preferred over complete digestion. It is so because if complete digestion is carried out, it is not necessary that all the fragments are represented. Thus partial digestion is preferred over complete digestion. "
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Libraries using phage cloning vectors are often kept as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) unpackaged phage",
            "b) packaged phage",
            "c) both packaged and unpackaged phage",
            "d) both packaged and unpackaged phage are used but packaged is favoured"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To avoid ligation of separate DNA fragments, phosphatase is used. By the use of phosphatase, terminal phosphate groups are removed and thus ligation is not done. Joining of separate fragments is avoided because it would lead to the formation of non-contiguous DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Libraries constructed in plasmid vectors can be kept as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plasmid containing cells",
            "b) naked DNA",
            "c) both plasmid containing cells and naked DNA",
            "d) naked DNA is preferred over plasmid containing cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vector and insert are mixed, ligated and packaged into the host by transformation and infection both."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for cDNA libraries.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They constitute of DNA copies produced from the RNA sequences and usually mRNA",
            "b) They represent expressed sequences",
            "c) Introns are not represented",
            "d) Comparison of cDNA sequences with genomic sequences leads to the determination of polyadenylation sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: cDNA libraries constitute of DNA copies produced from RNA sequences and usually mRNA. They are not only the collection of expressed sequences but post transcriptional changes are also recorded. Introns can also be represented. Comparison of cDNA sequences with genomic sequences can lead to the determination of positions of introns, polyadenylation sites etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "A times partial sequencing of cloned cDNAs is carried out. These cDNA are known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) expressed RNA sequences",
            "b) expressed sequence tags (ESTs)",
            "c) expressed cDNA sequences",
            "d) library"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The partial sequencing of cloned cDNA is the first step of genome characterization project. These cloned cDNA sequences are known as expressed sequence tags (ESTs)."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Polyadenylation of RNA species is an important criterion for the production of cDNA species. Which of the following holds true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyadenylation should be at 3’ end",
            "b) Eukaryotic mRNAs are mostly non-polyadenylated",
            "c) Bacterial mRNAs and organelle mRNAs are polyadenylated",
            "d) It is carried out by the addition of T residues after synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polyadenylation of RNA species is an important criterion for the production of cDNA species and polyadeylation should be at the 3’ end. Mostly eukaryotic mRNAs are polyadenylated. It is carried out by the addition of A residues after synthesis. Usually, bacterial mRNAs and organelle mRNAs are non-polyadenylated residues."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for oligo-dT cellulose.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is used for separation of polyadenylated mRNA from another mRNA",
            "b) oligo-dT are covalently attached to the solid support via OH bonds",
            "c) A solution containing RNA is passed through the column",
            "d) Poly A tail attaches to the oligo-dT by ionic bonds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: oligo-dT cellulose is used for separation of polyadeylated mRNA from another mRNA. These are covalently attached on a solid support via OH bonds. For separation, a solution containing RNA is passed through the column and the molecules having poly A tails are attached to the column via hydrogen bonds."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "At times streptavidin is used in place of cellulose. Choose the correct statement for this alternative.",
        "Options": [
            "a) oligo-dT streptavidin conjugate can be extracted by magnetic beads",
            "b) The magnetic beads are attached with activin",
            "c) Recovery is not based on the magnetic properties of the beads",
            "d) The interaction between polyA tail and the oligo-dT is reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All non-specific mRNA are firstly eluted from the column. The poly A tail is eluted from using low salt concentration, it is so because low salt concentration destabilizes nucleic acids.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Choose the correct with respect to RNA molecules.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are less labile than DNA molecules",
            "b) The 2’ hydroxyl group of ribose group decreases the activity",
            "c) There is no less of activity while boiling",
            "d) Baking of glassware, treatment with UV can be used for protection against degradation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If streptavidin is used in the place of cellulose, oligo-dT streptavidin conjugate can be extracted by magnetic beads. These magnetic beads are having biotin attached to them. Recovery is based on the magnetic properties of the beads. The interaction between the polyA tail and the oilgo-dT still remains the basic principle and it is not affected."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "What is the basis of RNaseH method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is based on RNA synthesis by DNA strand",
            "b) It is based on complementary DNA synthesis by RNA strand through reverse transcriptase",
            "c) It is based on complementary DNA synthesis by RNA strand through RNaseH enzyme",
            "d) It is based on getting double strand RNA from a single strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RNA molecules are more labile as compared to the DNA molecules and they are more reactive because of the 2’ hydroxyl group of ribose group. Baking of glassware, treatment with UV can be used as methods for protection against degradation. If precautions are not taken, there is subsequent loss of activity while boiling."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "For the synthesis of the second DNA strand, incorporated oligo-dT is of no use. Why?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is so because it is unstable",
            "b) It is so because it is at the 3’ end of the template molecule",
            "c) It is so because it would be unable to initiate replication",
            "d) It is so because it detaches itself after first strand synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNase H method is based on the synthesis of the complementary DNA synthesis by RNA strand through reverse transcriptase enzyme and it leads to the formation of the duplex of RNA and DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for second DNA strand synthesis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The RNA: DNA complex is treated with the enzyme RNaseH and DNA pol",
            "b) The enzyme RNaseH is responsible for nicking the RNA strand and leaving free 3’ hydroxyl ends",
            "c) These RNA fragments can be used as primers",
            "d) There is no portion of RNA left attached to the DNA strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For second strand DNA synthesis, the RNA: DNA complex is treated with RNaseH enzyme along with DNA pol. The enzyme is responsible for nicking the RNA strand and leaving 3’ hydroxyl ends. These free ends are used for second strand synthesis. These RNA fragments can be used as primers. After DNA: DNA duplex formation, only a small portion of RNA is left at the 5’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "What is the final product of the RNaseH method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) blunt ended dsDNA",
            "b) staggered dsDNA at both ends",
            "c) staggered dsDNA at 3’ end",
            "d) staggered dsDNA at 5’ end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The final product of the RNaseH method is blunt ended dsDNA. The RNA piece left at the 5’ end is removed by RNase and thus blunt ended dsDNA is left.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "What would not happen if the RNA strand is completely removed from RNA: DNA hybrid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are no chances of the synthesis of the second DNA strand",
            "b) Chance complementarity would take place",
            "c) Hairpin structure would be formed",
            "d) Hairpin structure is formed is not the final structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the RNA strand is completely removed from RNA: DNA hybrid, the single stranded DNA remains. Then chance complementarity takes place and the 3’ end complements with any other portion in the single stranded DNA. It leads to the formation of a hairpin structure and the 3’ end extends in the presence of DNA pol and nucleotides."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The loop region is single stranded. It can be cleaved by using which enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exonuclease",
            "b) S1 nuclease",
            "c) RNaseH",
            "d) DNase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The loop region in the hairpin structure is single stranded in nature. The single stranded portion can be cleaved by S1 nuclease."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement with respect to the self priming method of cDNA synthesis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is less preferred than RNaseH method",
            "b) A hairpin structure is formed with guarantee",
            "c) The sequence corresponding to the 5’ end is lost",
            "d) Reverse transcriptase is not used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The self priming method is based on the formation of a hairpin structure. But there are only chances and no guarantee of formation of hairpin structure. In the first strand synthesis, reverse transcriptase is used. The sequence corresponding to the 5’ end is lost and in cDNA large deletions are observed. This method is less preferred than RNaseH method."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the method homopolymer tailing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The first step is the RNA: DNA hybrid synthesis",
            "b) Terminal transferase is used for the addition of nucleotides on 3’ end",
            "c) Terminal transferase adds only at DNA strands",
            "d) The DNA strand is now having known sequence at 3’ end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Homolpoymer tailing is also used for cDNA synthesis. The first step remains same as the other methods, which is the synthesis of RNA: DNA hybrid. It is then treated by terminal transferase, the enzyme is responsible for adding nucleotides on 3’ end of both DNA and RNA. The 3’ end is now having a known DNA sequence and it is used as a tail in the reaction. "
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for RACE.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Random Amplification of cDNA ends",
            "b) It is for cloning particular cDNA ends",
            "c) It is only of one type, which is 5’ RACE",
            "d) Sequence data is not available in any case"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RACE stands for Rapid Amplification of cDNA ends. Sometimes, we wish to clone specific cDNA portion and are having some sequence data.  It is meant for cloning specific cDNA ends and is classified into two types, 5’ RACE and 3’RACE."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The first primer in the case of 3’ RACE is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) internal sequence",
            "b) oligo-dT adaptor molecule",
            "c) oligo-dA adaptor molecule",
            "d) adaptor oligo-dT primer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first primer in the case of 3’ RACE is oligo-dT adaptor molecule. The second primer is an internal sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "What is the second primer in the case of 5’ RACE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal primer",
            "b) Oligo-dA sequence",
            "c) Adaptor-oligo-dT primer",
            "d) Oligo-dT adaptor molecule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first cDNA strand in the case of 5’ RACE is tailed with an oligo-dA tail. The synthesis of the first cDNA strand is by an internal primer."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "RNaseH method and homopolymer tailing method generates blunt ended cDNA molecules. Which of the following can be used for attaching them to vector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blunt ended ligation",
            "b) Addition of linkers",
            "c) Using appropriate restriction enzymes",
            "d) All the methods can be used equivalently"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As the products of RNaseH method and homopolymer tailing method generates dsDNA and blunt ended molecules, there are many methods to attach them to vector. Blunt ended ligation, the addition of linkers and restriction enzymes all can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for modification of homopolymer tailing method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It includes modification of primers",
            "b) Primers are varied by simply altering their size by randomly adding or removing bases",
            "c) The 5’ end of the first cDNA strand is tailed with C residues",
            "d) A single stranded oilgonucleotide is then used for second strand synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The modification of homopolymer tailing method includes modification of primers. Primers can be modified by the introduction of restriction sites in them. The 3’ end of the first cDNA strand is tailed with C residues. Another oligo-dG primer precedes the introduced restriction site and is contained with the double stranded oligonucleotide region. It is used for second strand synthesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the homopolymer tailing of cDNA strands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The blunt ended double stranded cDNA molecules are treated with terminal transferase and dCTPs",
            "b) Vector is also treated with terminal transferase and dGTPs",
            "c) The vector and cDNA can now anneal with the help of DNA ligase",
            "d) If gaps are created they can be repaired by physiological processes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double stranded oligonucleotides are required for the synthesis of second cDNA strand. This double stranded oligonucleotide is synthesized by separately synthesizing two strands and then annealing them."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement if the RNA is non polydenylated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A collection of chemically synthesized oligonucleotides is used as primers",
            "b) They are usually tetramer",
            "c) Unequal quantities of A, G, T and C are used",
            "d) The primers attach at only specific sequences for first strand synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For homopolymer tailing of cDNA strands, the blunt ended double stranded molecules are treated with terminal transferase and dCTPs. This leads to the addition of C residues at 3’ end. Vector is also treated with terminal transferase and dGTPs. This leads to annealing of vector and cDNA molecules and DNA ligase is not required. The gaps created can be repaired by physiological processes once the recombinant molecules enter the host."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "In case if molecules smaller than the fragments required for making a full genomic library are used for making a collection. This collection is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) library",
            "b) shelf",
            "c) small library",
            "d) mini library"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the RNA is non polyadenylated, oilgo-dT primer can’t be used and in place of it a collection of chemically synthesized oligonucleotides is used as primers. They are usually hexamers and are made by equal quantities of A, G, C and T. And thus all hexameric sequences can be synthesized. The primers can attach to the RNA sequences throughout. "
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for construction of a library subsection.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The size of a particular restriction fragment on which the gene is located is not known",
            "b) The size of the restriction fragment can be known by carrying out southern blotting",
            "c) Another digest of the genomic DNA is carried out by a different enzyme",
            "d) DNA fragments of different size are recovered after carrying out gel electrophoresis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the molecules smaller than the fragments required for making a full genomic library are used for collection, this collection is called a shelf. It is a subsection of the library."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "What do we mean by housekeeping genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Housekeeping genes are those genes which are specific to an organism",
            "b) Housekeeping genes are those genes which are present in all the organisms",
            "c) Housekeeping genes are those genes which are meant for repair and maintenance in a species of organism",
            "d) Housekeeping genes are those genes which required for the replication process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the construction of a subsection of the library, some steps are followed. The size of a particular restriction fragment on which gene is located is known at times. The size of the fragment can be known by carrying out southern blotting. After the size is known, another digest of the genomic DNA is carried out and is done by the same enzyme. DNA fragments of the approximately same size are recovered from the gel after carrying out gel electrophoresis. They can be further cloned into a vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for RNA fractionation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The RNA is fractioned by size but before separating on oligo-dT cellulose",
            "b) A sucrose density gradient is used",
            "c) The RNA is applied to the top of a pre-poured gradient and during centrifugation smaller molecules move down the tube faster",
            "d) Different bands are formed according to the density in the sucrose density gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Any cDNA library would represent a fraction of RNA species of an organism, the whole organism can’t be represented in a library. It depends on the developmental stage, physiological state and the tissue from which RNA was isolated."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "What is done after RNA fractionation is carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Each band is translated in vivo",
            "b) Translation is carried out in wheat gram or lysate of rabbit reticulocyte cells",
            "c) Translation is carried out with a high background",
            "d) Amino acid is not radioactively labelled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Housekeeping genes are those genes which are present in all the organisms. cDNA libraries may therefore contain housekeeping genes and genes specific to that organism."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "The polypeptides produced after addition of mRNA are analysed with antibodies. Choose the incorrect statement for this analysis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antibodies are added to each reaction tube and precipitation is simply based on antigen-antibody reaction",
            "b) Along with simple antigen-antibody complex, a substrate is added for easy precipitation",
            "c) Protein A-Sepharose is added",
            "d) Protein A-Sepharose binds to IgG antibodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNA fractionation is carried out and the basis is the size. It is fractioned by size after carrying out separation on oligo-dT cellulose. A sucrose density is used for size based separation. The RNA is applied to the top of a pre-poured gradient and during centrifugation larger molecules move down the tube faster. There are different bands formed on the basis of size in the sucrose density gradient."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "What is done after the recovery of pellets has been carried out in order to know the amount of polypeptides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Denaturing and gel electrophoresis in SDS- Polyacryamide gel",
            "b) Gel electrophoresis in agarose gel",
            "c) Quantitative PCR",
            "d) Weighing pellets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNA fractionation is carried out and it is followed by a translation of each band in vitro. It is carried out in wheat gram or lysate of rabbit reticuloycte cells. Ribosomes, tRNAs are added in order to carry out the translation with low background. An amino acid is radioactively labelled and thus the polypeptide sequence synthesized is labelled. "
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Sometimes the required mRNA is present in less number. So the process of increasing the representation of rare mRNAs is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) amplification",
            "b) normalization",
            "c) selection",
            "d) narrowing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the required mRNA is present in less number, its representation can be increased by a process called normalization. It reduces the number of times the library has to be screened for required cDNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement in order to enrich rare species.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The most basic principle relies on the kinetics of hybridization",
            "b) A collection of single stranded molecules is allowed to reanneal under given conditions",
            "c) The strands which are less abundant are able to find their complement easily",
            "d) The left over molecules are more abundant in nature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to enrich the rare species, the basic principle relies on the kinetics of hybridisation. A collection of double stranded cDNA molecules is allowed to melt. As the strands melt away, they are then allowed to reanneal under suitable conditions. The more abundant the species is, the more easily they anneal. The rare species are obtained in single stranded form because it is difficult to reanneal them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which statement holds true for hydroxyapatite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It binds to single stranded molecules more tightly than double stranded molecules",
            "b) It binds to linear molecules more tightly than circular molecules",
            "c) It binds to circular molecules more tightly than linear molecules",
            "d) It binds to double stranded molecules more tightly than single stranded molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydroxyapatite is the molecule which binds more tightly to the double stranded molecules than the single stranded molecules. This property is very useful in the process of enrichment of rare species."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Libraries in which a particular sequence is present in one organism but are absent from another organism, are called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) normalized libraries",
            "b) subtractive libraries",
            "c) selective libraries",
            "d) partial libraries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sometimes it happens that a particular sequence is present in one organism but is absent from another organism, such libraries are known as subtractive libraries."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "The nucleic acid from the cell type that contains the sequence we are interested in is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) driver",
            "b) subtractive sequence",
            "c) tracer",
            "d) wanted sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The nucleic acid from the cell type containing the sequence we are interested in is called a tracer. The driver is the molecule which lacks the sequence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for libraries constructed by mixing cell types differing in the sequences they are having.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The driver and tracer are mixed in double stranded form",
            "b) Tracer is in stoichiometric excess in comparison to driver",
            "c) Tracer and driver are in the same amount",
            "d) The sequences are allowed to hybridize"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is about subtractive libraries. The driver and tracer are mixed in single stranded form and driver is in stoichiometric excess in comparison to the driver. It is about tenfold excess. The sequences are mixed and allowed to hybridize."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Which of the following is desirable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Driver- driver hybrid",
            "b) Driver- tracer hybrid",
            "c) Tracer- tracer hybrid",
            "d) Driver alone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Our sequence of interest is present in the tracer. So if it hybridizes with a driver, it means that the sequence is present is it also and thus it is not required by us. Hence, either tracer-tracer hybrids or single stranded tracers are required."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the statement holds true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The tracer is treated with an enzyme which generates compatible ends",
            "b) The driver is treated with an enzyme which generates compatible ends",
            "c) Both driver and tracer are treated with an enzyme to generate compatible ends",
            "d) Both driver and tracer are treated with an enzyme to generate incompatible ends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tracer is treated with an enzyme which generates compatible ends and the driver is treated to generate incompatible ends. It is done so because then driver-driver or driver-tracer hybrids won’t form. Only tracer-tracer hybrids would form."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Sometimes a gene which we want to clone is present on a particular chromosome. For this purpose, the chromosome should be in which phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prophase",
            "b) Telophase",
            "c) Metaphase",
            "d) Anaphase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of physical removal methods, the driver is amplified and is labelled with biotin. After hybridization between tracer and driver, streptavidin is added and it attaches to biotin. Methods such as phenol extraction are used in order to remove streptavidin and sequences attached to it. Thus, tracer sequences which are not attached to driver remain in the aqueous phase only."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "For cloning purposes, the intact chromosomes should be separated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) agarose gel electrophoresis",
            "b) fluorescence- activated sorter",
            "c) polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis",
            "d) chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The chromosomes should be in metaphase state because then they will be in a condensed form and it would be easy to handle them."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "The process of examining stained chromosomes in a light microscope and removing appropriate regions with a micro-manipulator is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) microdissection",
            "b) chromosome sorting",
            "c) chromosome walking",
            "d) chromosome jumping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For cloning purposes, the intact chromosomes should be separated by using fluorescence-activated sorter. The amount of fluorescence obtained is based on the amount of dye and thus depends on the size of the chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "The process of finding a particular member of the library which is having some defined properties is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) searching",
            "b) screening",
            "c) locating",
            "d) narrowing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of finding a particular member of the library which is having some defined properties is called as screening. Mostly screening is carried out for a particular coding sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "If for a particular organism sequence data is available and we have to simply search in the data through a computer, then this method is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) annotation",
            "b) database search",
            "c) in silico",
            "d) electronic search"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The easiest way to find for a particular sequence is to exploit the genomic analyses. If the database is available for a particular sequence and the task is to simply search the data through the computer then the procedure is called in silico. "
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "If screening is carried out on the basis of sequences which are related to the desired sequence, then the process is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) in-silico",
            "b) homologue search",
            "c) annotation",
            "d) partial search"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Homologues are a group of organisms which contain similar sequences. Screening for such organisms can be carried out by using programs such as BLAST (Basic Local Alignment Search Tool). Search can be carried out within or for nucleotide and protein sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "How many techniques are there for carrying out the screening of sequences encoding for RNAs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the search is carried out on the basis of the related sequence rather than looking for the actual sequence then the process is termed as an annotation."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for colony or plaque lift.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the base for screening based on nucleic acid hybridization",
            "b) It is also known as Grunstein-Hogness technique",
            "c) It is based on the fact that which members of the library have the same sequence as the DNA probe",
            "d) The library may be plaques on a bacterial lawn and in that case it is known as plaque lift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are basically two techniques used for carrying out the screening of sequences encoding for RNAs. The first technique is based on nucleic acid hybridization and the second is based on coding function in vivo."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement with respect to the membranes used for adhering of bacterial cells onto them.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrocellulose membranes were preferred earlier",
            "b) They bind DNA very efficiently",
            "c) They can be handled easily without breakage",
            "d) They are inflammable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Colony lift or plaque lift is the basis for nucleic acid hybridization. It is also known as Grunstein-Hogness technique named after the discoverer. It is based on the fact that which members of the library are complementary to the sequence of DNA probe can be known. The library may be plaques on a bacterial lawn and in that case it is known as plaque lift. There may be colonies on a plate and in that case, it is known as colony lift."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "What is used for lysing of bacterial cells and denaturation of DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exonuclease",
            "b) Sulphuric Acid",
            "c) Sodium Hydroxide",
            "d) Heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Firstly, the membrane is placed onto the plate containing recombinant cells. Then the membrane is peeled off and the bacterial cells are carried away with it. After this, cells are lysed and denaturing of DNA is done. It is followed by hybridization with labelled DNA and then visualization is done. "
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "The process of baking or cross-linking of the membrane is carried out by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) By heating at 80 degrees",
            "b) By irradiating with UV",
            "c) Both irradiation and heating method are used",
            "d) By addition of agarose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cross-linking or baking of membrane is carried out by either heating it at 80 degrees or irradiating with UV. It is important to carry out this step because it binds the DNA irreversibly to the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for prehybridization mixture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The function of it is to carry out specific binding",
            "b) It constitutes of non-labelled DNA of non-specific sequence which is obtained from salmon or herring testes or sperm",
            "c) It is added in a small amount",
            "d) It is carried out before the hybridization is carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Prehybridization mixture is meant for blocking sites which are meant for non-specific binding. It constitutes of non-labelled DNA of non-specific sequence which is obtained from salmon or herring testes or sperm. They are added in a small amount and it is added before the hybridization is carried out. So that when hybridization is carried out, only specific binding takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "After hybridization how the position of the labelled DNA probe is determined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By staining",
            "b) By UV irradiation",
            "c) By using chemiluminescence",
            "d) By electronic microscope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After the hybridization has been carried out and the membrane has been washed, the position of the labelled DNA probe is determined by using chemiluminescence. Commonly the probe is labelled by incorporation of fluoroscein conjugated molecules. "
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "The important parameters for precise annealing of the probe and the subsequent washing don’t include ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of the probe",
            "b) Proportion of only A",
            "c) Ionic concentration of hybridization buffer",
            "d) Other agents which alter the base pairing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The probe should anneal precisely and the parameters which decide these are size of the probe, proportion of all A, G, T and C. Ionic concentration of hybridization buffer and other agents such as formamide which alter base pairing. These parameters define the maximum temperature at which probe and target DNA bind fully. "
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "If hybridization is carried out with a clone having a sequence similar to that of the vector from which library has been constructed, then it is of no use. Choose the correct statement in respect to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCR amplification of the probe can be carried out",
            "b) Excision of the probe should be carried out which should be followed polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis",
            "c) If the vector sequence and the DNA probe are having similarities, some of the vector would be hybridized",
            "d) Probe should be in a vector that is having some sequence similarity with the library to be screened"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If hybridization is carried out with a clone having a sequence similar to that of the vector from which the library has been constructed then all the vector would hybridize. To make the sequence different, PCR amplification of the probe can be carried out. Also, excision of the probe can be carried out by using suitable restriction enzymes and it is followed by agarose gel electrophoresis. Or probe in a vector should not have any sequence similarity with the library to be screened."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "At what temperatures the hybridization and washing of the DNA probes should be carried out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At melting temperature",
            "b) At a temperature lower than the melting temperature",
            "c) At a temperature higher than the melting temperature",
            "d) At 100 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The hybridization and washing of the DNA probes should be carried out at a temperature below than the melting temperature. It is so because if it is carried out a temperature lower than the melting temperature, some amount of mismatch is allowed. Melting temperature depends on the composition of the probes."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which library should be used, genomic or cDNA when the screening is carried out by oligonucleotide probes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Genomic",
            "b) cDNA",
            "c) Both genomic and cDNA library can be used equivalently",
            "d) None of the libraries are preferred if oligonucleotide probes are used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If oligonucleotide probes are used, then cDNA libraries should be used. It is so because cDNA libraries are enriched for coding sequences and thus fewer sequences have to be screened."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Sometimes successive rounds of screening of a genomic library are carried out and an ordered collection of clones is done in a linear fashion, then the process is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chromosome jumping",
            "b) chromosome sorting",
            "c) chromosome walking",
            "d) transposon tagging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chromosome walking is the process of successive rounds of screening of a genomic library and it leads to the collection of clones in a linear order."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "If the clone for a gene is obtained on the basis of its position in the gene map, then it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) locational cloning",
            "b) positional cloning",
            "c) chromosome walking",
            "d) transposon tagging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the clone for a gene is obtained on the basis of its position in the gene map then it is called positional cloning."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Mobile portions of a chromosome which can be transferred from one portion to another are termed as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mobile part",
            "b) transposons",
            "c) walking elements",
            "d) transferrable genetic element"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transposons are the mobile portions of the chromosomes which can be transferred from one portion of the chromosome to another either on the same chromosome or different chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "At times screening is done for the protein product of DNA of interest rather than the sequence itself. How many methods are there to carry out this?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two methods for this procedure are the direct selection for insert function and the second is ligand binding by the expressed protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement if the screening is carried out by screening by expression in vivo.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The proportion of recombinants carrying gene of interest is small",
            "b) The recombinants carrying gene of interest don’t complement the host mutation",
            "c) Mutation should be affecting many genes",
            "d) Most of the products selected would be result of complementation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The proportion of recombinants carrying the gene of interest is small. The host is mutant towards the gene of interest and thus the recombinants complement the host mutation. Mutation used should affect only one gene. The most of the products selected would be a result of reversion of only mutation and not complementation."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement with respect to host used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The host must carry mutation for the gene of interest",
            "b) The host should not contain restriction enzymes",
            "c) The host if having restriction enzymes, then the incoming DNA should not be methylated",
            "d) The host should be deficient in recombination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The host used must carry the mutation for the gene of interest. The host must not contain restriction enzymes. If the host is having restriction enzymes then the incoming DNA must be methylated. If the incoming DNA is not methylated, then it would be cleaved by restriction enzymes. The host should also be deficient in recombination otherwise it would be difficult to get it."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "If the library to be screened and the host belongs to different species, then it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) homologous selection",
            "b) heterologous selection",
            "c) intraspecies selection",
            "d) mixed selection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case, if gene which is to be screened belongs to prokaryotic species than there are chances that it is not expressed. There are chances that promoter is not present in the insert region. "
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "The direct selection allows _______ number of recombinants to be screened and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) less, slowly",
            "b) less, quickly",
            "c) more, quickly",
            "d) more, slowly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the library to be screened and the host belong to different species, then it is called as heterologous selection. In this case, there are chances that protein is expressed but it is non functional."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Xenopus oocyte cells are also used at the time to carry out screening. Choose the incorrect statement for this procedure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA from collections is transcribed within in vitro and the transcription products are microinjected into oocytes",
            "b) The RNA is translated within oocytes",
            "c) Screening is carried out on the basis of DNA",
            "d) The screening is helpful for the proteins whose function can be easily screened such as transport of ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the direct selection is carried out on a plate, then the process results in the screening of more recombinants and it is done quickly and easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "In the case of ligand binding by the expressed protein, the library can be screened by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) immunochemically, by the use of antibodies",
            "b) ligands if the sequence we are looking for encodes a protein specific to a ligand",
            "c) using a specific DNA sequence which can bind to the protein encoded by the sequence of interest",
            "d) all of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DNA from collections is transcribed within in vitro and the transcription products are microinjected into the oocytes. The RNA is translated within the oocytes and screening is carried out on the basis of RNA. The screening is helpful for those proteins whose functions can be easily screened such as transport of ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "In the case of immunochemical screening, the position of ________ antibody is detected by ________ antibody.",
        "Options": [
            "a) secondary, primary",
            "b) primary, secondary",
            "c) primary, tertiary",
            "d) secondary, tertiary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are various ways to screen such a library. It can be done immunochemically i.e. by the use of antibodies. Ligands can also be used which bind to the specific proteins encoded by the sequence. There are also cases in which specific DNA sequences bind to the protein encoded by the sequence of interest."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for panning.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a variant of ligand binding approach",
            "b) The ligand is immobilized on the solid support and the cells are passed over it",
            "c) If the ligand-binding domain is exposed on surface of the any recombinant molecules then they will bind to ligand",
            "d) They are not useful for scanning libraries in cultured mammalian cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of immunochemical screening, the position of the primary antibody is detected with a secondary antibody. Secondary antibody is common for all the primary antibodies and thus detection becomes easier."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "If screening is carried out by using a combination of nascent peptide and mRNA, then it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) nascent peptide display",
            "b) mRNA display",
            "c) ribosome display",
            "d) ribozyme display"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ligand should bind to a single protein only for the screening process, because if binds to a heterodimer than both the proteins should be present and then it would become difficult."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "If an expression of the coding sequence is to be carried in the vitro, then which of the statement holds true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The extract in which the host DNA constructs are incubated is capable of translation only",
            "b) The extract in which the host DNA constructs are incubated is capable of transcription only",
            "c) The extract is made up of lysate of E. coli cells, containing RNA polymerase, ribosomes, tRNAs etc",
            "d) Non radiolabelled amino acids are used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If an expression of the coding sequence is to be carried in vitro, then the extract in which host DNA constructs are incubated is capable of both transcription and translation. The extract is made up of lysate of E. coli cells, containing RNA polymerase, ribosomes, tRNAs etc. Radiolabelled amino acids are used and thus detection becomes easier."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "If translation and transcription are taking place together, the reaction is called as ______ and if they are carried out separately, it is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) coupled, linked",
            "b) linked, coupled",
            "c) grouped, separate",
            "d) grouped, individual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If translation and transcription are carried out together, it is known as a coupled reaction. If they are carried out separately then they are known as linked reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "If translation and transcription are carried out separately, then what is added to carry out translation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase",
            "b) RNA polymerase",
            "c) Taq polymerase",
            "d) Tfl polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The added RNA polymerase carries out the translation in a separate reaction by the use of lysate of wheat gram cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the open reading frame.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is helpful in deciding whether the clone is correct or not",
            "b) It consists of an initiation codon",
            "c) It consists of a termination codon",
            "d) The presence of introns doesn’t affect the open reading frame"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the screening of DNA constructs is carried out in pooled batches then less time is taken. Once the pooled batch is identified with recombinants then each member is screened."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Introns are ________ in nature and the sequence is _______ than exons.",
        "Options": [
            "a) coding, less random",
            "b) non-coding, less random",
            "c) non-coding, more random",
            "d) coding, more random"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Open reading frame is very important in deciding whether the clone is correct or not. It consists of an initiation codon, followed by a stretch of DNA and termination codon. The presence of introns the open reading would be affected and makes detection difficult."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "If the genome size is small, then sequencing of the entire genome is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) easy",
            "b) difficult",
            "c) independent of the size of genome",
            "d) not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Introns are non-coding in nature and thus the sequence is having a more random base composition than exons. Exons are coding sequences. "
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement with respect to the bacterial genome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are easy to sequence",
            "b) They are difficult to sequence",
            "c) Methods such as transcription and translation are satisfactory",
            "d) Only transcription can be carried out"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the genome size is small, then the sequencing of entire genome is carried out easily. Hence, direct sequencing is carried out if the genome size is small."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "For identification of genes that are expressed under special conditions, _______ libraries are used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cDNA",
            "b) genomic",
            "c) subtractive",
            "d) shelf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bacterial genome is of large size and thus it is difficult to carry out sequencing. Methods such as transcription and translation are unsatisfactory."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "In ______ organisms, firstly the gene is looked into model organisms.",
        "Options": [
            "a) eukaryotic",
            "b) prokaryotic",
            "c) both eukaryotic and prokaryotic",
            "d) large sized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If genes are expressed under special conditions then specialized libraries should be used. These specialized libraries are subtractive. In this, driver and tracers are used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Promoter-probe vectors are used often. Choose the correct statement for these vectors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are used for identifying sequences that can function as promoter in vivo",
            "b) It contains a reporter gene which contains its promoter along",
            "c) The reporter gene is having a cloning site",
            "d) After insertion of DNA into the cloning site, selection of plasmids is carried out by blue white screening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Promoter- probe vectors are used for identification of sequences that can function as a promoter in vivo. It consists of a reporter gene which is not having its promoter along but other genes such as those for chloramphenicol resistance are present. The reporter gene is preceded by the cloning site and after the insertion of DNA has been done, selection of plasmids is carried out by using chloramphenicol resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "GFP is one of a marker which is used for screening libraries in hosts other than E. coli. Choose the incorrect statement for GFP.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It stands for Green Fluorescent Protein",
            "b) It is obtained from a bio-luminescent jellyfish and produces protein aequorin which emits blue light",
            "c) The blue light is produced because of binding of sodium ions",
            "d) The absorbed blue light produces green light which can be detected further"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It stands for green fluorescent protein and is obtained from a bio-luminescent jellyfish. The jellyfish produces protein aequorin which produces blue light. This blue light is produced because of binding Calcium ions. The absorbed blue light emits green light which is detected further. "
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Luciferase genes are also used at times for detection. Choose the correct statement for them.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are obtained from fire flies only",
            "b) The detection requires provision of substrate which produces light",
            "c) Enzymes such as beta-galactosidase requires substrate X-gluc to produce light",
            "d) Lucifearse genes are preferred over fluorescent proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Luciferase genes are not obtained only from fire flies but also from bio-luminescent bacteria and a sea pansy. The section requires a substrate which produces light. Enzymes such as beta-galactosidase requires X-gal for the production of blue light. Fluorescent proteins are more preferable over these because they don’t require substrates like luciferase genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Sequences that can function as origins of replication are called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) partial replicating sequences",
            "b) self replicating sequences",
            "c) autonomously replicating sequences",
            "d) modified replicating sequences"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For promoter-probe vectors, the same species should be used as a host for the vector whose DNA is to be screened. It is so because a gene which is a promoter in one species may not be a promoter in other gene and thus it becomes difficult to detect."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Screening is often carried out for a sequence that interacts with a protein for which already a clone is present. It is carried out in which host?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacterial host",
            "b) Fungal host",
            "c) Parasitic host",
            "d) Yeast host"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are some sequences which can function as origins of replication and they are known as autonomously replicating sequences (ARS). At times, the selection is carried out for these sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "In two hybrid screening system, the activator binds through _______ domain to a sequence upstream of the gene under its control, and ________ domain stimulates transcription.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA binding, activation",
            "b) Activation, DNA binding",
            "c) Activation, transcription",
            "d) DNA binding, transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Screening is often carried out for a sequence that interacts with a protein for which already a clone is present. This type of screening is often carried out in a yeast host."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "For two hybrid systems, activation domains can be present in different proteins also rather than being on a single protein. A sequence encodes _______ protein for which we want to find an interacting protein.",
        "Options": [
            "a) prey",
            "b) bait",
            "c) binding",
            "d) activation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two hybrid-screening system is based on the fact that many transcriptional activators consist of two domains, the DNA binding domain and activation domain. The activator binds through the DNA binding domain to a sequence upstream of the gene under its control. The activation domain stimulates transcription. "
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "The transcription domain is ________ if some of the bait and prey proteins are non-specific in nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) deactivated",
            "b) activated",
            "c) destroyed",
            "d) may be activated or not"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bait protein is the name given to the protein for whom we are looking for an interacting protein. Bait protein is cloned adjacent to the DNA binding protein. The protein interacting with bait protein is called as prey protein and leading to activation of domains."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "_____ should enter the cell in the case of activation of the reporter gene for two hybrid system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bait protein",
            "b) Prey protein",
            "c) Both bait and prey protein",
            "d) Either one of them"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the bait and prey proteins are non-specific in nature, some of them might lead to activation of the transcription domain without the presence of another domain."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Direct alteration of particular parts of protein as a way of probing the relationship between structure and function is termed as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) genetic engineering",
            "b) protein engineering",
            "c) alteration of protein function",
            "d) structure engineering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Protein engineering is the direct alteration of parts of protein as a way of probing the relationship between its structure and function. The function of protein is altered in a controlled way."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "At times, the gene which is cloned is not well known for the protein encoded by it. To access the function, the endogenous gene for the mutant strain is inactivated. This technique is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reverse genetics",
            "b) protein engineering",
            "c) mutation",
            "d) location of function"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reverse genetics is the technique by which the exact function of the gene cloned is known. It is done by inactivating the mutant strain in the host. "
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Approaches for creating mutations can be divided into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are basically two approaches to creating mutations. They are relying on restriction enzymes and oligonucleotide-directed DNA synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "If there are multiple restriction sites for an enzyme in a given molecule, digestion is carried out in many steps. The initial digestion should be?",
        "Options": [
            "a) complete",
            "b) partial",
            "c) carried out by a different enzyme then that the restriction site",
            "d) carried out by a mixture of restriction enzymes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the deletion of a restriction site, it should be cleaved with the same restriction enzyme. As it is cleaved, the restriction site is destroyed and further the staggered ends created are either filled or degraded. After this religation is carried out but the restriction site is destroyed."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "If a functional gene is disrupted while disrupting a restriction site _______ is created.",
        "Options": [
            "a) frameshift mutation",
            "b) point mutation",
            "c) either of the mutations",
            "d) any other kind of mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If there are multiple restriction sites for an enzyme in a given molecule, the initial digestion would be partial. It is so because molecules cut on one site at an average."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Restriction site can also be introduced by oligonucleotide directed mutagenesis of a region that is _______   and ______ to the original restriction site.",
        "Options": [
            "a) not only similar, also exactly same",
            "b) similar, not same",
            "c) not similar, is entirely different",
            "d) different, near"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a functional gene is disrupted while disrupting a restriction site, a frameshift mutation would be created. As it is created, the gene might become dysfunctional."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Small deletions at a restriction site can be generated by cutting and degrading the ________ with an exonuclease.",
        "Options": [
            "a) double stranded ended",
            "b) circular molecules",
            "c) single stranded ends",
            "d) supercoiled molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Additional restriction sites can be introduced near the existing restriction site by mutagenesis. It is done by inserting chemically synthesized oilgonucleotide carrying the appropriate sequence. "
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "When a series of deleted regions are replaced by some other DNA fragment of equal length, then it is known as:",
        "Options": [
            "a) linker scanning",
            "b) generation of deletions",
            "c) mutation",
            "d) replacement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Restriction site can also be introduced by oligonucleotide directed mutagenesis of a region that is similar and is not the same to the original restriction site."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Bisulphite ions are used to deaminate ________ residues in _______ DNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C, double stranded",
            "b) C, single stranded",
            "c) U, double stranded",
            "d) U, single stranded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bisulphite ions are used to deaminate C residues in single stranded DNA. These C residues on deamination give U residues."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "For mutagenesis without PCR, which of the following can be used as a template?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single stranded DNA",
            "b) Double stranded DNA",
            "c) Circular DNA",
            "d) Both single and double stranded DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If mutagenesis is carried without PCR, both single and double stranded DNA can be used as a template. The single stranded DNA is obtained from filamentous phages and double stranded DNA is obtained from conventional vectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "An oligonucleotide is synthesized which contains the mutation and the rest is _______ to the template DNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) complementary",
            "b) non-complementary",
            "c) can either be complementary or non-complementary",
            "d) not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The oligonucleotide is synthesized which contains the mutation and the rest of the sequence is complementary to the template DNA. And the oligonucleotide is allowed to anneal to the template DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect for the synthesis of the second strand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The oligonucleotide is acting as a primer for the synthesis of the second strand",
            "b) DNA polymerase and dNTPs are added for synthesis",
            "c) The polymerase should have 5’-3’ exonuclease activity",
            "d) A polymerase having 5’-3’ exonuclease activity would degrade the primer that carries the mutant sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the template is double stranded, then the two strands are separated before annealing of the oligonucleotide. This separation is done by heating or alkali denaturation."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Once the double stranded molecule with the mutation is introduced into E. coli for replication, how many types of molecules are produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The oligonucleotide is acting as a primer for synthesis of the second strand. DNA polymerase and dNTPs are added for synthesis and the polymerase should not have 5’-3’ exonuclease activity. If the polymerase is having exonuclease activity it would degrade the primer that carries the mutant sequence and the mutated portion is replaced by template DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "How many sites can be mutated at a time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) Many"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Once the double stranded molecule with the mutation is introduced into E. coli for replication, there are basically two types of molecules produced after replication. One is the wild type molecule and the other is having mutated sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "If mixed oligonucleotides are used, it is regarded as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mixed mutagenesis",
            "b) multiple mutagenesis",
            "c) cassette mutagenesis",
            "d) polymutagenesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Many sites can be mutated at a time. For inducing more than one mutation, more than one mismatch are there in oligonucleotide to the target sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "It is easier to subclone a restriction fragment if it belongs to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small gene",
            "b) large gene",
            "c) prokaryotic organism",
            "d) eukaryotic organism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Several mutations can be induced at one site. This is done by using a mixture of oligonucleotides which are having different nucleotides at the same position."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "A megaprimer method is a ____ stage approach and uses _____ oligonucleotide primers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) two, two",
            "b) two, three",
            "c) one, two",
            "d) one, three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A megaprimer method is an approach of carrying out mutagenesis by using PCR. It is a two stage approach and uses three oligonucleotide primers."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) There are two flanking primers and they are having mutations",
            "b) There is one primer which anneals the target sequence and is having mutation",
            "c) Either of the flanking primers or the primer is annealing to the target sequence is having mutation",
            "d) One of the flanking primer and the primer annealing to the target sequence is having mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the megaprimer approach three primers are used. There are two primers which flank the target sequence and a third primer anneal to the target sequence. The mutation is there in the third primer."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Sometimes mutagenesis is carried out with the help of primers. Choose the correct statement with respect to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double stranded circular molecule is used as a template",
            "b) Mutation is introduced into one of flanking primers",
            "c) Single stranded circular molecule is used as a template",
            "d) After amplification, mutation is introduced into one strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Megaprimer is produced when amplification is carried out by using mutagenic primer and one of the flanking primers. It corresponds to the part of the gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "If PCR is used to introduce random mutations rather than specific mutations, it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mutagenic PCR",
            "b) error-prone PCR",
            "c) random PCR",
            "d) general PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double stranded circular molecules are used as a template. Mutation is introduced into both of the primers and then amplification is carried out. After amplification is carried out, mutation can be introduced either in one strand or both the strands."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "For the selection of the molecules having mutated sequence, which of the statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is suitable for methods which are PCR based",
            "b) It is suitable for methods which are not PCR based",
            "c) It is suitable for both PCR and not PCR based",
            "d) Selection of molecules with the mutant sequence is not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At times, PCR is used to introduce random mutations, rather than specific mutations and this type of PCR is called as error-prone PCR. There can be either one or many mutations."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the methodology of selection of molecules with mutant sequences.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A vector is used which is having antibiotic resistance gene",
            "b) Apart from antibiotic resistance gene, a second antibiotic resistance gene is also present",
            "c) There are two mutagenic primers which are used",
            "d) The second strand synthesis is carried out by only one primer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Selection is done either of molecules having a mutant sequence or degradation of wild type molecules is carried out. For selection of molecules having a mutant sequence, it can be used for methods which are not PCR based."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Once second strand synthesis is carried out, it is introduced into the host. Host is having which mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mutS mutation",
            "b) mutD mutation",
            "c) mutE mutation",
            "d) mutG mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A vector is used which is having conventional antibiotic resistance and along with a second antibiotic resistance gene. The second gene is inactivated because of point mutation. Also, there are two mutagenic primers used. The first primer is used for directing the incorporation of mutation. The second primer makes the inactive gene inactive. Both the primers are used for second strand synthesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "In a phosphothiorate nucleotide, oxygen atom is replaced by with atom?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnesium",
            "b) Calcium",
            "c) Sodium",
            "d) Sulphur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The host is having a mutS mutation. And because of this mutation, no mismatch repair takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "What is the function of ung gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is responsible for deamination of cytosine",
            "b) It is responsible for deamination of uracil",
            "c) It is responsible for removal of uracil",
            "d) It is responsible for removal of cytosine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Replication can be either by first strand or second strand. First strand replication leads to generation of wild type molecules and the antibiotic resistance is inactive. If the replication is carried out by second strand, mutated sequence is formed and the antibiotic resistance gene becomes active."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "DpnI cuts ________ strands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) methylated",
            "b) non-methylated",
            "c) phosphorylated",
            "d) non-phosphorylated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a phosphothiorate nucleotide, oxygen atom is replaced by a sulphur atom. Because of this replacement the DNA molecule becomes resistant to attack by nucleases."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The minor change in amino acid sequence can lead to _______ effect on three dimensional structure and there _____ in the primary sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) huge, may be no change",
            "b) no, may be huge change",
            "c) very less, is very less change",
            "d) huge, would be huge change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minor change in the amino acid sequence can lead to a huge effect on the three dimensional structure and might also abolish its function. In the primary sequence, there might be no change."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "It is often useful to inactivate endogenous genes in an organism. It might be helpful in finding out _________ role of the wild type gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) biological",
            "b) chemical",
            "c) physiological",
            "d) anatomical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inactivation of endogenous genes in an organism is very important at times. It is helpful in finding out the physiological role of the wild type gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "How can mutant strains be produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In systematic mutagenesis programmes",
            "b) In individual organisms",
            "c) Both by individual organisms and systematic mutagenesis programmes",
            "d) Apart from these two, other methods are also used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inactivation of endogenous genes is very useful. It can be used to direct the expression of the mutated gene in the absence of background expression of wild type gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "The principle of gene disruption is ________ to replace the endogenous chromosomal copy of a gene with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) homologous recombination, inactivated gene",
            "b) reciprocal translocation, inactivated gene",
            "c) homologous recombination, activated gene",
            "d) reciprocal translocation, activated gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For popular model organisms, there are databases for mutant strains. These mutant strains can either be produced by systematic mutagenesis programmes or by individual organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "The gene to be disrupted is cloned and a selectable marker is inserted. What should be the effect of selectable marker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It should have no effect on target gene",
            "b) It should make the target gene non-functional",
            "c) There is no restriction; it can be either functional or non-functional",
            "d) It should improvise the chances of survival of the target gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For gene disruption, the basic principle is homologous recombination to replace the endogenous chromosomal copy of a gene with the inactivated gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "The disrupted gene is excised from the vector and is inserted into the target organism. The excised gene should be in which form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular",
            "b) Supercoiled",
            "c) Either supercoiled or circular",
            "d) Linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the target gene, a selectable marker should be inserted. It can be either in the form of ampicillin resistance or a nutritional marker. The selectable marker should render the target gene non-functional."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "If ______ gene is there, the double crossover may leave ________ in the chromosome.",
        "Options": [
            "a) linear, functional copy",
            "b) circular, functional copy",
            "c) linear, a non-functional copy",
            "d) circular, a non-functional copy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The disrupted gene is excised from the vector and is inserted into the target organism. The excised gene should be linear in form."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "If the target organism contains more than one copy of the gene, what is the effect on these copies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only copy is disrupted",
            "b) All the copies are disrupted",
            "c) It is difficult to ensure that all the copies are disrupted",
            "d) Only a specified number of copies are disrupted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The incoming molecule having the marker will not replicate stably because it is linear. For the stable replication, double crossover of the flanking sequence should take place, replacing the endogenous gene with the disrupted gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "If methods are based on cellular processes that lead to inactivation of gene expression by affecting the RNA, then it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transcriptional",
            "b) pre-transcriptional",
            "c) post-transcriptional",
            "d) translational"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If inactivation of gene expression is carried out by affecting the RNA then these methods are referred to as post-transcriptional. As transcription is the process of obtaining RNA from DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for the method based on antisense RNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA is synthesized complementary to the sequence of the gene which is to be inactivated",
            "b) It is achieved by placing a DNA sequence which encodes RNA complementary to the RNA to be inactivated",
            "c) Expression of the endogenous gene is diminished",
            "d) This method is preferred over gene disruption has gene inactivation can be achieved completely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Antisense RNA is the RNA which is complementary to the RNA sequence which is to be inactivated. It is done with the help of a DNA sequence. Expression of the endogenous gene is diminished. This method doesn’t lead to complete inactivation, which is not the case with gene disruption."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "The method of post transcriptional gene silencing is particularly useful in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plants",
            "b) animals",
            "c) insects",
            "d) microorganisms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The method of post transcriptional gene silencing is particularly useful in plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Down regulation of expression of endogenous genes by transformation with constructs that would generate sense RNA, rather than anti-sense RNA is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) suppression",
            "b) co-suppression",
            "c) multisuppression",
            "d) anti-suppression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When anti-sense RNA is used in plants, a phenomenon observed is co-suppression. It is the down regulation of expression of endogenous genes by transformation with constructs that would generate sense RNA, rather than anti-sense RNA. "
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Double stranded RNA is cleaved by a nuclease called as Dicer and small fragments are generated known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) short interfering RNAs",
            "b) long interfering RNAs",
            "c) short interspersed RNAs",
            "d) long interspersed RNAs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In some organisms, presence of double stranded RNAs leads to the breakdown of corresponding single stranded endogenous mRNA. The double stranded RNA is having one strand same as that of endogenous RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The process of RNA inactivation by siRNAs is termed as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA silencing",
            "b) RNA interference",
            "c) Short RNA inactivation",
            "d) RNA disfunction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double stranded RNA is cleaved by a nuclease called as Dicer and small fragments are generated, they are about 22 nucleotides long and are known as short interfering RNAs (siRNA)."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "DNA _________ is also a method for gene silencing through short RNAs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) acetylation",
            "b) phosphorylation",
            "c) methylation",
            "d) acylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: siRNAs are short interfering RNAs. The process of RNA inactivation by use of these is called as RNA interference (RNAi)."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Introduction into host organism can also be done by using a DNA construct, which when transcribed, generates an RNA which is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) circular",
            "b) linear",
            "c) double stranded",
            "d) self-complementary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Short RNAs can also lead to gene silencing via DNA methylation."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "The ________ protein of bacteriophage P1 mediates site-specific recombination at a 34 bp sequence, loxP.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cre recombinase",
            "b) gene II",
            "c) gene IV",
            "d) gene VIII"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Cre recombinase protein of bacteriophage P1 mediates site-specific recombination at a 34 bp sequence, loxP."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for cre-lox excision.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The chromosomal copy of the target gene replaces the target gene flanked by loxP sites",
            "b) The second step is supply of Cre recombinase",
            "c) Integration of cre takes place under a controllable promoter followed by induction of the promoter",
            "d) Induction results in expression of cre, recombination along loxP sites and excision of the sequence between"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For cre-lox excision, the chromosomal copy of the target gene is replaced by target gene flanked by loxP sites. The second step is supply of cre recombinase. Integration of cre is done by a controllable promoter which is followed by the induction of promoter. This induction results in expression of cre and recombination along loxP sites, leading to excision."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "How much effect is there on the surrounding genes by the loxP sequence which is left after recombination has taken place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Little effect",
            "b) No effect",
            "c) Huge effect",
            "d) It depends on the nature of the surrounding gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally cre is introduced with the help of a promoter. But it can also be introduced by crossing it with a strain containing the gene or by infection with virus containing it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "The ability to control the expression of cre allows controlling what?",
        "Options": [
            "a) recombination",
            "b) replication",
            "c) excision",
            "d) packaging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the recombination has taken place, the loxP sequence remains there. The remaining loxP sequence has no effect on the surrounding genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Excision of DNA flanked by loxP sequences is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) subtle excision",
            "b) croxing",
            "c) floxing",
            "d) sequence specific excision"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ability to control the expression of cre allows when and where excision takes place. Specific excision of the target takes place if an expression is tissue or time specific."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "RNA molecule with catalytic activity is termed as________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ribosomes",
            "b) catalytic RNA",
            "c) reactive RNA",
            "d) ribozyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Excision of DNA flanked by loxP sequences is called as floxing at times. Other site specific recombination systems are also used."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for self cleavage reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is nucleophilic attack reaction by 2’ hydroxyl of RNA",
            "b) It is nucleophilic attack reaction by 3’ hydroxyl of RNA",
            "c) It is nucleophilic attack reaction by 2’ hydroxyl of DNA",
            "d) It is nucleophilic attack reaction by 3’ hydroxyl of DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Any RNA molecule with catalytic activity is termed as a ribozyme. Some of the catalytic activity can be removal of introns by self-splicing."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Self cleavage reaction can take place in?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) RNA",
            "c) Both DNA and RNA",
            "d) Can take place in both but is preferred in DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hepatitis delta virus, which is associated with hepatitis B is capable of self cleavage. Ribozymes mainly comprise of RNA molecules which are capable of self cleavage."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Cloning vectors designed for the purpose of synthesis of RNA and proteins are known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cloning vectors",
            "b) RNA vectors",
            "c) Bacteriophage vectors",
            "d) Expression vectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Expression vectors are those vectors which are used for the synthesis of RNA and protein i.e. cloned DNA sequences are used for expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "For studying processes such as splicing and cleavage, RNA is required. Choose the correct statement for this.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A mixture of different types of RNA is required",
            "b) Two types of RNA are required",
            "c) A few contaminating proteins are required",
            "d) Sodium hydroxide is required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For studying RNA processing events such as splicing and cleavage, RNA is required. Here, a single type of RNA is required and along with it, a few contaminating proteins are also used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "RNA can be synthesized by using vector. A vector with _______ is used and further through ________ RNA is isolated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) origin of replication, translation",
            "b) promoter, transcription",
            "c) promoter, translation",
            "d) origin of replication, transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vectors can be used at times for synthesis of RNA. A vector with the promoter is used and transcription is carried out in a bacterial cell and afterward RNA is isolated."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Promoters are generally used after isolation from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteriophage T7",
            "b) bacteriophage SP6",
            "c) baceriophage Mu",
            "d) both bacteriophage T7 and SP6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Isolation of RNA can’t be carried out easily from bacterial cells. Hence, the production of RNA is carried out by the transcription of cloned DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "By selecting the appropriate polymerase to activate the promoter ________ can be carried out _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) transcription, regardless of orientation",
            "b) transcription, only in one orientation",
            "c) translation, regardless of orientation",
            "d) translation, only in one orientation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Promoters used for the synthesis of RNA are generally obtained from bacteriophage T7 and SP6. They can also be obtained rarely from bacteriophage T3."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Guanylyl transferase and GTP are used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transcription",
            "b) Translation",
            "c) Capping of the message",
            "d) Packaging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By selecting the appropriate polymerase to activate the promoter, transcription can be carried out but it is regardless of the orientation."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Capping can be introduced by the use of cap analogue. Which of the statement is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cap analogue can be introduced at the end of the transcript",
            "b) Cap analogue can be introduced at the start of the transcript",
            "c) Cap analogue can be introduced anywhere in the transcript",
            "d) Cap analogue can be introduced both at the end and starting of the transcript"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At times, capping of the message is very necessary. Capping can be achieved by incubating the transcripts with enzymes such as guanylyl transferase and GTP."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "If the cells containing plasmids are infected with helper phage, which type of DNA can be produced, packaged and secreted into the medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single stranded DNA",
            "b) Double stranded DNA",
            "c) Both single and double stranded DNA",
            "d) Circular DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For achieving capping, cap analogue should be introduced. Cap analogue should be introduced at the starting of the transcript. It is so because it requires 5’ end."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Little quantities of radiolabelled proteins are required for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) co or post translational targeting",
            "b) modification of proteins",
            "c) both co or post translational targeting and modification of proteins",
            "d) crystallization for structural studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Protein synthesis is very important and they are having varied functions. Small quantities of radiolabelled proteins are required for co or post translational targeting and modification of proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "__________ quantities of _______ protein are required for determination of properties in biochemical and biological assays.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small, non-radiolabelled",
            "b) Small, radiolabelled",
            "c) Large, radiolablelled",
            "d) Large, non-radiolabelled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: At times, large and non-radiolabelled proteins are required for determination of properties in biochemical and biological assays. It is also required for carrying out the crystallization for structural studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "For the production of unlabelled and huge amount of proteins, which of the following is true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transcription is carried out in vivo and translation in vitro",
            "b) Transcription and translation both are carried out in vivo",
            "c) Transcription and translation both are carried out in vitro",
            "d) Transcription is carried out in vitro and translation in vivo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If small quantities of radiolabelled RNA are required, it can be produced by translation in vitro which is accomplished by transcription in vitro."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "How many methods are there, which are used for protein synthesis in vitro?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For having, large and unlabelled proteins, transcription and translation both should be carried out in vivo."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Reticulocytes are immature red cells, which are obtained from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rabbit",
            "b) pig",
            "c) human",
            "d) cow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are basically three methods which are used for protein synthesis in vitro. They are based on a lysate of reticulocytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "What is the use of adding micrococcal nuclease in the reticulocyte cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It degrades DNA",
            "b) It degrades mRNA",
            "c) It degrades proteins",
            "d) It degrades RNA and untranslated DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reticulocytes are immature red blood cells which are obtained from rabbits. The lysate of this is used for transcription in vitro."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "In ________ transcription and translation is coupled.",
        "Options": [
            "a) prokaryotes",
            "b) eukaryotes",
            "c) both prokaryotes and eukaryotes",
            "d) both prokaryotes and eukaryotes, but favourable in eukaryotes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The micrococcal nuclease is added in the reticulocyte cells in order to degrade the mRNA. This mRNA produces a high amount of background in translational products."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "In which of the following systems, transcription and translation are carried out together?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reticuloycte lysate",
            "b) Wheat gram extract",
            "c) Both in reticulocyte lysate and wheat gram extract",
            "d) S-30 extract"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The treatment of reticulocyte cells is done with EGTA. It chelates the calcium ions and they are required for the functioning of micrococcal nuclease. It is required for cleavage of mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "If overexpression of proteins takes place, they become toxic at times. In such a case _______ colonies are recovered after ______ with the recombinant plasmid.",
        "Options": [
            "a) few, translation",
            "b) few, transformation",
            "c) no, transformation",
            "d) no, translation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At times, overexpression of proteins takes place. It leads to toxicity. In such a case, no colonies are recovered after transformation with the recombinant plasmid. It is so because no colonies survive because of overexpression of the protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Ribosome binding site in E.coli is composed of which sequence primarily?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -GAGG-",
            "b) -CTCC-",
            "c) -ATGG-",
            "d) -CGTT-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ribosome binding site is responsible for initiating translation. It is composed of –GAGG- sequence primarily."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Translation starts at first _____ codon in the mRNA downstream from the ribosome binding site.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ACG",
            "b) AUG",
            "c) UAC",
            "d) CAG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Translation starts at first AUG codon in the mRNA downstream from the ribosome binding site. It is the start codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "If an expression vector contains all three, viz. a controllable promoter, a ribosome binding site and an initiation codon, then a hybrid protein is produced. The _______ region of hybrid protein is encoded by vector and the rest is expressed by the sequence inserted.",
        "Options": [
            "a) N terminal",
            "b) C terminal",
            "c) Both N & C terminal",
            "d) Middle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Expression of cloned sequences in E. coli requires a promoter, a ribosome binding site and an initiation codon. Initiation codon is the start codon AUG."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Proteins synthesized by carrying out a translation of the vector region and continuing it in the insert region is called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hybrid protein",
            "b) fusion protein",
            "c) combination protein",
            "d) insert protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If all three elements are present, then a hybrid protein is formed. The N terminal region of the hybrid protein is encoded by the vector and the rest is expressed by the sequence inserted."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "It is also possible to generate a fusion protein in which ______ is encoded by the vector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) N terminal",
            "b) C terminal",
            "c) Both N and C terminal",
            "d) Middle region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At times, translation of vector is carried out and is continued in the insert. Proteins produced by this method are known as fusion proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which of the following is present in E. coli rrnB operon for rRNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initiation codon",
            "b) Termination codon",
            "c) Both initiation and termination codon",
            "d) Both are absent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, N terminal is encoded by the vector. But at times it is also possible to generate a fusion protein by encoding C terminal."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Termination codon is required for stopping high levels of transcription of other regions such as _______ which might interfere with ___________ of the vector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) origin, replication",
            "b) end, replication",
            "c) end, stability",
            "d) origin, stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Initiation codon is present in all expression vectors, but few are also having termination codons. It is necessary to stop high levels of transcription. "
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Some vectors carry a mutant form of promoter known as lacUV5 promoter. It carries ______ in the promoter region and _____ the efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) point mutations, decreases",
            "b) point mutations, increases",
            "c) frameshift mutations, increases",
            "d) frameshift mutations, increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In some vectors, lacUV5 promoter is present. It is a mutant form and carries point mutations which increase the efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Lambda PL promoter is used in which vectors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cloning vectors",
            "b) Expression vectors",
            "c) Both cloning and expression vectors",
            "d) Bacteriophage Mu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lambda PL promoters are the promoters for the left region in bacteriophage lambda. It is widely used in expression vectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Choose the correct statement for rifampcin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It inactivates both E. coli polymerase and T7 polymerase",
            "b) It activates both E. coli polymerase and T7 polymerase",
            "c) It inhibits T7 polymerase but doesn’t inhibits E. coli polymerase",
            "d) It inhibits E. coli polymerase but doesn’t inhibits T7 polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The promoter is activated at a temperature higher than 30 degrees because at this temperature repressor is inactivated. "
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The ______ operon encodes proteins involved in arabinose metabolism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) araBCD",
            "b) araABD",
            "c) araBAD",
            "d) araDBA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rifampcin is added in order to reduce the transcription of other genes. It inhibits the E. coli RNA polymerase but doesn’t inhibit the T7 polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "tac promoter is an example of which type of promoter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hybrid promoter",
            "b) fusion promoter",
            "c) lacZ promoter",
            "d) araBAD promoter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The araBAD operon encodes proteins involved in arabinose metabolism. It is controlled by AraC transcriptional regulator."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The tac promoter is made by _____ region of trp promoter and _____ region of the lacUV5 promoter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10, 35",
            "b) 35, 10",
            "c) 10, 10",
            "d) 35, 35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hybrid promoters are those promoters which are produced by two promoters from different sources. Tac promoter is a hybrid promoter produced from trp promoter and lacUV5 promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Expression of T7 promoter- lac operator hybrid requires ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) T7 RNA polymerase",
            "b) An inducer such as IPTG",
            "c) Both T7 RNA polymerase and inducer such as IPTG",
            "d) T7 DNA polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It is a hybrid promoter made by 35 regions of trp promoter and 10 regions of the lacUV5 promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "When lacUV5 control system is used, addition of IPTG _______ the expression of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) activates, T7 RNA polymerase",
            "b) inactivates, T7 RNA polymerase",
            "c) activates, T7 DNA polymerase",
            "d) inactivates,  T7 DNA polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tac promoter includes the lac operator and is regulated by the repressor. The repressor is to be supplied by the host."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "There are some advantages of expressing protein as a fusion protein. It may enhance stability, folding ______ and ______ formation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) solubility, phosphodiester bond formation",
            "b) insolubility, phosphodiester bond formation",
            "c) solubility, disulphide bond formation",
            "d) insolubility, disulphidebond formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Expressing a protein as a fusion protein is advantageous. It may enhance stability, folding, solubility and disulphide bond formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "A short peptide region fused to a protein of interest is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tag",
            "b) oligonucleotide",
            "c) fragment",
            "d) dimer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A short peptide region (generally, a few nucleotides long) is fused to a protein of interest and is known as tag."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Maltose binding protein is the product of ______ gene in E.coli and located in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) malE, nucleus",
            "b) malD, nucleus",
            "c) malE, periplasmic space",
            "d) malD, periplasmic space"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GST enzyme is used for the conjunction of Glutathione molecules and is also having a protective function in many organisms. It is widely used as a basis for fusion proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Thioredexin protein contains two _______ residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cysteine",
            "b) cystine",
            "c) adenine",
            "d) guanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Maltose binding protein is the product malE gene in E.coli and is located in the periplasmic space. It is responsible for uptake of maltose and other sugars. "
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Often, protein to be expressed is fused with histidine and it is called as histidine tags. For their purification, matrix containing ______ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) calcium ions",
            "b) nickel ions",
            "c) iron ions",
            "d) fluorine ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This protein contains two cysteine residues and they are reversibly oxidized to cysteine residues."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Pel B protein is produced in plants and helps in the degradation of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) vacuole",
            "b) plasma membrane",
            "c) cell wall",
            "d) mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Histidine tags are used in place of naturally occurring protein at times for fusion proteins. For purification, matrix containing nickel ions is used and is based on affinity purification."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Enterokinase is an intestinal enzyme that converts _______ to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pepsinogen, pepsin",
            "b) pepsin, pepsinogen",
            "c) trypsinogen, trypsin",
            "d) trypsin, trypsinogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pectate lyase or pelB protein is produced in plants and helps in the degradation of plant cell wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Cyanogen bromide is used for cleavage of junctions. It cleaves after ________ residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) methionine",
            "b) tryptophan",
            "c) cysteine",
            "d) phenolic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: His tagged proteins can be eluted using EDTA or a pH gradient from the matrix. They disrupt the chelation."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "If it is desirable to express two or more proteins simultaneously, then it is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hybrid of proteins",
            "b) fusion of proteins",
            "c) co-expression of proteins",
            "d) combination of proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If it is desirable to express two or more proteins simultaneously, then it is called as co-expression of proteins. There are varied uses of such proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "A considerable amount of modification can take place in the ______ region of RNA in _______ before translation. It affects the yield of proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) coding, prokaryotes",
            "b) coding, eukaryotes",
            "c) non-coding, prokaryotes",
            "d) non-coding, eukaryotes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For co-expression of proteins, there are two strategies which are used. The first is to use several different expression vectors at a single time. The second method is to use several independent sets of promoters and signals in a single vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Strong secondary structure in a message may affect ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) translation",
            "b) transcription",
            "c) both translation and transcription",
            "d) none of translation and transcription"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A considerable amount of modification in the coding region of the RNA can take place in eukaryotes before translation. This can have an effect on the yield of the protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "What is the function of T7 lysozyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attacking the peptidoglycan in bacterial cell walls",
            "b) Inhibitor of T7 polymerase",
            "c) Activator of T7 polymerase",
            "d) Both attacking the peptidogylcan in bacterial cell walls and inhibitor of T7 polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is not necessary that if transcription and translation initiate well, they continue well. Factors such as secondary structure, affect translation. There are other factors such as codon usage and codon meaning which affect translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "As the activity of T7 polymerase is reduced by lysosome, what is an effect on the rate of synthesis after induction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) May increase or decrease",
            "d) No effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: T7 lysozyme is used for reducing the level of expression from T7 promoters. It is phage encoded and serves a dual purpose. It attacks the peptidoglycan in bacterial cell walls and is an inhibitor of T7 polymerase."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Proteins at times are not soluble in the cell and form aggregates known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) coagulation",
            "b) aggregated mass",
            "c) inclusion bodies",
            "d) insoluble mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As the activity of T7 polymerase is reduced by the lysosome, resultantly the rate of synthesis after induction is also reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Lon protease is used for degradation of foreign proteins in E.coli cells. It is active against which type of proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Partially denatured proteins",
            "b) Completely denatured proteins",
            "c) Both partially and completely denatured proteins",
            "d) Intact proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Proteins are not always soluble and at times they form insoluble aggregates. These are called as inclusion bodies. It is to separate them out by centrifugation."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Lon mutation can lead to ______ and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mucoidy, UV sensitivity",
            "b) mucoidy, UV insensitivity",
            "c) overproduction of fats, UV sensitivity",
            "d) overproduction of fats, UV insensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At times, it is possible to solubilise proteins from the aggregated mass of proteins. And this further helps in correct folding."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Mutation in gale gene or cpsA-E gene cluster is used for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) suppression of mucoidy",
            "b) activation of mucoidy",
            "c) suppression of UV sensitivity",
            "d) both suppression of mucoidy and UV sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lon protease is used for degradation of foreign proteins. It is active against both partially and completely denatured proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "How many types of reporter gene constructs are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are mainly two constructs for the reporter gene. In the first construct, reporter gene completely replaces the target gene. In the second construct, there is a fusion between the target gene and the reporter gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "______ fluorescent protein should be used for determination of _______ of subcellular components.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One, age",
            "b) One, location",
            "c) More than one, location",
            "d) More than one, age"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Desired changes are made in the structure of the promoter in order to know about the region of expression. "
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Sequences can be cloned flanking the reporter genes using the transposon tagging approach. The use of reporter genes to identify sequences expressed in this way is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) trapping",
            "b) tagging",
            "c) identification",
            "d) blotting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fluorescent protein is used for location of subcellular components. More than one fluorescent protein should be used for exact determination of the location of the subcellular components. "
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "If detection of enhancers is done it is called as ______ and for detection of transcribed sequences, it is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) enhancer trapping, promoter trapping",
            "b) enhancer trapping, gene trapping",
            "c) promoter trapping, gene trapping",
            "d) promoter trapping, enhancer trapping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sequences can be cloned flanking the reporter genes using the transposon tagging approach and if sequences are identified in this way, then it is called as trapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "The enhancer trap system will _____ in the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) not replicate independently, host",
            "b) replicate independently, host",
            "c) not replicate independently, vector",
            "d) replicate independently, vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trapping can be classified into different types by using different types of constructs. If enhancer is detected it is called as enhancer trapping. For promoter, it is called as promoter trapping and for transcribed sequences it is called as gene trapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "For gene trap vector system, reporter gene and _____ are present. Reporter gene is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) selectable marker, having promoter",
            "b) selectable marker, promoterless",
            "c) helper phage, promoterless",
            "d) helper phage, having promoter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The enhancer trap system will not replicate independently in the host. But the detection can be done by using a selectable marker."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "The reporter gene in enhancer trap system is preceded by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) intron",
            "b) exon",
            "c) promoter",
            "d) origin of replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For gene trap vector system, reporter gene and a selectable marker are present. The reporter gene is promoterless. "
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Insertion of vector into intron gives rise to ________ it contains a part coming from intron and a part from ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) hybrid intron, exon",
            "b) hybrid vector, exon",
            "c) hybrid intron, target DNA sequence",
            "d) hybrid vector, target DNA sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reporter gene in the enhancer trap system is promoterless and it is preceded by introns.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "An organism containing a gene which doesn’t belong to it and is derived from somewhere else then the organism is said to be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transformed",
            "b) transgenic",
            "c) mutant",
            "d) modified"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An organism which contains a gene which doesn’t belong to it and is derived from somewhere else, it is said to be transgenic. "
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "If a host other than E.coli is to be used, what property of DNA to be inserted is disadvantageous?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular DNA",
            "b) Linear DNA",
            "c) Replicating DNA",
            "d) Non-replicating DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are basically two types of bacteria, gram negative and gram positive. E.coli is a gram negative bacterium. These two groups are having properties which make them different."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "If plasmids direct their own transfer from one bacterium cell to another, then they are called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) self-transmissible",
            "b) auto-transmissible",
            "c) autonomously replicating",
            "d) auto-transfer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the DNA is to be inserted in a host other than E.coli than the DNA can be circular or linear and it should be non-replicating. As it is non-replicating, it can be stably maintained in the host only by integration into replicon."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "If a plasmid can’t be transferred from one cell to another, then it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) non-transmissible",
            "b) non-mobilizable",
            "c) untransferrable",
            "d) immobilized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is important to transfer the plasmids from one bacterium to another. If, plasmids are able to direct their own transfer, then it is called as self-transmissible. There are some plasmids which do it with the help of other plasmids."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for shuttle vectors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) These are vector hybrids constructed from E.coli and other plasmids",
            "b) They are having a varied use",
            "c) They can replicate and selected in both the species",
            "d) They are the plasmids which are having naturally broad host range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some plasmids can’t be transferred from one cell to another even with the help of other plasmids. Such plasmids are said to be non-mobilizable."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Which of the bacteria are used as hosts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-positive",
            "b) Gram-negative",
            "c) Both gram positive and negative are preferred equally",
            "d) Both can be used but gram positive is preferred"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shuttle vectors are those vector hybrids which are constructed artificially with the help of E.coli and other plasmids. They are able to replicate and selected in both the species and thus they are having a varied use. These are the plasmids which are having artificially broad host range because of the introduction of an extra origin of replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Basically, there are how many methods for introduction of DNA into the bacterial cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gram positive bacteria are particularly used as hosts. It is so because they secrete the expressed proteins in the growth medium at a much higher rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Competence is determined by the excretion into growth medium of _______ & _________ proteins called as competence proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cellular & high molecular weight",
            "b) cellular & low molecular weight",
            "c) extracellular & low molecular weight",
            "d) extracellular & high molecular weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are basically three methods for introduction of DNA into the bacterial cells. These are the introduction of naked DNA, transformation of protoplasts and conjugation."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Natural transformation can be relieved by the use of protoplasts, in the presence of osmotic buffer and polyethylene glycol. What are protoplasts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protoplasts are the cells from which cell membrane has been removed",
            "b) Protoplasts are the cells from which cell wall has been removed",
            "c) Protoplasts are the cells from which vacuole has been removed",
            "d) Protoplasts are the cells from which golgi bodies are removed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: These include species which exhibit natural competence. It means that they take up DNA without any physiological treatment."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Transfer of plasmids from one cell to another can also be done conjugation. The plasmid to be transferred known as ______ is often unable to do so by itself and thus it relies on other plasmids known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) cargo, conjugal",
            "b) conjugal, cargo",
            "c) cargo, helper",
            "d) conjugal, helper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Competence proteins are the proteins which are extracellular and low molecular weight and they help in determination of competence. Competence further develops as cell density."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "The transfer of plasmid from one bacterial cell to another when cargo and conjugal plasmids are used, it is usually is carried out by _____ mating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) diparental",
            "b) uniparental",
            "c) triparental",
            "d) multiparental"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Protoplasts are the cells from which the cell wall has been removed. They help in relieving natural transformation in the presence of osmotic buffer and polyethylene glycol."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "One of the commonly used markers is the URA3 gene. It encodes for ______ biosynthesis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) adenine",
            "b) uracil",
            "c) guanine",
            "d) cytosine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: URA3 gene is a commonly used selectable marker. It encodes an enzyme for uracil biosynthesis. The enzyme encoded is orotidine-5’-phosphate decarboxylase."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "CAN1 gene encodes a permease that causes uptake of _________ analogue.",
        "Options": [
            "a) toxic guanidine",
            "b) toxic arginine",
            "c) non-toxic guanidine",
            "d) non-toxic arginine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CAN1 gene encodes a permease that causes uptake of toxic arginine analogue. It causes consequent cell death. "
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Phosphoribosyl amino-imidazole carboxylase is a component of _______ biosynthesis pathway.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pyrimidine",
            "b) purine",
            "c) both purine and pyrimidine",
            "d) only adenine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Loss of SUP4 abolishes canavanine uptake. It is an arginine analogue. It causes canavanine resistance and cells can be readily selected."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Cells that have lost SUP4 gene acquire _____ pigment and are visibly distinguishable from others.",
        "Options": [
            "a) red",
            "b) blue",
            "c) green",
            "d) pink"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phosphoribosyl amino-imidazole carboxylase is a component of the purine biosynthesis pathway. The mutation for this enzyme is used in the selection of SUP4 gene. "
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Cells mutant in _____ gene can be selected by using 5-fluoro orotic acid, which is turned into ____ products by wild type protein.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SUP4, toxic",
            "b) SUP4, non-toxic",
            "c) URA3, toxic",
            "d) URA3, non-toxic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cells that have lost SUP4 gene acquire red colour and this makes them visibly distinguishable from others. This is the basis for selection."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "The replicating plasmid vectors in yeast can be divided broadly into how many categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cells mutant in URA3 gene can be selected by using 5-fluoro orotic acid, which is turned into toxic products by wild type protein. URA3 gene is responsible for uracil biosynthesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "CEN4 in YCp50 is an example of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) tetracycline resistant gene",
            "b) ampicillin resistant gene",
            "c) chromosomal centromeric sequence",
            "d) autonomously replicating sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The replicating plasmid vectors in yeast can be broadly divided into two main categories. These are yeast centromeric plasmid and yeast episomal plasmid vectors. "
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Yeast episomal plasmids have the following feature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They contain ARS and CEL both",
            "b) They contain ARS but not CEL",
            "c) They contain CEL but not ARS",
            "d) CEL is necessarily present but ARS may or may not be present"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yeast centromeric plasmid contains ampicillin and tetracycline resistance gene along with an origin of replication."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Cis-acting REP 3 sequence is present in Yeast episomal plasmids. Choose the statement which holds true for it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is present along with chromosomal centromeric sequence",
            "b) It is the site of action of proteins that help in partitioning",
            "c) It gives less stability to that of YCs",
            "d) The copy number is low than that of YCs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CEN4 in YCp50is an example of chromosomal centromeric sequence. It allows partitioning of the plasmid in the same way as endogenous chromosomes are partitioned."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "When YAC is used to clone DNA. What is the size of the DNA that can be cloned?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large (upto megabases)",
            "b) Small (upto few hundred bases)",
            "c) No size restriction",
            "d) Medium (upto kilobases)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: YACs are sophisticated cloning vectors that are used for propagating large stretches of DNA which are upto a few megabases."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "TEL is the ______ sequence derived from the ends of ribosomal RNA-encoding molecules from the macromolecules of the protozoan Tetrahyena.",
        "Options": [
            "a) centromeric",
            "b) telomeric",
            "c) can be either centromeric or telomeric",
            "d) can be present anywhere on the chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TEL is the telomeric sequence derived from the ends of ribosomal RNA-encoding molecules from the macromolecules of the protozoan Tetrahyena. It is a part of YAC."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement for YAC vectors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The YAC molecule is approximately 10 kb in size",
            "b) It contains both yeast origin of replication and prokaryotic origin of replication",
            "c) It doesn’t contain ampicillin resistant gene",
            "d) It contains TEL sequence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: YAC vectors are approximately 10kb in size. It contains both yeast origin of replication and prokaryotic origin of replication. It also contains TEL sequence and an ampicillin resistant gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "If YAC DNA is digested with BamHI and ECoRI, how many fragments are generated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If YAC DNA is digested with BamHI and ECoRI, three fragments are generated. Two fragments are having TEL sequence and one is lacking this sequence."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "GAL1 is a controllable promoter and is obtained from genes for galactose metabolism. It is known for encoding ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) UDP-galactose-4-empirase",
            "b) Galactokinase",
            "c) Both UDP-galactose-4-empirase and galactokinase",
            "d) Glucokinase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transformed cells in the case of YAC can be selected by the presence of both URA3 and TRP1 genes. The presence of both these indicates that both the arms of YAC are acquired."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Transcription of GAL1 and GAL10 is suppressed in the presence of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) glucose",
            "b) galactose",
            "c) maltose",
            "d) fructose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GAL1 is a controllable promoter and is obtained from genes for galactose metabolism. It encodes for galactokinase and GAL10 encodes for UDP-galactose-4-empirase."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "How many deletion variations of GAL1 promoter are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transcription of GAL1 and GAL10 is suppressed in the presence of glucose and elevated in the presence of galactose."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Which of the following are advantageous to be used for expression of eukaryotic cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prokaryotic systems",
            "b) Yeast cells",
            "c) Fungi cells",
            "d) Algae cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In GAL1 promoter, there are 2 deletion variations present. These deletion variations are known as GALL and GALS."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "Secretion of overexpressed proteins by fusion to a secretion signal can be useful because it helps in bringing about correct _______ and _____ protein folding.",
        "Options": [
            "a) glycosylation, enhance",
            "b) glycosylation, not affect",
            "c) phosphorylation, enhance",
            "d) phosphorylation, not affect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Secretion of overexpressed proteins can be useful because it helps in bringing about correct glycosylation and also enhances protein folding. It also assists in purification."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "The enzyme used for breaking down of sucrose into glucose and fructose is called as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sucrase",
            "b) glucanase",
            "c) maltase",
            "d) invertase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Invertase is the enzyme which is used for breaking down of sucrose into glucose and fructose. Invertase is used as a secretion signal and is product of SUC2 gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "For introduction of exogenous DNA into S.cerevisiae ______ is added along with polyethylene glycol and heat shock treatment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) calcium chloride",
            "b) sodium acetate",
            "c) lithium acetate",
            "d) magnesium chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are mainly three methods which are used for the introduction of exogenous DNA into S.cervisiae. Lithium acetate is added along with polyethylene glycol and heat shock treatment."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Schizosaccharomyces pombe is yeast and it reproduces by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) budding",
            "b) fissing",
            "c) either budding or fissing",
            "d) a method of reproduction other than budding or fissing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Protoplast transformation is a method used for carrying out transformation but is more time consuming than method based on lithium acetate. But protoplast transformation gives a higher efficiency than method based on lithium acetate."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "The leu1+ marker encodes which enzyme?",
        "Options": [
            "a) orotidine-5’-phosphate decarboxylase",
            "b) beta isopropylmalate dehydrogenase",
            "c) orotidine-5’-phosphate decarboxylase or beta isopropylmalate dehydrogenase",
            "d) orotidine-5’-phosphate decarboxylase & beta isopropylmalate dehydrogenase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Schizosaccharomyces pombe is yeast which produces by fission but other yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae reproduces by budding."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "The replacement of one plasmid by another by introduction of the second plasmid into strain containing the first, followed by removal of the first by counterselection is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) shuffle vector",
            "b) plasmid shuffle",
            "c) counterselection plasmid",
            "d) combination plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The leu1+ marker encodes beta isopropylmalate dehydrogenase. Orotidine-5’-phosphate decarboxylase is another selectable marker and is encoded by ura4+ gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Promoters can be divided basically into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plasmid shuffle is the system where one plasmid is replaced by another via introduction of the second plasmid into the strain containing first. It is followed by the removal of first by counterselction."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "nmt1+ gene is used for _____ biosynthesis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) uracil",
            "b) adenine",
            "c) cytosine",
            "d) thiamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Promoters can be mainly divided into two types mainly and these are known as constitutive and inducible promoters."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Species which can grow on _______ as a carbon source are called as methylotropic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) methylase",
            "b) methanol",
            "c) methane",
            "d) methanoic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: nmt1+ gene is used for thiamine biosynthesis. It is the gene from which inducible promoter is obtained. "
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Chlamyodomonas reinhardtii is a green _________ algae.",
        "Options": [
            "a) unicellular",
            "b) di-cellular",
            "c) multicellular",
            "d) either unicellular or di-cellular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chlamyodomonas reinhardtii is a green, unicellular algae. It has been used as a model system and studies have been carried out."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Chlamyodomonas genome is _______ rich.",
        "Options": [
            "a) AT",
            "b) GC",
            "c) Only A",
            "d) Only C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chlamyodomonas genome is very GC rich. Hence, heterologous genes can’t be expressed until they come from a GC rich genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Transformation of Chlamydomonas is most efficient in which method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lithium acetate method",
            "b) Electroporation",
            "c) Protoplast based method",
            "d) Both electroporation and protoplast based method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Integration of DNA into the Chlamydomonas genome is via non-homologous recombination. And because of this gene disruption can’t be carried out efficiently. "
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "OEE1 gene encodes a component of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) photosystem I",
            "b) photosystem II",
            "c) both photosystem I and II",
            "d) which neither belongs to photosystem I nor II"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transformation of Chlamydomonas is most efficient in the protoplast method. In this autolysin is used in order to carry out cell wall degradation."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Homologue of yeast ARG4 in Chlamydomonas is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARG1",
            "b) ARG2",
            "c) ARG5",
            "d) ARG7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: OEE1 gene encodes a component which is a component of photosystem II. It allows mutant cells lacking that polypeptide to grow photoautotrophically. "
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "cw15 is a mutant strain, it ________ and thus called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lacks cell wall, natural protoplast",
            "b) lacks cell wall, artificial protoplast",
            "c) has cell wall, artificial protoplast",
            "d) has cell wall, natural protoplast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ARG4 is present in yeast and is used for the production of arginine and as a selectable marker. Homologue of yeast ARG4 in Chlamydomonas is ARG7."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "For Chlorella, which method is used for DNA uptake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electroporation",
            "b) Direct uptake of naked DNA",
            "c) Conjugation",
            "d) Chemically induced uptake by protoplast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: cw15 is a mutant strain. It lacks a cell wall and thus it is called as natural protoplast. It is so because protoplasts are those structures which lack a cell wall. "
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Members of genera Haematococcus are used for production of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) xanthenoid",
            "b) carotenoid",
            "c) chlorophyll",
            "d) carotenoid and xanthenoid both"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genetic manipulation of green algae such as Volvox carteri is carried out by using nitrogen reductase or antibiotic resistance. They act as selectable markers."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "The disease crown gall is caused by which bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agrobacterium tumefaciens",
            "b) Agrobacterium rhizogenes",
            "c) Agrobacterium tumefaciens & rhizogenes bacterium causes the disease crown gall",
            "d) Any bacteria belonging to genera Rhizobium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disease crown gall is caused by Agrobacterium tumefaciens.  Agrobacterium rhizogenes causes the disease hair root. Agrobacterium mediated transfer forms a basis for the transfer of DNA in vascular plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Agrobacterium tumefaciens form ______ plasmids and Agrobacterium rhizogenes form _______ plasmids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) root inducing, tumour inducing",
            "b) tumour inducing, root inducing",
            "c) tumour inducing, shoot inducing",
            "d) non-tumour inducing, shoot inducing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The former bacterium forms tumour inducing plasmids whereas the second bacterium forms root inducing plasmids. These plasmids are large in size."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Transfer of T DNA depends on a set of genes called as ______ if they are present on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vir, chromosome",
            "b) chv, tumour inducing plasmid",
            "c) chv, chromosome",
            "d) vir, whether they are present on tumour inducing plasmid or chromosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: T-DNA (Transferred DNA) is the region which is to be transported from the bacterium to the nucleus of the vascular plant and thus it is very important."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "What is the function of onc genes in TDNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tumour suppressing potential",
            "b) Tumour inducing potential",
            "c) Either tumour inducing or suppressing depending on the conditions",
            "d) Act as replicative genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transfer of TDNA depends on a set of genes known as vir if present on tumour inducing plasmids and chv if they are present on chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Which of the plant growth regulators are produced by TDNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salicyclic acid",
            "b) Cytokinin",
            "c) Cytokinin and Auxin",
            "d) Jasmonic Acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Onc genes present in TDNA act as tumour inducing genes. Tumour inducing potential is also known as oncogenity."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "If a small intermediate vector system is used along with a selectable marker, then it is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fusion plasmids",
            "b) hybrid plasmids",
            "c) co-integrative plasmids",
            "d) complex plasmids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TDNA is having oncogenes and apart from it also produces plant growth regulators cytokinins and auxin. These plant growth regulators are plant hormones and are called as phytohormones."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "If transfer of DNA from Agrobacterium to plants is done via incubation of explanted material and the vector containing DNA of interest and then selection is done via selectable marker then this method is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transformation",
            "b) co-cultivation",
            "c) co-transformation",
            "d) floral dipping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tumour inducing plasmids are very large in size and thus they can be manipulated easily. In order to overcome this, small integrating plasmids with a selectable marker are used and it is known as co-integrative plasmid. They are then further inserted into the bacterium."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "If gene of interest is inserted into protoplasts but the transformation is not stable, then it is called as __________ expression systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) permanent",
            "b) temporary",
            "c) transient",
            "d) unstable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As, we know Ti plasmid is difficult to manipulate because eof larger size, other alternatives are used. Binary vector system contains the gene of interest flanked by border repeats. Border repeats are the sequences present in the Ti plasmid originally. With the help of it, transfer is done into the plants. "
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "35S promoter is obtained from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tobacco mosaic virus",
            "b) Cauliflower mosaic virus",
            "c) Agrobacterium",
            "d) Arabdopsis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Co-cultivation is the method of incubation of explanted material and the vector containing DNA of interest. Further selection is done via selectable marker such as antibiotic resistance. Floral dipping is an approach used for plant Arabidopsis."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the following promoter is having high tissue specificity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35S promoter",
            "b) nos promoter",
            "c) 35S & nos promoters are having high specificity",
            "d) neither of the promoter is having high specificity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the gene of interest is inserted into protoplasts but the transformation is not stable, then it is called as transient expression systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "What is the function of glyphosate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a fungicide",
            "b) It is an herbicide",
            "c) It is an enzyme used in place of glucose as a carbon source",
            "d) It is used for adding phosphate groups"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 35S promoter is obtained from cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV). It is responsible for the generation of 35S transcript in infected cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Baciullus thuringiensis is used for the production of toxins which can be used as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) insecticides",
            "b) pesticides",
            "c) germicides",
            "d) fungicides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Both the promoters, 35S and CaMV are having low tissue specificity. Tissue specificity can be achieved by insertion of sequences from other promoters."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of the following compounds control ripening in tomatoes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auxin",
            "b) Cytokinin",
            "c) Ethylene",
            "d) Jasmonic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glyphosate is an herbicide. It inhibits an enzyme which is necessary for shikmic acid pathway."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Mitochondrial genome encodes tRNAs ___________ and polypeptides involved in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) mRNAs, oxidative phosphorylation",
            "b) rRNAs, oxidative phosphorylation",
            "c) rRNAs, reductive phosphorylation",
            "d) mRNAs, reductive phosphorylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mitochondrial genome encodes tRNAs, rRNAs and polypeptides which are required for oxidative phosphorylation. tRNAs and rRNAs are also encoded by chloroplast genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Atrazine is a herbicide and it acts on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reaction centre in photosystemI",
            "b) reaction centre in photosytemII",
            "c) reaction centre in both the photosystems",
            "d) neither of the photosystems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Atrazine is a herbicide and it acts on a reaction centre present in photosystem II. This herbicide is a product of chloroplast psbA gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "atpB encodes _______ subunit of ATP synthase, an enzyme used for generation of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) beta, ADP",
            "b) alpha, ATP",
            "c) beta, ATP",
            "d) alpha, ADP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At times, the presence of a normal gene in the organelle doesn’t create a problem and thus inserting modified organelle genes into the nucleus may be expressed well. Such an expression is called a allotropic gene expression."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Bacterial aadA gene is responsible for conferring resistance to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) spectinomycin",
            "b) streptomycin",
            "c) ampicillin",
            "d) spectomycin and streptomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: atpB encodes a beta subunit of ATP synthase, it is a multisubunit complex used for generation ATP and it is done in the presence of light reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "How many types of the chloroplast are there in Chlamydomonas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacterial aadA gene is responsible for conferring resistance to both streptomycin and spectomycin. It is used a selectable marker for chloroplast transformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "For transformation of the chloroplast of higher plants, a vector is used which ______ in the chloroplast.",
        "Options": [
            "a) doesn’t replicates",
            "b) replicates",
            "c) may or may not replicate",
            "d) replicates under certain specified conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chlamydomonas is having only one type of chloroplast and this property makes it easier to use it for transformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Mutant strains of Saccharomyces cervevisiae in which endogenous DNA are deleted are called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rho0",
            "b) synthetic rho",
            "c) rho+",
            "d) rho-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For transformation of the chloroplast of higher plants, a vector is used which doesn’t replicates in the chloroplast. There is a selectable marker which is present and the gene of interest is flanked by chloroplast DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "COX3 gene is a selectable marker. Choose the correct statement with respect to it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) It confers the ability to grow by anaerobic respiration",
            "b) It confers the ability to grow by aerobic respiration",
            "c) It confers the ability to grow in absence of uracil",
            "d) It confers the ability to grow in lithium acetate medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cholorplast can’t be transferred through pollen for all the crops. Thus incorporation of transgenes in chloroplast may offer more biological containment then that incorporation into nucleus may offer."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "The ARG8m gene which produces an enzyme for arginine biosynthesis is located in _______ and is of ______ origin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) mitochondrial, nuclear",
            "b) nuclear, mitochondrial",
            "c) nuclear, nuclear",
            "d) mitochondrial, mitochondrial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Mutant strains of Saccharomyces cervevisiae in which endogenous DNA are deleted are called as rho0. Synthetic rho- strains are produced when DNA is introduced into mitochondria and concatamers are produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Barstar is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNAse",
            "b) RNAse inhibitor",
            "c) DNAse",
            "d) DNAse inhibitor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: COX3 gene is used as a selectable marker. It confers the ability to grow by aerobic respiration in the mutant cells for mitochondrial COX3 gene. "
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Caenorhabditis elegans is a model organism of great importance in biological systems. It is a/an _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) algae",
            "b) parasite",
            "c) fungi",
            "d) nematode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ARG8m gene which produces an enzyme for arginine biosynthesis is located in the mitochondria but is of nuclear origin. It is designed for expression in the mitochondrion and will confer the ability to grow in the absence of arginine."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Autographa californica nuclear polyhedrois virus (AcNPV) is commonly used bacilovirus for infecting cultured cells. The virus is ________ and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) single stranded, linear",
            "b) double stranded, linear",
            "c) double stranded, circular",
            "d) single stranded, circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: AcNPV is a commonly used bacilovirus for infecting cultured cells. It is double stranded and circular. It is isolated from caterpillar and infects around 30 species."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "DNA replication of the AcNPV takes 6 hours after infection. After how many hours of infection new virus particles are produced by budding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 hrs",
            "b) 10 hrs",
            "c) 12 hrs",
            "d) 16 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After 10 hrs of infection, new virus particles are produced. And these virus particles are termed as extracellular virus particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The polyhedrin and p10 protein are produced in ____________ amount and other genes are expressed in _________ amount.",
        "Options": [
            "a) low, high",
            "b) high, high",
            "c) high, low",
            "d) low, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The virus particles are held together by polyhedron and p10 proteins. Polyhedron protein is of 29kDa. The virus particles are held together as occlusion bodies."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Expression of proteins using nuclear polyhedrosis viruses is advantageous because it gives _______ protein yields and post-translational modifications are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high, not possible",
            "b) high, possible",
            "c) low, possible",
            "d) low, not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The polyhedron and p10 protein are expressed in large amounts and other genes are expressed in low amount. The former proteins are up to 20% of protein synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "The size of the viral genome is large and thus poses a problem. This problem can be resolved by using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) transfer vector",
            "b) co-integration plasmid",
            "c) hybrid vector",
            "d) fusion vector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Expression of proteins using nuclear polyhedrosis viruses is advantageous because it gives high protein yields and post-translational modifications are also possible. These modifications are not possible in prokaryotic systems and yeast or are carried out very less."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "The gene of interest is inserted into transfer vector and then further into viral genome leading to the formation of modified virus. How can plaques from modified virus differentiated from plaques from wild-type virus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemically",
            "b) Visually",
            "c) On the basis of magnetic properties",
            "d) On the basis of longeitivity of plaques"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The size of the viral genome is a problem because it is very large. It is solved by using a transfer vector. Transfer vector is composed of sequences that allow propagation of E.coli, the viral promoter, the polyhedrin mRNA polyadenylation signal and the polyhedron gene is flanked by the viral sequences."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "If the DNA is linearized, what is the effect on the recombination frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The recombination frequency decreases",
            "b) The recombination frequency increases",
            "c) The recombination may increase or decrease depending on the amount of DNA",
            "d) There is no effect on the recombination frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plaques from the recombinant virus and from the wild type virus can be differentiated simply visually."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "For the generation of recombinant baculovirus, recombinants can be selected by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) blue-white screening",
            "b) antibiotic resistance",
            "c) either antibiotic resistance or blue white screening",
            "d) radioactivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the DNA is linearixed, the recombination frequency increases. It is so because eit makes the DNA more recombinogenic."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Transgenic Drosophila can be created by microinjection of DNA into the embryos. These embryos are at which stage of development?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One-cell stage",
            "b) Pre-blastoderm stage",
            "c) Blastoderm",
            "d) Morula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transgenic Drosophila can be created by microinjection of DNA into the embryos. The embryo should be at pre-blastodermal stage. Other developmental stages such as blastoderm and morula follow the pre-blastodermal stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Syncytium is a layer of ______ that have not been separated into individual cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) nuclei",
            "b) mitochondria",
            "c) cytoplasm",
            "d) nuclei and cytoplasm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Syncytium is a layer of nuclei which is not divided into separate individual cells. This is found at pre-blastodermal stage of development. "
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "______ integration systems are used for the transfer of DNA in Drosophila and it is composed of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Artificial, P elements",
            "b) Artificial, S elements",
            "c) Natural, P elements",
            "d) Natural, S elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Drosophila, only nuclei cells give rise to germline cells. These germline cells are located at one end of the embryo and acquire DNA stably."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Only the _____ part of Drosophila is transgenic and the rest is not. This is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) germline cell, mosaic",
            "b) nurse cells, mosaic",
            "c) germline cells, hybrid",
            "d) nurse cells, hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Drosophila, the natural integration systems are used for the transfer of DNA and it is composed of transposable elements. These transposable elements are known as P elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "rosy gene is used as a selectable marker for transformation in Drosophila, it produces an enzyme required for the synthesis of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) wing pigment",
            "b) eye pigment",
            "c) both eye and wing pigment",
            "d) thorax pigment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only the germline cells portion (but not necessarily all germline cells) is modified and the rest is non-transgenic. This is collectively known as mosaic."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Wild-type Drosophila flies are _____  to ethanol supplied in food.",
        "Options": [
            "a) resistant",
            "b) non-resistant",
            "c) resistant at low concentration and non-resistant at higher concentration",
            "d) resistant at higher concentrations and non-resistant at lower concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rosy gene is used as a selectable marker for transformation in Drosophila, it produces enzyme xanthine dehydrogenase and it is required for pigments of the eye."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "Cis-acting sites should be present in the vector for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) replication",
            "b) selecting recombinants by acting as a marker",
            "c) transposition",
            "d) providing high copy number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wild type genes have brick-red eyes whereas rosy mutant have crimson red eyes. Thus, rosy genes can be used as selectable marker. "
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The host should ____ P elements, these elements lead to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) not have, instability",
            "b) have, stability",
            "c) not have, increase the time taken for integration",
            "d) have, reduces the time taken for integration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wild type flies are resistant to ethanol supplied in the food. This property can be exploited as a selectable marker and which is in the form of alcohol dehydrogenase gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Where do P elements integrate into the genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At specifically defined sites",
            "b) Randomly",
            "c) Only at the ends of the genome",
            "d) Integration depends on reaction conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Apart from selectable markers, cis acting sites should also be present. These are required for transposition."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Transient gene silencing can be carried out by microinjecting ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) single stranded RNA",
            "b) double stranded DNA",
            "c) double stranded RNA",
            "d) either double stranded DNA or RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The host should not have P elements, these elements lead to instability. It is so because they are responsible for transposition."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Lesch-Nyhan syndrome is caused by the deficiency of the enzyme hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyl transferase (HGPRT). Cells deficient in HGPRT die in a medium containing which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypoxanthine and thymidine",
            "b) Thymidine",
            "c) Aminopterin and thymidine",
            "d) Hypoxanthine, thymidine and aminopterin (HAT medium)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: HGPRT deficient cells in the medium containing all three hypoxanthine, thymidine and aminopterin. It is so because aminopterin blocks the endogenous synthesis of purines needed for the synthesis of nucleic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Presence of wild-type DNA onto the HGPRT– in the presence of _______ led to DNA uptake and stable transformation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lithium acetate",
            "b) calcium phosphate",
            "c) sodium chloride",
            "d) aluminum sulphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Presence of wild type in HGPRT—in the presence of calcium phosphate led to DNA uptake and stable transformation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Hygromycin is used as a selectable marker in mammalian cultured cells. It is used for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) initiating protein synthesis",
            "b) inhibiting protein synthesis",
            "c) initiating DNA binding process",
            "d) inhibiting DNA binding process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cells deficient in thymidine kinase are also killed in HAT medium. It is so because pyrimidine synthesis is also blocked in the presence of aminopterin and utilization of thymidine in the HAT medium requires a functional TK. "
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Puromycin is a protein synthesis inhibitor. It is conferred by _______ gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) streptococcal",
            "b) bacilovirus",
            "c) streptomyces",
            "d) both streptococcal and streptomyces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hygromycin is used as a protein synthesis inhibitor. It is conferred by a bacterial hph gene which encodes hygromycin phosphotransferase. Resistance to hygromycin is used as a selectable marker."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Resistance to bleomycin (zeocin) is used as a selectable marker for mammalian cultured cells and its function is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA damaging agent",
            "b) DNA synthesis promoter",
            "c) Inhibiting RNA synthesis",
            "d) Activating RNA synthesis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Puromycin is a protein synthesis inhibitor and is conferred by streptomyces gene. It does so by encoding puromycin-N-acetyltransferase."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Resistance to methotrexate, which inhibits the enzyme dihydrofolate reductase (DHFR) is used as a selectable marker. This enzyme is involved in the synthesis of _____ carbon units and is required for _____ biosynthesis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) two, nucleoside",
            "b) two, nucleotide",
            "c) one, nucleotide",
            "d) one, nucleoside"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Resistance to bleomycin (zeocin) is used as a selectable marker for mammalian cultured cells and it is a DNA damaging agent. It does so by expression of a binding protein."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Many mammalian cells contain Thymidine Kinase, the mammalian enzyme uses the analogue _____ than does the viral enzyme.",
        "Options": [
            "a) more efficiently",
            "b) less efficiently",
            "c) with same efficiency",
            "d) either with same or more efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Resistance to methotrexate, which is used as a selectable marker inhibits DHFR enzyme. This enzyme is involved in the synthesis of one carbon units and is required for nucleoside synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "A wide range of host cell lines are available and commonly used human cell lines are obtained from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) kidney",
            "b) liver",
            "c) lymphoblast from leukaemia patient",
            "d) both kidney and lymphoblast from a leukaemia patient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Histidinol dehydrogenase is also used as a selectable marker. It allows synthesis of histdidine from exogenous histanol and protects from toxic effects of histidinol."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "DEAE-dextran is used for introduction of DNA. It is a modified _____ and is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) polysaccharide, negatively",
            "b) polysaccharide, positively",
            "c) monosaccharide, positively",
            "d) monosaccharide, negatively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many mammalian cells contain thymidine kinase, the mammalian enzyme uses the analogue less efficiently than the viral enzyme. If cells lack viral enzyme they are resistant to analogue and are able to grow in a mammalian enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Cells whose contents have been removed and replaced, by swelling and shrinking in solutions of suitable osmotic strength are called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) protoplast",
            "b) ghosts",
            "c) shrunken cells",
            "d) vacuole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is a wide range of host cell lines available. Commonly used human cell lines are HeLa 293T, obtained from kidney and Jurkat which is obtained from lymphoblast from a leukaemia patient."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "In ___________ cells, virus replication doesn’t take place and viral DNA ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) non-permissive, is also not expressed",
            "b) permissive, is also not expressed",
            "c) non-permissive, can be expressed",
            "d) non-permissive, is always expressed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are various methods for the uptake of transformation DNA such as electroporation and DEAE-dextran method. It is a modified polysaccharide and is positively charged. It forms a complex with negatively charged DNA and is taken into cells by endocytosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "SV40 is a virus and it produces how many transcripts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ghosts are those cells whose contents have been removed and replaced by swelling and shrinking in solutions of suitable osmotic strength. Red blood ghosts are also used for the introduction of DNA into mammalian cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "T protein is required for replication. It is a product of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) delayed early transcription",
            "b) late transcription",
            "c) early transcription",
            "d) both early and late replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: T protein is required for replication and it is a product of early transcription. If T protein is absent, the introduction of DNA takes place only by integration."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Vaccinia virus is a commonly used virus and it is a member of pox virus family. It has a large genome of _____________ and can accept at least ____________ of foreign DNA.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200kb, 25kb",
            "b) 1000kb, 200kb",
            "c) 500kb, 50kb",
            "d) 800kb, 100kb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vaccinia virus is a commonly used virus. It is having a large genome of size 200kb and can atleast accept foreign DNA of size 25kb."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Vaccinia virus produces its own ______ which is functional in _____ of infected cells where the virus also replicates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase, nucleus",
            "b) DNA polymerase, cytoplasm",
            "c) RNA polymerase, cytoplasm",
            "d) RNA polymerase, nucleus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vaccinia virus produces its own RNA polymerase which is functional in the cytoplasm of infected cells and virus also replicates here."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "LNSX is a retrovirus and is combined with ______ in order to create a shuttle vector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) eukaryotic plasmid",
            "b) prokaryotic plasmid",
            "c) either eukaryotic or prokaryotic plasmid",
            "d) yeast plasmid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Use of retrovirus is quite beneficial for the manipulation of cells in the culture. It is so because they infect the susceptible cells with great efficiency and bring about stable integration."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "The retroviral transfected DNA is infected into mammalian cells by helper retrovirus. Helper retrovirus should not be packaged and the method adopted for this is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deletion of the packaging signal in the helper genome",
            "b) Deletion of multiple parts of the helper genome",
            "c) Division of the helper genome into several pieces",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LNSX is a retrovirus and is combined with a prokaryotic plasmid so that it can act as a shuttle vector. The retrovirus contains neomycin resistance gene as a selectable marker and a promoter."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement in respect to MACs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are mammalian or human artificial chromosomes",
            "b) Large stretches of DNA (in excess of 100 kb) can be inserted",
            "c) A selectable marker is required",
            "d) It can be maintained for long term"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Helper retrovirus is used for introduction of transfected DNA into mammalian cells. But it is necessary that helper retrovirus itself should not be packaged. It can be achieved by deletion of the packaging signal in the helper genome, deletion of multiple parts of the helper genome and division of the helper genome into several pieces."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Centromere is the most important component of the human artificial chromosome. It is constructed from tandemly repeated copies of 171 bp of ______ DNA sequence.",
        "Options": [
            "a) alpha satellite",
            "b) beta satellite",
            "c) satellite 2",
            "d) satellite 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nowdays, MACs have been developed and they are the mammalian or human artificial chromosomes. They can carry large stretches of DNA and can be maintained for long term without the requirement of being selected."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Constitutive promoters are majorly obtained from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fungi",
            "b) bacteria",
            "c) mammalian cells",
            "d) viral cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Centromere is the most important component of the human artificial chromosome. It is constructed from tandemly repeated copies of 171 bp of alpha satellite DNA sequence. There are other satellite DNA sequences such as beta, satellite 1 and 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "In naturally occurring bacterial systems, tetracycline binding repressor protein binds in the _____ of tetracycline to the control sequence and _______ transcription.",
        "Options": [
            "a) presence, activates",
            "b) absence, activates",
            "c) absence, inactivates",
            "d) presence, inactivates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Constitutive promoters are majorly obtained from viral cells. They commonly include, SV40 promoters, adenovirus major late promoter etc. In some cases they are also obtained from mammalian cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Expression of tTA gene is ________ by doxycycline which is _______ analogue.",
        "Options": [
            "a) activated, tetracycline",
            "b) inactivated, chloramphenicol",
            "c) activated, chloramphenicol",
            "d) inactivated, tetracycline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In naturally occurring bacterial systems, tetracycline binding repressor protein binds in the absence of tetracycline to the control sequence tet0 and inactivates transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "Glucorticoid-responsive element is ______ promoter from ______ of mouse mammory tumour virus (MMTV).",
        "Options": [
            "a) inducible, short terminal repeat region",
            "b) inducible, long terminal repeat region",
            "c) constitutive, short terminal repeat region",
            "d) constitutive, long terminal repeat region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transactivator protein is the protein formed by fusion of tetracycline binding repressor protein to the transcription activator protein from herpes simple virus. The protein which is repressing originally transforms into activating in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "There are a group of promoters from the genes for metallothioneins. These are a group of proteins rich in ______ residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) cysteine",
            "b) methionine",
            "c) either cysteine or methionine",
            "d) cysteine and methionine both"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Expression of tTA gene is inactivated by doxycyline which is tetracycline analogue. It is very strong and the expression is very less in the presence of doxycycline."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The amount of expression of DNA inserted into a vector _______ on promoter and ______ on chromosomal location.",
        "Options": [
            "a) depends only on, not depends",
            "b) depends, depends also",
            "c) doesn’t depends, but depends",
            "d) neither depends, nor depends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glucorticoid-responsive element is an inducible promoter from the long terminal repeat region of MMTV. Promoters are basically of two types constitutive and inducible."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "If the embryo is at one-cell stage then it is found in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ovary",
            "b) oviduct",
            "c) uterus",
            "d) either ovary or uterus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When embryo is at one-cell stage it is found in oviduct. This is important for the generation of whole organisms that are transgenic. Isolation of one-cell embryo is done and then it is micro-injected into the pro-nucleus."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Embryonic stem cells are also used for generation of transgenic organisms. They are obtained from _______ of a developing ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) trophoectoderm, gastrula",
            "b) trophoectoderm, blastula",
            "c) inner cell mass, blastula",
            "d) inner cell mass, gastrula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Embryonic stem cells are also used for generation of transgenic organisms. They are obtained from the inner cell mass of a developing blastula. A developing blastula composes of inner cell mass and it is surrounded by trophoectoderm."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "ES cells are used in order to ensure that insertion is done at the required chromosomal location and it is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gene targeting",
            "b) knocking out",
            "c) knocking in",
            "d) gene disruption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ES cells are isolated and are injected into the blastocoel of the developing embryo. But the embryo is not composed wholly of ES cells and thus it is said to be chimeric."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "If a gene is inactivated by gene targeting then it is called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) knock-in gene",
            "b) knock-out gene",
            "c) gene disruption",
            "d) insertional inactivation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ES cells are used in order to ensure that insertion is done at the required chromosomal location and the process is termed as gene targeting. In some cases, it is not necessary to ensure that integration is taking place at a normal chromosomal location."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Integration events may be insertional involving _____ crossover or replacement involving _____ crossovers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) single, single",
            "b) double, double",
            "c) double, single",
            "d) single, double"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a gene is inactivated by gene targeting then it is called a knock-out gene. If a gene is replaced by some other gene then it is called as knocking in."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "The gene targeting approach produces individuals which are ______ for inactivation of the gene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) homozygous",
            "b) heterozygous",
            "c) either only homozygous or only heterozygous",
            "d) both heterozygous and homozygous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Integration can be done by either insertion or replacement. Insertion is carried out by using single crossover and replacement is carried out by double crossover."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "If controlled inactivation of a gene is carried out and some of the consequences when inactivation of a target gene is deleterious are avoided. It is referred as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) specialized gene targeting",
            "b) controlled gene targeting",
            "c) conditional gene targeting",
            "d) specific gene targeting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is necessary to analyze the genome of transgenic cells to confirm that the site of integration is correct and it is carried out by southern blotting. DNA from cultures derived from individual transformed cells is used for screening."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "For carrying out gene manipulation, the use of cultured cells is _____ transgenic organisms.",
        "Options": [
            "a) less reliable",
            "b) more reliable",
            "c) may be less or more reliable",
            "d) is same reliable as"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The gene targeting approach produces individuals which are heterozygous for inactivation of the gene. But it is necessary to generate homozygotes and they are produced by crossing heterozygous individuals and then screening is carried out."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Amplification of specific region can be done by using primers for specific regions. If the PCR product is ______ and is in sufficient quantity, then sequence can be determined ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) non-specific, directly",
            "b) non-specific, indirectly or directly",
            "c) specific, directly",
            "d) specific, indirectly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amplification of specific region can be done by using primers for specific regions. If the PCR product is specific, it means that only a single band is obtained in gel electrophoresis and is insufficient quantity then the sequence can be determined directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not suitable if the PCR product is non-specific?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adjusting the concentration of magnesium ions",
            "b) Increasing annealing temperature",
            "c) Using touchdown PCR",
            "d) Using inverse PCR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In case, products are non-specific then sequence can’t be known directly. Optimization of PCR should be carried out and various other strategies should be used such as adjusting the concentration of magnesium ions, increasing annealing temperature or using touch-down PCR."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "How many approaches are there in order to clone the complete genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantage of this approach is that there is no permanent record until some of the bacterial cells are preserved. If enough bacteria are there initially then genomic library can be constructed."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "If a full proteomic analysis of growth medium is carried out and is combined with ____________ genome sequence, genes for other _____________ proteins are also obtained.",
        "Options": [
            "a) partial, defensive",
            "b) partial, secreted",
            "c) complete, defensive",
            "d) complete, secreted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are basically two approaches in order to clone the complete genome. In the first approach, systematic cloning is cloned is carried out. The second approach is based on cloning overlapping fragments at random."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "If a putative protein sequence is cloned in an expression vector and the expressed protein is not showing protease activity, then which of the following is not correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The protein is not protease",
            "b) The protein can be incorrectly folded which can block the protease activity",
            "c) There might be some other cofactor required for protease activity",
            "d) The most commonly used expression system is E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If a full proteomic analysis of growth medium is carried out and is combined with complete genome sequence, genes for other secreted proteins can also be obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "For getting a large amount of proteins to crystallize, which of the following should be used as an expression system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacterial system",
            "b) Yeast systems",
            "c) Eukaryotic systems",
            "d) Both eukaryotic and bacterial systems can be used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the putative protein sequence is cloned and the expressed protein is not showing protease activity, it is not necessary that it is not protease. Suppression of protease activity can be because of incorrect folding or that some cofactor is required for protease activity. The most commonly used expression system is E.coli. "
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "The RNA level ___________ the steady-state level of the corresponding protein directly and the post-translational modification of the protein ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) reflects, can be determined",
            "b) reflects, can’t be determined",
            "c) doesn’t necessarily reflects, can be determined",
            "d) doesn’t necessarily reflects, can’t be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The system to be used for getting large amounts of proteins to crystallize can be either bacterial or eukaryotic. It depends on the source of the gene and whether post-translational modification is necessary or not."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "For a convenient transformation system, _____ can be used for gene silencing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) antisense RNA",
            "b) transposon insertion",
            "c) either antisense RNA or transposon insertion",
            "d) transposon insertion followed by antisense RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At times mutated proteins are not expressed well. Mutation perturbs a structure at times and it affects the stability and folding of the protein."
    }
]